Introduction

Welcome!

This guide will teach you about Elixir fundamentals - the language syntax, how to define modules, the common data structures in the language, and more. This chapter will focus on ensuring that Elixir is installed and that you can successfully run Elixir's Interactive Shell, called IEx.

Let's get started.

Installation

If you haven't yet installed Elixir, visit our installation page. Once you are done, you can run elixir --version to get the current Elixir version. The requirements for this guide are:

Elixir 1.15.0 onwards
Erlang/OTP 26 onwards

If you are looking for other resources for learning Elixir, you can also consult the learning page of the official website.

Interactive mode

When you install Elixir, you will have three new command line executables: iex, elixir and elixirc.

For now, let's start by running iex (or iex.bat if you are on Windows PowerShell, where iex is a PowerShell command) which stands for Interactive Elixir. In interactive mode, we can type any Elixir expression and get its result. Let's warm up with some basic expressions.

Open up iex and type the following expressions:

Erlang/OTP 26 [64-bit] [smp:2:2] [...]

Interactive Elixir - press Ctrl+C to exit
iex(1)> 40 + 2
42
iex(2)> "hello" <> " world"
"hello world"

Please note that some details like version numbers may differ a bit in your session, that's not important. By executing the code above, you should evaluate expressions and see their results. To exit iex press Ctrl+C twice.

It seems we are ready to go! We will use the interactive shell quite a lot in the next chapters to get a bit more familiar with the language constructs and basic types, starting in the next chapter.

Running scripts

After getting familiar with the basics of the language you may want to try writing simple programs. This can be accomplished by putting the following Elixir code into a file:

IO.puts("Hello world from Elixir")

Save it as simple.exs and execute it with elixir:

$ elixir simple.exs
Hello world from Elixir

Later on we will learn how to compile Elixir code and how to create and work within Elixir projects using the Mix build tool. For now, let's move on to learn the basic data types in the language.

Code

Utilities for managing code compilation, code evaluation, and code loading.

This module complements Erlang's :code module to add behavior which is specific to Elixir. For functions to manipulate Elixir's AST (rather than evaluating it), see the Macro module.

Working with files

This module contains three functions for compiling and evaluating files. Here is a summary of them and their behavior:

require_file/2 - compiles a file and tracks its name. It does not compile the file again if it has been previously required.

compile_file/2 - compiles a file without tracking its name. Compiles the file multiple times when invoked multiple times.

eval_file/2 - evaluates the file contents without tracking its name. It returns the result of the last expression in the file, instead of the modules defined in it. Evaluated files do not trigger the compilation tracers described in the next section.

In a nutshell, the first must be used when you want to keep track of the files handled by the system, to avoid the same file from being compiled multiple times. This is common in scripts.

compile_file/2 must be used when you are interested in the modules defined in a file, without tracking. eval_file/2 should be used when you are interested in the result of evaluating the file rather than the modules it defines.

The functions above work with Elixir source. If you want to work with modules compiled to bytecode, which have the .beam extension and are typically found below the _build directory of a Mix project, see the functions in Erlang's :code module.

Code loading on the Erlang VM

Erlang has two modes to load code: interactive and embedded.

By default, the Erlang VM runs in interactive mode, where modules are loaded as needed. In embedded mode the opposite happens, as all modules need to be loaded upfront or explicitly.

You can use ensure_loaded/1 (as well as ensure_loaded?/1 and ensure_loaded!/1) to check if a module is loaded before using it and act.

ensure_compiled/1 and ensure_compiled!/1

Elixir also includes ensure_compiled/1 and ensure_compiled!/1 functions that are a superset of ensure_loaded/1.

Since Elixir's compilation happens in parallel, in some situations you may need to use a module that was not yet compiled, therefore it can't even be loaded.

When invoked, ensure_compiled/1 and ensure_compiled!/1 halt the compilation of the caller until the module becomes available. Note that the distinction between ensure_compiled/1 and ensure_compiled!/1 is important: if you are using ensure_compiled!/1, you are indicating to the compiler that you can only continue if said module is available.

If you are using Code.ensure_compiled/1, you are implying you may continue without the module and therefore Elixir may return {:error, :unavailable} for cases where the module is not yet available (but may be available later on).

For those reasons, developers must typically use Code.ensure_compiled!/1. In particular, do not do this:

case Code.ensure_compiled(module) do
  {:module, _} -> module
  {:error, _} -> raise ...
end

Finally, note you only need ensure_compiled!/1 to check for modules being defined within the same project. It does not apply to modules from dependencies as dependencies are always compiled upfront.

In most cases, ensure_loaded/1 is enough. ensure_compiled!/1 must be used in rare cases, usually involving macros that need to invoke a module for callback information. The use of ensure_compiled/1 is even less likely.

Compilation tracers

Elixir supports compilation tracers, which allow modules to observe constructs handled by the Elixir compiler when compiling files. A tracer is a module that implements the trace/2 function. The function receives the event name as first argument and Macro.Env as second and it must return :ok. It is very important for a tracer to do as little work as possible synchronously and dispatch the bulk of the work to a separate process. Slow tracers will slow down compilation.

You can configure your list of tracers via put_compiler_option/2. The following events are available to tracers:

:start - (since v1.11.0) invoked whenever the compiler starts to trace a new lexical context. A lexical context is started when compiling a new file or when defining a module within a function. Note evaluated code does not start a new lexical context (because they don't track unused aliases, imports, etc) but defining a module inside evaluated code will.

Note this event may be emitted in parallel, where multiple files/modules invoke :start and run at the same time. The value of the lexical_tracker of the macro environment, albeit opaque, can be used to uniquely identify the environment.

:stop - (since v1.11.0) invoked whenever the compiler stops tracing a new lexical context, such as a new file.

{:import, meta, module, opts} - traced whenever module is imported. meta is the import AST metadata and opts are the import options.

{:imported_function, meta, module, name, arity} and {:imported_macro, meta, module, name, arity} - traced whenever an imported function or macro is invoked. meta is the call AST metadata, module is the module the import is from, followed by the name and arity of the imported function/macro. A :remote_function/:remote_macro event may still be emitted for the imported module/name/arity.

{:imported_quoted, meta, module, name, [arity]} - traced whenever an imported function or macro is processed inside a quote/2. meta is the call AST metadata, module is the module the import is from, followed by the name and a list of arities of the imported function/macro.

{:alias, meta, alias, as, opts} - traced whenever alias is aliased to as. meta is the alias AST metadata and opts are the alias options.

{:alias_expansion, meta, as, alias} traced whenever there is an alias expansion for a previously defined alias, i.e. when the user writes as which is expanded to alias. meta is the alias expansion AST metadata.

{:alias_reference, meta, module} - traced whenever there is an alias in the code, i.e. whenever the user writes MyModule.Foo.Bar in the code, regardless if it was expanded or not.

{:require, meta, module, opts} - traced whenever module is required. meta is the require AST metadata and opts are the require options. If the meta option contains the :from_macro, then module was called from within a macro and therefore must be treated as a compile-time dependency.

{:struct_expansion, meta, module, keys} - traced whenever module's struct is expanded. meta is the struct AST metadata and keys are the keys being used by expansion

{:remote_function, meta, module, name, arity} and {:remote_macro, meta, module, name, arity} - traced whenever a remote function or macro is referenced. meta is the call AST metadata, module is the invoked module, followed by the name and arity.

{:local_function, meta, name, arity} and {:local_macro, meta, name, arity} - traced whenever a local function or macro is referenced. meta is the call AST metadata, followed by the name and arity.

{:compile_env, app, path, return} - traced whenever Application.compile_env/3 or Application.compile_env!/2 are called. app is an atom, path is a list of keys to traverse in the application environment and return is either {:ok, value} or :error.

:defmodule - (since v1.16.2) traced as soon as the definition of a module starts. This is invoked early on in the module life cycle, Module.open?/1 still returns false for such traces

{:on_module, bytecode, _ignore} - (since v1.13.0) traced whenever a module is defined. This is equivalent to the @after_compile callback and invoked after any @after_compile in the given module. The third element is currently :none but it may provide more metadata in the future. It is best to ignore it at the moment. Note that Module functions expecting not yet compiled modules (such as Module.definitions_in/1) are still available at the time this event is emitted.

The :tracers compiler option can be combined with the :parser_options compiler option to enrich the metadata of the traced events above.

New events may be added at any time in the future, therefore it is advised for the trace/2 function to have a "catch-all" clause.

Below is an example tracer that prints all remote function invocations:

defmodule MyTracer do
  def trace({:remote_function, _meta, module, name, arity}, env) do
    IO.puts("#{env.file}:#{env.line} #{inspect(module)}.#{name}/#{arity}")
    :ok
  end

  def trace(_event, _env) do
    :ok
  end
end

Summary

Types

binding()

A list with all variables and their values.

diagnostic(severity)

Diagnostics returned by the compiler and code evaluation.

line()

The line. 0 indicates no line.

position()

The position of the diagnostic.

Functions

append_path(path, opts \\ [])

Appends a path to the Erlang VM code path list.

append_paths(paths, opts \\ [])

Appends a list of paths to the Erlang VM code path list.

available_compiler_options()

Returns a list with all available compiler options.

can_await_module_compilation?()

Returns true if the current process can await for module compilation.

compile_file(file, relative_to \\ nil)

Compiles the given file.

compile_quoted(quoted, file \\ "nofile")

Compiles the quoted expression.

compile_string(string, file \\ "nofile")

Compiles the given string.

compiler_options()

Gets all compilation options from the code server.

compiler_options(opts)

Stores all given compilation options.

delete_path(path)

Deletes a path from the Erlang VM code path list.

delete_paths(paths)

Deletes a list of paths from the Erlang VM code path list.

ensure_all_loaded(modules)

Ensures the given modules are loaded.

ensure_all_loaded!(modules)

Same as ensure_all_loaded/1 but raises if any of the modules cannot be loaded.

ensure_compiled(module)

Similar to ensure_compiled!/1 but indicates you can continue without said module.

ensure_compiled!(module)

Ensures the given module is compiled and loaded.

ensure_loaded(module)

Ensures the given module is loaded.

ensure_loaded!(module)

Same as ensure_loaded/1 but raises if the module cannot be loaded.

ensure_loaded?(module)

Ensures the given module is loaded.

env_for_eval(env_or_opts)

Returns an environment for evaluation.

eval_file(file, relative_to \\ nil)

Evaluates the given file.

eval_quoted(quoted, binding \\ [], env_or_opts \\ [])

Evaluates the quoted contents.

eval_quoted_with_env(quoted, binding, env, opts \\ [])

Evaluates the given quoted contents with binding and env.

eval_string(string, binding \\ [], opts \\ [])

Evaluates the contents given by string.

fetch_docs(module_or_path)

Returns the docs for the given module or path to .beam file.

format_file!(file, opts \\ [])

Formats a file.

format_string!(string, opts \\ [])

Formats the given code string.

get_compiler_option(key)

Returns the value of a given compiler option.

loaded?(module)

Returns true if the module is loaded.

prepend_path(path, opts \\ [])

Prepends a path to the Erlang VM code path list.

prepend_paths(paths, opts \\ [])

Prepends a list of paths to the Erlang VM code path list.

print_diagnostic(diagnostic, opts \\ [])

Prints a diagnostic into the standard error.

purge_compiler_modules()

Purge compiler modules.

put_compiler_option(key, value)

Stores a compilation option.

quoted_to_algebra(quoted, opts \\ [])

Converts a quoted expression to an algebra document using Elixir's formatter rules.

require_file(file, relative_to \\ nil)

Requires the given file.

required_files()

Lists all required files.

string_to_quoted(string, opts \\ [])

Converts the given string to its quoted form.

string_to_quoted!(string, opts \\ [])

Converts the given string to its quoted form.

string_to_quoted_with_comments(string, opts \\ [])

Converts the given string to its quoted form and a list of comments.

string_to_quoted_with_comments!(string, opts \\ [])

Converts the given string to its quoted form and a list of comments.

unrequire_files(files)

Removes files from the required files list.

with_diagnostics(opts \\ [], fun)

Executes the given fun and capture all diagnostics.

Types

binding()

@type binding() :: [{atom() | tuple(), any()}]

A list with all variables and their values.

The binding keys are usually atoms, but they may be a tuple for variables defined in a different context.

diagnostic(severity)

@type diagnostic(severity) :: %{
  :source => Path.t() | nil,
  :file => Path.t() | nil,
  :severity => severity,
  :message => String.t(),
  :position => position(),
  :stacktrace => Exception.stacktrace(),
  :span => {line :: pos_integer(), column :: pos_integer()} | nil,
  optional(:details) => term(),
  optional(any()) => any()
}

Diagnostics returned by the compiler and code evaluation.

The file and position relate to where the diagnostic should be shown. If there is a file and position, then the diagnostic is precise and you can use the given file and position for generating snippets, IDEs annotations, and so on. An optional span is available with the line and column the diagnostic ends.

Otherwise, a stacktrace may be given, which you can place your own heuristics to provide better reporting.

The source field points to the source file the compiler tracked the error to. For example, a file lib/foo.ex may embed .eex templates from lib/foo/bar.eex. A syntax error on the EEx template will point to file lib/foo/bar.eex but the source is lib/foo.ex.

line()

@type line() :: non_neg_integer()

The line. 0 indicates no line.

position()

@type position() :: line() | {line :: pos_integer(), column :: pos_integer()}

The position of the diagnostic.

Can be either a line number or a {line, column}. Line and columns numbers are one-based. A position of 0 represents unknown.

Functions

append_path(path, opts \\ [])

@spec append_path(Path.t(), [{:cache, boolean()}]) :: true | false

Appends a path to the Erlang VM code path list.

This is the list of directories the Erlang VM uses for finding module code. The list of files is managed per Erlang VM node.

The path is expanded with Path.expand/1 before being appended. It requires the path to exist. Returns a boolean indicating if the path was successfully added.

Examples

Code.append_path(".")
#=> true

Code.append_path("/does_not_exist")
#=> false

Options

:cache - (since v1.15.0) when true, the code path is cached the first time it is traversed in order to reduce file system operations. It requires Erlang/OTP 26, otherwise it is a no-op.

append_paths(paths, opts \\ [])

(since 1.15.0)

@spec append_paths([Path.t()], [{:cache, boolean()}]) :: :ok

Appends a list of paths to the Erlang VM code path list.

This is the list of directories the Erlang VM uses for finding module code. The list of files is managed per Erlang VM node.

All paths are expanded with Path.expand/1 before being appended. Only existing paths are appended. This function always returns :ok, regardless of how many paths were appended. Use append_path/1 if you need more control.

Examples

Code.append_paths([".", "/does_not_exist"])
#=> :ok

Options

:cache - when true, the code path is cached the first time it is traversed in order to reduce file system operations. It requires Erlang/OTP 26, otherwise it is a no-op.

available_compiler_options()

@spec available_compiler_options() :: [atom()]

Returns a list with all available compiler options.

For a description of all options, see put_compiler_option/2.

Examples

Code.available_compiler_options()
#=> [:docs, :debug_info, ...]

can_await_module_compilation?()

(since 1.11.0)

@spec can_await_module_compilation?() :: boolean()

Returns true if the current process can await for module compilation.

When compiling Elixir code via Kernel.ParallelCompiler, which is used by Mix and elixirc, calling a module that has not yet been compiled will block the caller until the module becomes available. Executing Elixir scripts, such as passing a filename to elixir, does not await.

compile_file(file, relative_to \\ nil)

(since 1.7.0)

@spec compile_file(binary(), nil | binary()) :: [{module(), binary()}]

Compiles the given file.

Accepts relative_to as an argument to tell where the file is located.

Returns a list of tuples where the first element is the module name and the second one is its bytecode (as a binary). Opposite to require_file/2, it does not track the filename of the compiled file.

If you would like to get the result of evaluating file rather than the modules defined in it, see eval_file/2.

For compiling many files concurrently, see Kernel.ParallelCompiler.compile/2.

compile_quoted(quoted, file \\ "nofile")

@spec compile_quoted(Macro.t(), binary()) :: [{module(), binary()}]

Compiles the quoted expression.

Returns a list of tuples where the first element is the module name and the second one is its bytecode (as a binary). A file can be given as second argument which will be used for reporting warnings and errors.

compile_string(string, file \\ "nofile")

@spec compile_string(List.Chars.t(), binary()) :: [{module(), binary()}]

Compiles the given string.

Returns a list of tuples where the first element is the module name and the second one is its bytecode (as a binary). A file can be given as a second argument which will be used for reporting warnings and errors.

Warning: string can be any Elixir code and code can be executed with the same privileges as the Erlang VM: this means that such code could compromise the machine (for example by executing system commands). Don't use compile_string/2 with untrusted input (such as strings coming from the network).

compiler_options()

@spec compiler_options() :: map()

Gets all compilation options from the code server.

To get individual options, see get_compiler_option/1. For a description of all options, see put_compiler_option/2.

Examples

Code.compiler_options()
#=> %{debug_info: true, docs: true, ...}

compiler_options(opts)

@spec compiler_options(Enumerable.t({atom(), term()})) :: %{
  optional(atom()) => term()
}

Stores all given compilation options.

Changing the compilation options affect all processes running in a given Erlang VM node. To store individual options and for a description of all options, see put_compiler_option/2.

Returns a map with previous values.

Examples

Code.compiler_options(infer_signatures: false)
#=> %{infer_signatures: true}

delete_path(path)

@spec delete_path(Path.t()) :: boolean()

Deletes a path from the Erlang VM code path list.

This is the list of directories the Erlang VM uses for finding module code. The list of files is managed per Erlang VM node.

The path is expanded with Path.expand/1 before being deleted. If the path does not exist, this function returns false.

Examples

Code.prepend_path(".")
Code.delete_path(".")
#=> true

Code.delete_path("/does_not_exist")
#=> false

delete_paths(paths)

(since 1.15.0)

@spec delete_paths([Path.t()]) :: :ok

Deletes a list of paths from the Erlang VM code path list.

This is the list of directories the Erlang VM uses for finding module code. The list of files is managed per Erlang VM node.

The path is expanded with Path.expand/1 before being deleted. If the path does not exist, this function returns false.

ensure_all_loaded(modules)

(since 1.15.0)

@spec ensure_all_loaded([module()]) :: :ok | {:error, [{module(), reason}]}
when reason: :badfile | :nofile | :on_load_failure

Ensures the given modules are loaded.

Similar to ensure_loaded/1, but accepts a list of modules instead of a single module, and loads all of them.

If all modules load successfully, returns :ok. Otherwise, returns {:error, errors} where errors is a list of tuples made of the module and the reason it failed to load.

Examples

iex> Code.ensure_all_loaded([Atom, String])
:ok

iex> Code.ensure_all_loaded([Atom, DoesNotExist])
{:error, [{DoesNotExist, :nofile}]}

ensure_all_loaded!(modules)

(since 1.15.0)

@spec ensure_all_loaded!([module()]) :: :ok

Same as ensure_all_loaded/1 but raises if any of the modules cannot be loaded.

ensure_compiled(module)

@spec ensure_compiled(module()) ::
  {:module, module()}
  | {:error, :embedded | :badfile | :nofile | :on_load_failure | :unavailable}

Similar to ensure_compiled!/1 but indicates you can continue without said module.

While ensure_compiled!/1 indicates to the Elixir compiler you can only continue when said module is available, this function indicates you may continue compilation without said module.

If it succeeds in loading the module, it returns {:module, module}. If not, returns {:error, reason} with the error reason. If the module being checked is currently in a compiler deadlock, this function returns {:error, :unavailable}. Unavailable doesn't necessarily mean the module doesn't exist, just that it is not currently available, but it (or may not) become available in the future.

Therefore, if you can only continue if the module is available, use ensure_compiled!/1 instead. In particular, do not do this:

case Code.ensure_compiled(module) do
  {:module, _} -> module
  {:error, _} -> raise ...
end

See the module documentation for more information on code loading.

ensure_compiled!(module)

(since 1.12.0)

@spec ensure_compiled!(module()) :: module()

Ensures the given module is compiled and loaded.

If the module is already loaded, it works as no-op. If the module was not compiled yet, ensure_compiled!/1 halts the compilation of the caller until the module given to ensure_compiled!/1 becomes available or all files for the current project have been compiled. If compilation finishes and the module is not available or is in a deadlock, an error is raised.

Given this function halts compilation, use it carefully. In particular, avoid using it to guess which modules are in the system. Overuse of this function can also lead to deadlocks, where two modules check at the same time if the other is compiled. This returns a specific unavailable error code, where we cannot successfully verify a module is available or not.

See the module documentation for more information on code loading.

ensure_loaded(module)

@spec ensure_loaded(module()) ::
  {:module, module()}
  | {:error, :embedded | :badfile | :nofile | :on_load_failure}

Ensures the given module is loaded.

If the module is already loaded, this works as no-op. If the module was not yet loaded, it tries to load it.

If it succeeds in loading the module, it returns {:module, module}. If not, returns {:error, reason} with the error reason.

See the module documentation for more information on code loading.

Examples

iex> Code.ensure_loaded(Atom)
{:module, Atom}

iex> Code.ensure_loaded(DoesNotExist)
{:error, :nofile}

ensure_loaded!(module)

(since 1.12.0)

@spec ensure_loaded!(module()) :: module()

Same as ensure_loaded/1 but raises if the module cannot be loaded.

ensure_loaded?(module)

@spec ensure_loaded?(module()) :: boolean()

Ensures the given module is loaded.

Similar to ensure_loaded/1, but returns true if the module is already loaded or was successfully loaded. Returns false otherwise.

Examples

iex> Code.ensure_loaded?(String)
true

env_for_eval(env_or_opts)

(since 1.14.0)

Returns an environment for evaluation.

It accepts either a Macro.Env, that is then pruned and prepared, or a list of options. It returns an environment that is ready for evaluation.

Most functions in this module will automatically prepare the given environment for evaluation, so you don't need to explicitly call this function, with the exception of eval_quoted_with_env/3, which was designed precisely to be called in a loop, to implement features such as interactive shells or anything else with multiple evaluations.

Options

If an env is not given, the options can be:

:file - the file to be considered in the evaluation

:line - the line on which the script starts

:module - the module to run the environment on

eval_file(file, relative_to \\ nil)

@spec eval_file(binary(), nil | binary()) :: {term(), binding()}

Evaluates the given file.

Accepts relative_to as an argument to tell where the file is located.

While require_file/2 and compile_file/2 return the loaded modules and their bytecode, eval_file/2 simply evaluates the file contents and returns the evaluation result and its binding (exactly the same return value as eval_string/3).

eval_quoted(quoted, binding \\ [], env_or_opts \\ [])

@spec eval_quoted(Macro.t(), binding(), Macro.Env.t() | keyword()) ::
  {term(), binding()}

Evaluates the quoted contents.

Warning: Calling this function inside a macro is considered bad practice as it will attempt to evaluate runtime values at compile time. Macro arguments are typically transformed by unquoting them into the returned quoted expressions (instead of evaluated).

See eval_string/3 for a description of binding and opts.

Examples

iex> contents = quote(do: var!(a) + var!(b))
iex> {result, binding} = Code.eval_quoted(contents, [a: 1, b: 2], file: __ENV__.file, line: __ENV__.line)
iex> result
3
iex> Enum.sort(binding)
[a: 1, b: 2]

For convenience, you can pass __ENV__/0 as the opts argument and all options will be automatically extracted from the current environment:

iex> contents = quote(do: var!(a) + var!(b))
iex> {result, binding} = Code.eval_quoted(contents, [a: 1, b: 2], __ENV__)
iex> result
3
iex> Enum.sort(binding)
[a: 1, b: 2]

eval_quoted_with_env(quoted, binding, env, opts \\ [])

(since 1.14.0)

@spec eval_quoted_with_env(Macro.t(), binding(), Macro.Env.t(), keyword()) ::
  {term(), binding(), Macro.Env.t()}

Evaluates the given quoted contents with binding and env.

This function is meant to be called in a loop, to implement features such as interactive shells or anything else with multiple evaluations. Therefore, the first time you call this function, you must compute the initial environment with env_for_eval/1. The remaining calls must pass the environment that was returned by this function.

Options

:prune_binding - (since v1.14.2) prune binding to keep only variables read or written by the evaluated code. Note that variables used by modules are always pruned, even if later used by the modules. You can submit to the :on_module tracer event and access the variables used by the module from its environment.

eval_string(string, binding \\ [], opts \\ [])

@spec eval_string(List.Chars.t(), binding(), Macro.Env.t() | keyword()) ::
  {term(), binding()}

Evaluates the contents given by string.

The binding argument is a list of all variables and their values. The opts argument is a keyword list of environment options.

Warning: string can be any Elixir code and will be executed with the same privileges as the Erlang VM: this means that such code could compromise the machine (for example by executing system commands). Don't use eval_string/3 with untrusted input (such as strings coming from the network).

Options

It accepts the same options as env_for_eval/1. Additionally, you may also pass an environment as second argument, so the evaluation happens within that environment.

Returns a tuple of the form {value, binding}, where value is the value returned from evaluating string. If an error occurs while evaluating string, an exception will be raised.

binding is a list with all variable names and their values after evaluating string. The binding keys are usually atoms, but they may be a tuple for variables defined in a different context. The names are in no particular order.

Examples

iex> {result, binding} = Code.eval_string("a + b", [a: 1, b: 2], file: __ENV__.file, line: __ENV__.line)
iex> result
3
iex> Enum.sort(binding)
[a: 1, b: 2]

iex> {result, binding} = Code.eval_string("c = a + b", [a: 1, b: 2], __ENV__)
iex> result
3
iex> Enum.sort(binding)
[a: 1, b: 2, c: 3]

iex> {result, binding} = Code.eval_string("a = a + b", [a: 1, b: 2])
iex> result
3
iex> Enum.sort(binding)
[a: 3, b: 2]

For convenience, you can pass __ENV__/0 as the opts argument and all imports, requires and aliases defined in the current environment will be automatically carried over:

iex> {result, binding} = Code.eval_string("a + b", [a: 1, b: 2], __ENV__)
iex> result
3
iex> Enum.sort(binding)
[a: 1, b: 2]

fetch_docs(module_or_path)

(since 1.7.0)

@spec fetch_docs(module() | String.t()) ::
  {:docs_v1, annotation, beam_language, format, module_doc :: doc_content,
   metadata, docs :: [doc_element]}
  | {:error,
     :module_not_found
     | :chunk_not_found
     | {:invalid_chunk, binary()}
     | :invalid_beam}
when annotation: :erl_anno.anno(),
     beam_language: :elixir | :erlang | atom(),
     doc_content: %{optional(binary()) => binary()} | :none | :hidden,
     doc_element:
       {{kind :: atom(), function_name :: atom(), arity()}, annotation,
        signature, doc_content, metadata},
     format: binary(),
     signature: [binary()],
     metadata: map()

Returns the docs for the given module or path to .beam file.

When given a module name, it finds its BEAM code and reads the docs from it.

When given a path to a .beam file, it will load the docs directly from that file.

It returns the term stored in the documentation chunk in the format defined by EEP 48 or {:error, reason} if the chunk is not available.

Examples

# Module documentation of an existing module
iex> {:docs_v1, _, :elixir, _, %{"en" => module_doc}, _, _} = Code.fetch_docs(Atom)
iex> module_doc |> String.split("\n") |> Enum.at(0)
"Atoms are constants whose values are their own name."

# A module that doesn't exist
iex> Code.fetch_docs(ModuleNotGood)
{:error, :module_not_found}

format_file!(file, opts \\ [])

(since 1.6.0)

@spec format_file!(
  binary(),
  keyword()
) :: iodata()

Formats a file.

See format_string!/2 for more information on code formatting and available options.

format_string!(string, opts \\ [])

(since 1.6.0)

@spec format_string!(
  binary(),
  keyword()
) :: iodata()

Formats the given code string.

The formatter receives a string representing Elixir code and returns iodata representing the formatted code according to pre-defined rules.

Options

Regular options (do not change the AST):

:file - the file which contains the string, used for error reporting

:line - the line the string starts, used for error reporting

:line_length - the line length to aim for when formatting the document. Defaults to 98. This value indicates when an expression should be broken over multiple lines but it is not guaranteed to do so. See the "Line length" section below for more information

:locals_without_parens - a keyword list of name and arity pairs that should be kept without parens whenever possible. The arity may be the atom :*, which implies all arities of that name. The formatter already includes a list of functions and this option augments this list.

:force_do_end_blocks (since v1.9.0) - when true, converts all inline usages of do: ..., else: ... and friends into do-end blocks. Defaults to false. Note that this option is convergent: once you set it to true, all keywords will be converted. If you set it to false later on, do-end blocks won't be converted back to keywords.

Migration options (change the AST), see the "Migration formatting" section below:

:migrate (since v1.18.0) - when true, sets all other migration options to true by default. Defaults to false.

:migrate_bitstring_modifiers (since v1.18.0) - when true, removes unnecessary parentheses in known bitstring modifiers, for example <<foo::binary()>> becomes <<foo::binary>>, or adds parentheses for custom modifiers, where <<foo::custom_type>> becomes <<foo::custom_type()>>. Defaults to the value of the :migrate option. This option changes the AST.

:migrate_charlists_as_sigils (since v1.18.0) - when true, formats charlists as ~c sigils, for example 'foo' becomes ~c"foo". Defaults to the value of the :migrate option. This option changes the AST.

:migrate_unless (since v1.18.0) - when true, rewrites unless expressions using if with a negated condition, for example unless foo, do: becomes if !foo, do:. Defaults to the value of the :migrate option. This option changes the AST.

Design principles

The formatter was designed under three principles.

First, the formatter never changes the semantics of the code by default. This means the input AST and the output AST are almost always equivalent.

The second principle is to provide as little configuration as possible. This eases the formatter adoption by removing contention points while making sure a single style is followed consistently by the community as a whole.

The formatter does not hard code names. The formatter will not behave specially because a function is named defmodule, def, or the like. This principle mirrors Elixir's goal of being an extensible language where developers can extend the language with new constructs as if they were part of the language. When it is absolutely necessary to change behavior based on the name, this behavior should be configurable, such as the :locals_without_parens option.

Running the formatter

The formatter attempts to fit the most it can on a single line and introduces line breaks wherever possible when it cannot.

In some cases, this may lead to undesired formatting. Therefore, some code generated by the formatter may not be aesthetically pleasing and may require explicit intervention from the developer. That's why we do not recommend to run the formatter blindly in an existing codebase. Instead you should format and sanity check each formatted file.

For example, the formatter may break a long function definition over multiple clauses:

def my_function(
  %User{name: name, age: age, ...},
  arg1,
  arg2
) do
  ...
end

While the code above is completely valid, you may prefer to match on the struct variables inside the function body in order to keep the definition on a single line:

def my_function(%User{} = user, arg1, arg2) do
  %{name: name, age: age, ...} = user
  ...
end

In some situations, you can use the fact the formatter does not generate elegant code as a hint for refactoring. Take this code:

def board?(board_id, %User{} = user, available_permissions, required_permissions) do
  Tracker.OrganizationMembers.user_in_organization?(user.id, board.organization_id) and
    required_permissions == Enum.to_list(MapSet.intersection(MapSet.new(required_permissions), MapSet.new(available_permissions)))
end

The code above has very long lines and running the formatter is not going to address this issue. In fact, the formatter may make it more obvious that you have complex expressions:

def board?(board_id, %User{} = user, available_permissions, required_permissions) do
  Tracker.OrganizationMembers.user_in_organization?(user.id, board.organization_id) and
    required_permissions ==
      Enum.to_list(
        MapSet.intersection(
          MapSet.new(required_permissions),
          MapSet.new(available_permissions)
        )
      )
end

Take such cases as a suggestion that your code should be refactored:

def board?(board_id, %User{} = user, available_permissions, required_permissions) do
  Tracker.OrganizationMembers.user_in_organization?(user.id, board.organization_id) and
    matching_permissions?(required_permissions, available_permissions)
end

defp matching_permissions?(required_permissions, available_permissions) do
  intersection =
    required_permissions
    |> MapSet.new()
    |> MapSet.intersection(MapSet.new(available_permissions))
    |> Enum.to_list()

  required_permissions == intersection
end

To sum it up: since the formatter cannot change the semantics of your code, sometimes it is necessary to tweak or refactor the code to get optimal formatting. To help better understand how to control the formatter, we describe in the next sections the cases where the formatter keeps the user encoding and how to control multiline expressions.

Line length

Another point about the formatter is that the :line_length configuration indicates when an expression should be broken over multiple lines but it is not guaranteed to do so. In many cases, it is not possible for the formatter to break your code apart, which means it will go over the line length. For example, if you have a long string:

"this is a very long string that will go over the line length"

The formatter doesn't know how to break it apart without changing the code underlying syntax representation, so it is up to you to step in:

"this is a very long string " <>
   "that will go over the line length"

The string concatenation makes the code fit on a single line and also gives more options to the formatter.

This may also appear in keywords such as do/end blocks and operators, where the do keyword may go over the line length because there is no opportunity for the formatter to introduce a line break in a readable way. For example, if you do:

case very_long_expression() do
end

And only the do keyword is beyond the line length, Elixir will not emit this:

case very_long_expression()
do
end

So it prefers to not touch the line at all and leave do above the line limit.

Keeping user's formatting

The formatter respects the input format in some cases. Those are listed below:

Insignificant digits in numbers are kept as is. The formatter, however, always inserts underscores for decimal numbers with more than 5 digits and converts hexadecimal digits to uppercase

Strings, charlists, atoms and sigils are kept as is. No character is automatically escaped or unescaped. The choice of delimiter is also respected from the input

Newlines inside blocks are kept as in the input except for:

expressions that take multiple lines will always have an empty line before and after and 2) empty lines are always squeezed together into a single empty line

The choice between :do keyword and do-end blocks is left to the user

Lists, tuples, bitstrings, maps, structs and function calls will be broken into multiple lines if they are followed by a newline in the opening bracket and preceded by a new line in the closing bracket

Newlines before certain operators (such as the pipeline operators) and before other operators (such as comparison operators)

The behaviors above are not guaranteed. We may remove or add new rules in the future. The goal of documenting them is to provide better understanding on what to expect from the formatter.

Multi-line lists, maps, tuples, and the like

You can force lists, tuples, bitstrings, maps, structs and function calls to have one entry per line by adding a newline after the opening bracket and a new line before the closing bracket lines. For example:

[
  foo,
  bar
]

If there are no newlines around the brackets, then the formatter will try to fit everything on a single line, such that the snippet below

[foo,
 bar]

will be formatted as

[foo, bar]

You can also force function calls and keywords to be rendered on multiple lines by having each entry on its own line:

defstruct name: nil,
          age: 0

The code above will be kept with one keyword entry per line by the formatter. To avoid that, just squash everything into a single line.

Parens and no parens in function calls

Elixir has two syntaxes for function calls. With parens and no parens. By default, Elixir will add parens to all calls except for:

calls that have do-end blocks
local calls without parens where the name and arity of the local call is also listed under :locals_without_parens (except for calls with arity 0, where the compiler always require parens)

The choice of parens and no parens also affects indentation. When a function call with parens doesn't fit on the same line, the formatter introduces a newline around parens and indents the arguments with two spaces:

some_call(
  arg1,
  arg2,
  arg3
)

On the other hand, function calls without parens are always indented by the function call length itself, like this:

some_call arg1,
          arg2,
          arg3

If the last argument is a data structure, such as maps and lists, and the beginning of the data structure fits on the same line as the function call, then no indentation happens, this allows code like this:

Enum.reduce(some_collection, initial_value, fn element, acc ->
  # code
end)

some_function_without_parens %{
  foo: :bar,
  baz: :bat
}

Code comments

The formatter handles code comments and guarantees a space is always added between the beginning of the comment (#) and the next character.

The formatter also extracts all trailing comments to their previous line. For example, the code below

hello #world

will be rewritten to

# world
hello

While the formatter attempts to preserve comments in most situations, that's not always possible, because code comments are handled apart from the code representation (AST). While the formatter can preserve code comments between expressions and function arguments, the formatter cannot currently preserve them around operators. For example, the following code will move the code comments to before the operator usage:

foo() ||
  # also check for bar
  bar()

In some situations, code comments can be seen as ambiguous by the formatter. For example, the comment in the anonymous function below

fn
  arg1 ->
    body1
    # comment

  arg2 ->
    body2
end

and in this one

fn
  arg1 ->
    body1

  # comment
  arg2 ->
    body2
end

are considered equivalent (the nesting is discarded alongside most of user formatting). In such cases, the code formatter will always format to the latter.

Newlines

The formatter converts all newlines in code from \r\n to \n.

Migration formatting

As part of the Elixir release cycle, deprecations are being introduced, emitting warnings which might require existing code to be changed. In order to reduce the burden on developers when upgrading Elixir to the next version, the formatter exposes some options, disabled by default, in order to automate this process.

These options should address most of the typical use cases, but given they introduce changes to the AST, there is a non-zero risk for meta-programming heavy projects that relied on a specific AST, or projects that are re-defining functions from the Kernel. In such cases, migrations cannot be applied blindly and some extra changes might be needed in order to address the deprecation warnings.

get_compiler_option(key)

(since 1.10.0)

@spec get_compiler_option(atom()) :: term()

Returns the value of a given compiler option.

For a description of all options, see put_compiler_option/2.

Examples

Code.get_compiler_option(:debug_info)
#=> true

loaded?(module)

(since 1.15.0)

@spec loaded?(module()) :: boolean()

Returns true if the module is loaded.

This function doesn't attempt to load the module. For such behavior, ensure_loaded?/1 can be used.

Examples

iex> Code.loaded?(Atom)
true

iex> Code.loaded?(NotYetLoaded)
false

prepend_path(path, opts \\ [])

@spec prepend_path(Path.t(), [{:cache, boolean()}]) :: boolean()

Prepends a path to the Erlang VM code path list.

This is the list of directories the Erlang VM uses for finding module code. The list of files is managed per Erlang VM node.

The path is expanded with Path.expand/1 before being prepended. It requires the path to exist. Returns a boolean indicating if the path was successfully added.

Examples

Code.prepend_path(".")
#=> true

Code.prepend_path("/does_not_exist")
#=> false

Options

:cache - (since v1.15.0) when true, the code path is cached the first time it is traversed in order to reduce file system operations. It requires Erlang/OTP 26, otherwise it is a no-op.

prepend_paths(paths, opts \\ [])

(since 1.15.0)

@spec prepend_paths([Path.t()], [{:cache, boolean()}]) :: :ok

Prepends a list of paths to the Erlang VM code path list.

This is the list of directories the Erlang VM uses for finding module code. The list of files is managed per Erlang VM node.

All paths are expanded with Path.expand/1 before being prepended. Only existing paths are prepended. This function always returns :ok, regardless of how many paths were prepended. Use prepend_path/1 if you need more control.

Examples

Code.prepend_paths([".", "/does_not_exist"])
#=> :ok

Options

:cache - when true, the code path is cached the first time it is traversed in order to reduce file system operations. It requires Erlang/OTP 26, otherwise it is a no-op.

print_diagnostic(diagnostic, opts \\ [])

(since 1.15.0)

@spec print_diagnostic(
  diagnostic(:warning | :error),
  keyword()
) :: :ok

Prints a diagnostic into the standard error.

A diagnostic is either returned by Kernel.ParallelCompiler or by Code.with_diagnostics/2.

Options

:snippet - whether to read the code snippet in the diagnostic location. As it may impact performance, it is not recommended to be used in runtime. Defaults to true.

purge_compiler_modules()

(since 1.7.0)

@spec purge_compiler_modules() :: {:ok, non_neg_integer()}

Purge compiler modules.

The compiler utilizes temporary modules to compile code. For example, elixir_compiler_1, elixir_compiler_2, and so on. In case the compiled code stores references to anonymous functions or similar, the Elixir compiler may be unable to reclaim those modules, keeping an unnecessary amount of code in memory and eventually leading to modules such as elixir_compiler_12345.

This function purges all modules currently kept by the compiler, allowing old compiler module names to be reused. If there are any processes running any code from such modules, they will be terminated too.

This function is only meant to be called if you have a long running node that is constantly evaluating code.

It returns {:ok, number_of_modules_purged}.

put_compiler_option(key, value)

(since 1.10.0)

@spec put_compiler_option(atom(), term()) :: :ok

Stores a compilation option.

Changing the compilation options affect all processes running in a given Erlang VM node.

Available options are:

:docs - when true, retains documentation in the compiled module. Defaults to true.

:debug_info - when true, retains debug information in the compiled module. This option can also be overridden per module using the @compile directive. Defaults to true.

This enables tooling to partially reconstruct the original source code, for instance, to perform static analysis of code. Therefore, disabling :debug_info is not recommended as it removes the ability of the Elixir compiler and other tools to provide feedback. If you want to remove the :debug_info while deploying, tools like mix release already do such by default.

Other environments, such as mix test, automatically disables this via the :test_elixirc_options project configuration, as there is typically no need to store debug chunks for test files.

:ignore_already_consolidated (since v1.10.0) - when true, does not warn when a protocol has already been consolidated and a new implementation is added. Defaults to false.

:ignore_module_conflict - when true, does not warn when a module has already been defined. Defaults to false.

:infer_signatures (since v1.18.0) - when false, it disables module-local signature inference used when type checking remote calls to the compiled module. Type checking will be executed regardless of the value of this option. Defaults to true.

mix test automatically disables this option via the :test_elixirc_options project configuration, as there is typically no need to store infer signatures for test files.

:relative_paths - when true, uses relative paths in quoted nodes, warnings, and errors generated by the compiler. Note disabling this option won't affect runtime warnings and errors. Defaults to true.

:no_warn_undefined (since v1.10.0) - list of modules and {Mod, fun, arity} tuples that will not emit warnings that the module or function does not exist at compilation time. Pass atom :all to skip warning for all undefined functions. This can be useful when doing dynamic compilation. Defaults to [].

:tracers (since v1.10.0) - a list of tracers (modules) to be used during compilation. See the module docs for more information. Defaults to [].

:parser_options (since v1.10.0) - a keyword list of options to be given to the parser when compiling files. It accepts the same options as string_to_quoted/2 (except by the options that change the AST itself). This can be used in combination with the tracer to retrieve localized information about events happening during compilation. Defaults to [columns: true]. This option only affects code compilation functions, such as compile_string/2 and compile_file/2 but not string_to_quoted/2 and friends, as the latter is used for other purposes beyond compilation.

:on_undefined_variable (since v1.15.0) - either :raise or :warn. When :raise (the default), undefined variables will trigger a compilation error. You may be set it to :warn if you want undefined variables to emit a warning and expand as to a local call to the zero-arity function of the same name (for example, node would be expanded as node()). This :warn behavior only exists for compatibility reasons when working with old dependencies, its usage is discouraged and it will be removed in future releases.

It always returns :ok. Raises an error for invalid options.

Examples

Code.put_compiler_option(:debug_info, true)
#=> :ok

quoted_to_algebra(quoted, opts \\ [])

(since 1.13.0)

@spec quoted_to_algebra(
  Macro.t(),
  keyword()
) :: Inspect.Algebra.t()

Converts a quoted expression to an algebra document using Elixir's formatter rules.

The algebra document can be converted into a string by calling:

doc
|> Inspect.Algebra.format(:infinity)
|> IO.iodata_to_binary()

For a high-level function that does the same, see Macro.to_string/1.

Formatting considerations

The Elixir AST does not contain metadata for literals like strings, lists, or tuples with two elements, which means that the produced algebra document will not respect all of the user preferences and comments may be misplaced. To get better results, you can use the :token_metadata, :unescape and :literal_encoder options to string_to_quoted/2 to provide additional information to the formatter:

[
  literal_encoder: &{:ok, {:__block__, &2, [&1]}},
  token_metadata: true,
  unescape: false
]

This will produce an AST that contains information such as do blocks start and end lines or sigil delimiters, and by wrapping literals in blocks they can now hold metadata like line number, string delimiter and escaped sequences, or integer formatting (such as 0x2a instead of 47). However, note this AST is not valid. If you evaluate it, it won't have the same semantics as the regular Elixir AST due to the :unescape and :literal_encoder options. However, those options are useful if you're doing source code manipulation, where it's important to preserve user choices and comments placing.

Options

:comments - the list of comments associated with the quoted expression. Defaults to []. It is recommended that both :token_metadata and :literal_encoder options are given to string_to_quoted_with_comments/2 in order to get proper placement for comments

:escape - when true, escaped sequences like \n will be escaped into \\n. If the :unescape option was set to false when using string_to_quoted/2, setting this option to false will prevent it from escaping the sequences twice. Defaults to true.

:locals_without_parens - a keyword list of name and arity pairs that should be kept without parens whenever possible. The arity may be the atom :*, which implies all arities of that name. The formatter already includes a list of functions and this option augments this list.

:syntax_colors - a keyword list of colors the output is colorized. See Inspect.Opts for more information.

require_file(file, relative_to \\ nil)

@spec require_file(binary(), nil | binary()) :: [{module(), binary()}] | nil

Requires the given file.

Accepts relative_to as an argument to tell where the file is located. If the file was already required, require_file/2 doesn't do anything and returns nil.

Note that if require_file/2 is invoked by different processes concurrently, the first process to invoke require_file/2 acquires a lock and the remaining ones will block until the file is available. This means that if require_file/2 is called more than once with a given file, that file will be compiled only once. The first process to call require_file/2 will get the list of loaded modules, others will get nil. The list of required files is managed per Erlang VM node.

See compile_file/2 if you would like to compile a file without tracking its filenames. Finally, if you would like to get the result of evaluating a file rather than the modules defined in it, see eval_file/2.

Examples

If the file has not been required, it returns the list of modules:

modules = Code.require_file("eex_test.exs", "../eex/test")
List.first(modules)
#=> {EExTest.Compiled, <<70, 79, 82, 49, ...>>}

If the file has been required, it returns nil:

Code.require_file("eex_test.exs", "../eex/test")
#=> nil

required_files()

(since 1.7.0)

@spec required_files() :: [binary()]

Lists all required files.

Examples

Code.require_file("../eex/test/eex_test.exs")
List.first(Code.required_files()) =~ "eex_test.exs"
#=> true

string_to_quoted(string, opts \\ [])

@spec string_to_quoted(
  List.Chars.t(),
  keyword()
) ::
  {:ok, Macro.t()}
  | {:error, {location :: keyword(), binary() | {binary(), binary()}, binary()}}

Converts the given string to its quoted form.

Returns {:ok, quoted_form} if it succeeds, {:error, {meta, message_info, token}} otherwise.

Options

:file - the filename to be reported in case of parsing errors. Defaults to "nofile".

:line - the starting line of the string being parsed. Defaults to 1.

:column - (since v1.11.0) the starting column of the string being parsed. Defaults to 1.

:columns - when true, attach a :column key to the quoted metadata. Defaults to false.

:unescape (since v1.10.0) - when false, preserves escaped sequences. For example, "null byte\\t\\x00" will be kept as is instead of being converted to a bitstring literal. Note if you set this option to false, the resulting AST is no longer valid, but it can be useful to analyze/transform source code, typically in combination with quoted_to_algebra/2. Defaults to true.

:existing_atoms_only - when true, raises an error when non-existing atoms are found by the tokenizer. Defaults to false.

:token_metadata (since v1.10.0) - when true, includes token-related metadata in the expression AST, such as metadata for do and end tokens, for closing tokens, end of expressions, as well as delimiters for sigils. See Macro.metadata/0. Defaults to false.

:literal_encoder (since v1.10.0) - how to encode literals in the AST. It must be a function that receives two arguments, the literal and its metadata, and it must return {:ok, ast :: Macro.t} or {:error, reason :: binary}. If you return anything than the literal itself as the term, then the AST is no longer valid. This option may still useful for textual analysis of the source code.

:static_atoms_encoder - the static atom encoder function, see "The :static_atoms_encoder function" section below. Note this option overrides the :existing_atoms_only behavior for static atoms but :existing_atoms_only is still used for dynamic atoms, such as atoms with interpolations.

:emit_warnings (since v1.16.0) - when false, does not emit tokenizing/parsing related warnings. Defaults to true.

Macro.to_string/2

The opposite of converting a string to its quoted form is Macro.to_string/2, which converts a quoted form to a string/binary representation.

The :static_atoms_encoder function

When static_atoms_encoder: &my_encoder/2 is passed as an argument, my_encoder/2 is called every time the tokenizer needs to create a "static" atom. Static atoms are atoms in the AST that function as aliases, remote calls, local calls, variable names, regular atoms and keyword lists.

The encoder function will receive the atom name (as a binary) and a keyword list with the current file, line and column. It must return {:ok, token :: term} | {:error, reason :: binary}.

The encoder function is supposed to create an atom from the given string. To produce a valid AST, it is required to return {:ok, term}, where term is an atom. It is possible to return something other than an atom, however, in that case the AST is no longer "valid" in that it cannot be used to compile or evaluate Elixir code. A use case for this is if you want to use the Elixir parser in a user-facing situation, but you don't want to exhaust the atom table.

The atom encoder is not called for all atoms that are present in the AST. It won't be invoked for the following atoms:

operators (:+, :-, and so on)

syntax keywords (fn, do, else, and so on)

atoms containing interpolation (:"#{1 + 1} is two"), as these atoms are constructed at runtime

atoms used to represent single-letter sigils like :sigil_X (but multi-letter sigils like :sigil_XYZ are encoded).

string_to_quoted!(string, opts \\ [])

@spec string_to_quoted!(
  List.Chars.t(),
  keyword()
) :: Macro.t()

Converts the given string to its quoted form.

It returns the AST if it succeeds, raises an exception otherwise. The exception is a TokenMissingError in case a token is missing (usually because the expression is incomplete), MismatchedDelimiterError (in case of mismatched opening and closing delimiters) and SyntaxError otherwise.

Check string_to_quoted/2 for options information.

string_to_quoted_with_comments(string, opts \\ [])

(since 1.13.0)

@spec string_to_quoted_with_comments(
  List.Chars.t(),
  keyword()
) ::
  {:ok, Macro.t(), [map()]} | {:error, {location :: keyword(), term(), term()}}

Converts the given string to its quoted form and a list of comments.

This function is useful when performing textual changes to the source code, while preserving information like comments and literals position.

Returns {:ok, quoted_form, comments} if it succeeds, {:error, {line, error, token}} otherwise.

Comments are maps with the following fields:

:line - The line number of the source code

:text - The full text of the comment, including the leading #

:previous_eol_count - How many end of lines there are between the comment and the previous AST node or comment

:next_eol_count - How many end of lines there are between the comment and the next AST node or comment

Check string_to_quoted/2 for options information.

Examples

iex> Code.string_to_quoted_with_comments("""
...> :foo
...>
...> # Hello, world!
...>
...>
...> # Some more comments!
...> """)
{:ok, :foo, [
  %{line: 3, column: 1, previous_eol_count: 2, next_eol_count: 3, text: "# Hello, world!"},
  %{line: 6, column: 1, previous_eol_count: 3, next_eol_count: 1, text: "# Some more comments!"},
]}

iex> Code.string_to_quoted_with_comments(":foo # :bar")
{:ok, :foo, [
  %{line: 1, column: 6, previous_eol_count: 0, next_eol_count: 0, text: "# :bar"}
]}

string_to_quoted_with_comments!(string, opts \\ [])

(since 1.13.0)

@spec string_to_quoted_with_comments!(
  List.Chars.t(),
  keyword()
) :: {Macro.t(), [map()]}

Converts the given string to its quoted form and a list of comments.

Returns the AST and a list of comments if it succeeds, raises an exception otherwise. The exception is a TokenMissingError in case a token is missing (usually because the expression is incomplete), SyntaxError otherwise.

Check string_to_quoted/2 for options information.

unrequire_files(files)

(since 1.7.0)

@spec unrequire_files([binary()]) :: :ok

Removes files from the required files list.

The modules defined in the file are not removed; calling this function only removes them from the list, allowing them to be required again.

The list of files is managed per Erlang VM node.

Examples

# Require EEx test code
Code.require_file("../eex/test/eex_test.exs")

# Now unrequire all files
Code.unrequire_files(Code.required_files())

# Note that modules are still available
function_exported?(EExTest.Compiled, :before_compile, 0)
#=> true

with_diagnostics(opts \\ [], fun)

(since 1.15.0)

@spec with_diagnostics(
  keyword(),
  (-> result)
) :: {result, [diagnostic(:warning | :error)]}
when result: term()

Executes the given fun and capture all diagnostics.

Diagnostics are warnings and errors emitted during code evaluation or single-file compilation and by functions such as IO.warn/2.

If using mix compile or Kernel.ParallelCompiler, note they already capture and return diagnostics.

Options

:log - if the diagnostics should be logged as they happen. Defaults to false.

Rescuing errors

with_diagnostics/2 does not automatically handle exceptions. You may capture them by adding a try/1 in fun:

{result, all_errors_and_warnings} =
  Code.with_diagnostics(fn ->
    try do
      {:ok, Code.compile_quoted(quoted)}
    rescue
      err -> {:error, err}
    end
  end)

DateTime

A datetime implementation with a time zone.

This datetime can be seen as a snapshot of a date and time at a given time zone. For such purposes, it also includes both UTC and Standard offsets, as well as the zone abbreviation field used exclusively for formatting purposes. Note future datetimes are not necessarily guaranteed to exist, as time zones may change any time in the future due to geopolitical reasons. See the "Datetimes as snapshots" section for more information.

Remember, comparisons in Elixir using ==/2, >/2, </2 and friends are structural and based on the DateTime struct fields. For proper comparison between datetimes, use the compare/2 function. The existence of the compare/2 function in this module also allows using Enum.min/2 and Enum.max/2 functions to get the minimum and maximum datetime of an Enum. For example:

iex> Enum.min([~U[2022-01-12 00:01:00.00Z], ~U[2021-01-12 00:01:00.00Z]], DateTime)
~U[2021-01-12 00:01:00.00Z]

Developers should avoid creating the DateTime struct directly and instead rely on the functions provided by this module as well as the ones in third-party calendar libraries.

Time zone database

Many functions in this module require a time zone database. A time zone database is a record of the UTC offsets that its locales have used at various times in the past, are using, and are expected to use in the future. Because those plans can change, it needs to be periodically updated.

By default, DateTime uses the default time zone database returned by Calendar.get_time_zone_database/0, which defaults to Calendar.UTCOnlyTimeZoneDatabase which only handles "Etc/UTC" datetimes and returns {:error, :utc_only_time_zone_database} for any other time zone.

Other time zone databases can also be configured. Here are some available options and libraries:

time_zone_info
tz
tzdata
zoneinfo - recommended for embedded devices

To use one of them, first make sure it is added as a dependency in mix.exs. It can then be configured either via configuration:

config :elixir, :time_zone_database, Tz.TimeZoneDatabase

or by calling Calendar.put_time_zone_database/1:

Calendar.put_time_zone_database(Tz.TimeZoneDatabase)

See the proper names in the library installation instructions.

Datetimes as snapshots

In the first section, we described datetimes as a "snapshot of a date and time at a given time zone". To understand precisely what we mean, let's see an example.

Imagine someone in Poland who wants to schedule a meeting with someone in Brazil in the next year. The meeting will happen at 2:30 AM in the Polish time zone. At what time will the meeting happen in Brazil?

You can consult the time zone database today, one year before, using the API in this module and it will give you an answer that is valid right now. However, this answer may not be valid in the future. Why? Because both Brazil and Poland may change their timezone rules, ultimately affecting the result. For example, a country may choose to enter or abandon "Daylight Saving Time", which is a process where we adjust the clock one hour forward or one hour back once per year. Whenever the rules change, the exact instant that 2:30 AM in Polish time will be in Brazil may change.

In other words, whenever working with future DateTimes, there is no guarantee the results you get will always be correct, until the event actually happens. Therefore, when you ask for a future time, the answers you get are a snapshot that reflects the current state of the time zone rules. For datetimes in the past, this is not a problem, because time zone rules do not change for past events.

To make matters worse, it may be that 2:30 AM in Polish time does not actually even exist or it is ambiguous. If a certain time zone observes "Daylight Saving Time", they will move their clock forward once a year. When this happens, there is a whole hour that does not exist. Then, when they move the clock back, there is a certain hour that will happen twice. So if you want to schedule a meeting when this shift back happens, you would need to explicitly say which occurrence of 2:30 AM you mean: the one in "Summer Time", which occurs before the shift, or the one in "Standard Time", which occurs after it. Applications that are date and time sensitive need to take these scenarios into account and correctly communicate them to users.

The good news is: Elixir contains all of the building blocks necessary to tackle those problems. The default timezone database used by Elixir, Calendar.UTCOnlyTimeZoneDatabase, only works with UTC, which does not observe those issues. Once you bring a proper time zone database, the functions in this module will query the database and return the relevant information. For example, look at how DateTime.new/4 returns different results based on the scenarios described in this section.

Converting between timezones

Bearing in mind the cautions above, and assuming you've brought in a full timezone database, here are some examples of common shifts between time zones.

# Local time to UTC
new_york = DateTime.from_naive!(~N[2023-06-26T09:30:00], "America/New_York")
#=> #DateTime<2023-06-26 09:30:00-04:00 EDT America/New_York>

utc = DateTime.shift_zone!(new_york, "Etc/UTC")
#=> ~U[2023-06-26 13:30:00Z]

# UTC to local time
DateTime.shift_zone!(utc, "Europe/Paris")
#=> #DateTime<2023-06-26 15:30:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Paris>

Summary

Types

t()

Functions

add(datetime, amount_to_add, unit \\ :second, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Adds a specified amount of time to a DateTime.

after?(datetime1, datetime2)

Returns true if the first datetime is strictly later than the second.

before?(datetime1, datetime2)

Returns true if the first datetime is strictly earlier than the second.

compare(datetime1, datetime2)

Compares two datetime structs.

convert(datetime, calendar)

Converts a given datetime from one calendar to another.

convert!(datetime, calendar)

Converts a given datetime from one calendar to another.

diff(datetime1, datetime2, unit \\ :second)

Subtracts datetime2 from datetime1.

from_gregorian_seconds(seconds, arg \\ {0, 0}, calendar \\ Calendar.ISO)

Converts a number of gregorian seconds to a DateTime struct.

from_iso8601(string, format_or_calendar \\ Calendar.ISO)

Parses the extended "Date and time of day" format described by ISO 8601:2019.

from_iso8601(string, calendar, format)

Converts from ISO8601 specifying both a calendar and a mode.

from_naive(naive_datetime, time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Converts the given NaiveDateTime to DateTime.

from_naive!(naive_datetime, time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Converts the given NaiveDateTime to DateTime.

from_unix(integer, unit \\ :second, calendar \\ Calendar.ISO)

Converts the given Unix time to DateTime.

from_unix!(integer, unit \\ :second, calendar \\ Calendar.ISO)

Converts the given Unix time to DateTime.

new(date, time, time_zone \\ "Etc/UTC", time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Builds a datetime from date and time structs.

new!(date, time, time_zone \\ "Etc/UTC", time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Builds a datetime from date and time structs, raising on errors.

now(time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Returns the current datetime in the provided time zone.

now!(time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Returns the current datetime in the provided time zone or raises on errors

shift(datetime, duration, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Shifts given datetime by duration according to its calendar.

shift_zone(datetime, time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Changes the time zone of a DateTime.

shift_zone!(datetime, time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

Changes the time zone of a DateTime or raises on errors.

to_date(datetime)

Converts a DateTime into a Date.

to_gregorian_seconds(datetime)

Converts a DateTime struct to a number of gregorian seconds and microseconds.

to_iso8601(datetime, format \\ :extended, offset \\ nil)

Converts the given datetime to ISO 8601:2019 format.

to_naive(datetime)

Converts the given datetime into a NaiveDateTime.

to_string(datetime)

Converts the given datetime to a string according to its calendar.

to_time(datetime)

Converts a DateTime into Time.

to_unix(datetime, unit \\ :second)

Converts the given datetime to Unix time.

truncate(datetime, precision)

Returns the given datetime with the microsecond field truncated to the given precision (:microsecond, :millisecond or :second).

utc_now(calendar_or_time_unit \\ Calendar.ISO)

Returns the current datetime in UTC.

utc_now(time_unit, calendar)

Returns the current datetime in UTC, supporting a specific calendar and precision.

Types

t()

@type t() :: %DateTime{
  calendar: Calendar.calendar(),
  day: Calendar.day(),
  hour: Calendar.hour(),
  microsecond: Calendar.microsecond(),
  minute: Calendar.minute(),
  month: Calendar.month(),
  second: Calendar.second(),
  std_offset: Calendar.std_offset(),
  time_zone: Calendar.time_zone(),
  utc_offset: Calendar.utc_offset(),
  year: Calendar.year(),
  zone_abbr: Calendar.zone_abbr()
}

Functions

add(datetime, amount_to_add, unit \\ :second, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.8.0)

@spec add(
  Calendar.datetime(),
  integer(),
  :day | :hour | :minute | System.time_unit(),
  Calendar.time_zone_database()
) :: t()

Adds a specified amount of time to a DateTime.

Accepts an amount_to_add in any unit. unit can be :day, :hour, :minute, :second or any subsecond precision from System.time_unit/0. It defaults to :second. Negative values will move backwards in time.

This function always considers the unit to be computed according to the Calendar.ISO.

This function relies on a contiguous representation of time, ignoring the wall time and timezone changes. For example, if you add one day when there are summer time/daylight saving time changes, it will also change the time forward or backward by one hour, so the elapsed time is precisely 24 hours. Similarly, adding just a few seconds to a datetime just before "spring forward" can cause wall time to increase by more than an hour.

While this means this function is precise in terms of elapsed time, its result may be misleading in certain use cases. For example, if a user requests a meeting to happen every day at 15:00 and you use this function to compute all future meetings by adding day after day, this function may change the meeting time to 14:00 or 16:00 if there are changes to the current timezone. Computing of recurring datetimes is not currently supported in Elixir's standard library but it is available by third-party libraries.

Examples

iex> dt = DateTime.from_naive!(~N[2018-11-15 10:00:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> dt |> DateTime.add(3600, :second, FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
#DateTime<2018-11-15 11:00:00+01:00 CET Europe/Copenhagen>

iex> DateTime.add(~U[2018-11-15 10:00:00Z], 3600, :second)
~U[2018-11-15 11:00:00Z]

When adding 3 seconds just before "spring forward" we go from 1:59:59 to 3:00:02:

iex> dt = DateTime.from_naive!(~N[2019-03-31 01:59:59.123], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> dt |> DateTime.add(3, :second, FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
#DateTime<2019-03-31 03:00:02.123+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

When adding 1 day during "spring forward", the hour also changes:

iex> dt = DateTime.from_naive!(~N[2019-03-31 01:00:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> dt |> DateTime.add(1, :day, FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
#DateTime<2019-04-01 02:00:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

This operation merges the precision of the naive date time with the given unit:

iex> result = DateTime.add(~U[2014-10-02 00:29:10Z], 21, :millisecond)
~U[2014-10-02 00:29:10.021Z]
iex> result.microsecond
{21000, 3}

To shift a datetime by a Duration and according to its underlying calendar, use DateTime.shift/3.

after?(datetime1, datetime2)

(since 1.15.0)

@spec after?(Calendar.datetime(), Calendar.datetime()) :: boolean()

Returns true if the first datetime is strictly later than the second.

Examples

iex> DateTime.after?(~U[2022-02-02 11:00:00Z], ~U[2021-01-01 11:00:00Z])
true
iex> DateTime.after?(~U[2021-01-01 11:00:00Z], ~U[2021-01-01 11:00:00Z])
false
iex> DateTime.after?(~U[2021-01-01 11:00:00Z], ~U[2022-02-02 11:00:00Z])
false

before?(datetime1, datetime2)

(since 1.15.0)

@spec before?(Calendar.datetime(), Calendar.datetime()) :: boolean()

Returns true if the first datetime is strictly earlier than the second.

Examples

iex> DateTime.before?(~U[2021-01-01 11:00:00Z], ~U[2022-02-02 11:00:00Z])
true
iex> DateTime.before?(~U[2021-01-01 11:00:00Z], ~U[2021-01-01 11:00:00Z])
false
iex> DateTime.before?(~U[2022-02-02 11:00:00Z], ~U[2021-01-01 11:00:00Z])
false

compare(datetime1, datetime2)

(since 1.4.0)

@spec compare(Calendar.datetime(), Calendar.datetime()) :: :lt | :eq | :gt

Compares two datetime structs.

Returns :gt if the first datetime is later than the second and :lt for vice versa. If the two datetimes are equal :eq is returned.

Note that both UTC and Standard offsets will be taken into account when comparison is done.

Examples

iex> dt1 = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "AMT",
...>                 hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                 utc_offset: -14400, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "America/Manaus"}
iex> dt2 = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                 hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                 utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Warsaw"}
iex> DateTime.compare(dt1, dt2)
:gt

convert(datetime, calendar)

(since 1.5.0)

@spec convert(Calendar.datetime(), Calendar.calendar()) ::
  {:ok, t()} | {:error, :incompatible_calendars}

Converts a given datetime from one calendar to another.

If it is not possible to convert unambiguously between the calendars (see Calendar.compatible_calendars?/2), an {:error, :incompatible_calendars} tuple is returned.

Examples

Imagine someone implements Calendar.Holocene, a calendar based on the Gregorian calendar that adds exactly 10,000 years to the current Gregorian year:

iex> dt1 = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "AMT",
...>                 hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                 utc_offset: -14400, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "America/Manaus"}
iex> DateTime.convert(dt1, Calendar.Holocene)
{:ok, %DateTime{calendar: Calendar.Holocene, day: 29, hour: 23,
                microsecond: {0, 0}, minute: 0, month: 2, second: 7, std_offset: 0,
                time_zone: "America/Manaus", utc_offset: -14400, year: 12000,
                zone_abbr: "AMT"}}

convert!(datetime, calendar)

(since 1.5.0)

@spec convert!(Calendar.datetime(), Calendar.calendar()) :: t()

Converts a given datetime from one calendar to another.

If it is not possible to convert unambiguously between the calendars (see Calendar.compatible_calendars?/2), an ArgumentError is raised.

Examples

Imagine someone implements Calendar.Holocene, a calendar based on the Gregorian calendar that adds exactly 10,000 years to the current Gregorian year:

iex> dt1 = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "AMT",
...>                 hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                 utc_offset: -14400, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "America/Manaus"}
iex> DateTime.convert!(dt1, Calendar.Holocene)
%DateTime{calendar: Calendar.Holocene, day: 29, hour: 23,
          microsecond: {0, 0}, minute: 0, month: 2, second: 7, std_offset: 0,
          time_zone: "America/Manaus", utc_offset: -14400, year: 12000,
          zone_abbr: "AMT"}

diff(datetime1, datetime2, unit \\ :second)

(since 1.5.0)

@spec diff(
  Calendar.datetime(),
  Calendar.datetime(),
  :day | :hour | :minute | System.time_unit()
) :: integer()

Subtracts datetime2 from datetime1.

The answer can be returned in any :day, :hour, :minute, or any unit available from System.time_unit/0. The unit is measured according to Calendar.ISO and defaults to :second.

Fractional results are not supported and are truncated.

Examples

iex> DateTime.diff(~U[2024-01-15 10:00:10Z], ~U[2024-01-15 10:00:00Z])
10

This function also considers timezone offsets:

iex> dt1 = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "AMT",
...>                 hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                 utc_offset: -14400, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "America/Manaus"}
iex> dt2 = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                 hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                 utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Warsaw"}
iex> DateTime.diff(dt1, dt2)
18000
iex> DateTime.diff(dt2, dt1)
-18000
iex> DateTime.diff(dt1, dt2, :hour)
5
iex> DateTime.diff(dt2, dt1, :hour)
-5

from_gregorian_seconds(seconds, arg \\ {0, 0}, calendar \\ Calendar.ISO)

(since 1.11.0)

@spec from_gregorian_seconds(integer(), Calendar.microsecond(), Calendar.calendar()) ::
  t()

Converts a number of gregorian seconds to a DateTime struct.

The returned DateTime will have UTC timezone, if you want other timezone, please use DateTime.shift_zone/3.

Examples

iex> DateTime.from_gregorian_seconds(1)
~U[0000-01-01 00:00:01Z]
iex> DateTime.from_gregorian_seconds(63_755_511_991, {5000, 3})
~U[2020-05-01 00:26:31.005Z]
iex> DateTime.from_gregorian_seconds(-1)
~U[-0001-12-31 23:59:59Z]

from_iso8601(string, format_or_calendar \\ Calendar.ISO)

(since 1.4.0)

@spec from_iso8601(String.t(), Calendar.calendar() | :extended | :basic) ::
  {:ok, t(), Calendar.utc_offset()} | {:error, atom()}

Parses the extended "Date and time of day" format described by ISO 8601:2019.

Since ISO 8601 does not include the proper time zone, the given string will be converted to UTC and its offset in seconds will be returned as part of this function. Therefore offset information must be present in the string.

As specified in the standard, the separator "T" may be omitted if desired as there is no ambiguity within this function.

Note leap seconds are not supported by the built-in Calendar.ISO.

Examples

iex> {:ok, datetime, 0} = DateTime.from_iso8601("2015-01-23T23:50:07Z")
iex> datetime
~U[2015-01-23 23:50:07Z]

iex> {:ok, datetime, 9000} = DateTime.from_iso8601("2015-01-23T23:50:07.123+02:30")
iex> datetime
~U[2015-01-23 21:20:07.123Z]

iex> {:ok, datetime, 9000} = DateTime.from_iso8601("2015-01-23T23:50:07,123+02:30")
iex> datetime
~U[2015-01-23 21:20:07.123Z]

iex> {:ok, datetime, 0} = DateTime.from_iso8601("-2015-01-23T23:50:07Z")
iex> datetime
~U[-2015-01-23 23:50:07Z]

iex> {:ok, datetime, 9000} = DateTime.from_iso8601("-2015-01-23T23:50:07,123+02:30")
iex> datetime
~U[-2015-01-23 21:20:07.123Z]

iex> {:ok, datetime, 9000} = DateTime.from_iso8601("20150123T235007.123+0230", :basic)
iex> datetime
~U[2015-01-23 21:20:07.123Z]

iex> DateTime.from_iso8601("2015-01-23P23:50:07")
{:error, :invalid_format}
iex> DateTime.from_iso8601("2015-01-23T23:50:07")
{:error, :missing_offset}
iex> DateTime.from_iso8601("2015-01-23 23:50:61")
{:error, :invalid_time}
iex> DateTime.from_iso8601("2015-01-32 23:50:07")
{:error, :invalid_date}
iex> DateTime.from_iso8601("2015-01-23T23:50:07.123-00:00")
{:error, :invalid_format}

from_iso8601(string, calendar, format)

@spec from_iso8601(String.t(), Calendar.calendar(), :extended | :basic) ::
  {:ok, t(), Calendar.utc_offset()} | {:error, atom()}

Converts from ISO8601 specifying both a calendar and a mode.

See from_iso8601/2 for more information.

Examples

iex> {:ok, datetime, 9000} = DateTime.from_iso8601("2015-01-23T23:50:07,123+02:30", Calendar.ISO, :extended)
iex> datetime
~U[2015-01-23 21:20:07.123Z]

iex> {:ok, datetime, 9000} = DateTime.from_iso8601("20150123T235007.123+0230", Calendar.ISO, :basic)
iex> datetime
~U[2015-01-23 21:20:07.123Z]

from_naive(naive_datetime, time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.4.0)

@spec from_naive(
  Calendar.naive_datetime(),
  Calendar.time_zone(),
  Calendar.time_zone_database()
) ::
  {:ok, t()}
  | {:ambiguous, first_datetime :: t(), second_datetime :: t()}
  | {:gap, t(), t()}
  | {:error,
     :incompatible_calendars
     | :time_zone_not_found
     | :utc_only_time_zone_database}

Converts the given NaiveDateTime to DateTime.

It expects a time zone to put the NaiveDateTime in. If the time zone is "Etc/UTC", it always succeeds. Otherwise, the NaiveDateTime is checked against the time zone database given as time_zone_database. See the "Time zone database" section in the module documentation.

Examples

iex> DateTime.from_naive(~N[2016-05-24 13:26:08.003], "Etc/UTC")
{:ok, ~U[2016-05-24 13:26:08.003Z]}

When the datetime is ambiguous - for instance during changing from summer to winter time - the two possible valid datetimes are returned in a tuple. The first datetime is also the one which comes first chronologically, while the second one comes last.

iex> {:ambiguous, first_dt, second_dt} = DateTime.from_naive(~N[2018-10-28 02:30:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> first_dt
#DateTime<2018-10-28 02:30:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>
iex> second_dt
#DateTime<2018-10-28 02:30:00+01:00 CET Europe/Copenhagen>

When there is a gap in wall time - for instance in spring when the clocks are turned forward - the latest valid datetime just before the gap and the first valid datetime just after the gap.

iex> {:gap, just_before, just_after} = DateTime.from_naive(~N[2019-03-31 02:30:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> just_before
#DateTime<2019-03-31 01:59:59.999999+01:00 CET Europe/Copenhagen>
iex> just_after
#DateTime<2019-03-31 03:00:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

Most of the time there is one, and just one, valid datetime for a certain date and time in a certain time zone.

iex> {:ok, datetime} = DateTime.from_naive(~N[2018-07-28 12:30:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> datetime
#DateTime<2018-07-28 12:30:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

This function accepts any map or struct that contains at least the same fields as a NaiveDateTime struct. The most common example of that is a DateTime. In this case the information about the time zone of that DateTime is completely ignored. This is the same principle as passing a DateTime to Date.to_iso8601/2. Date.to_iso8601/2 extracts only the date-specific fields (calendar, year, month and day) of the given structure and ignores all others.

This way if you have a DateTime in one time zone, you can get the same wall time in another time zone. For instance if you have 2018-08-24 10:00:00 in Copenhagen and want a DateTime for 2018-08-24 10:00:00 in UTC you can do:

iex> cph_datetime = DateTime.from_naive!(~N[2018-08-24 10:00:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> {:ok, utc_datetime} = DateTime.from_naive(cph_datetime, "Etc/UTC", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> utc_datetime
~U[2018-08-24 10:00:00Z]

If instead you want a DateTime for the same point time in a different time zone see the DateTime.shift_zone/3 function which would convert 2018-08-24 10:00:00 in Copenhagen to 2018-08-24 08:00:00 in UTC.

from_naive!(naive_datetime, time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.4.0)

@spec from_naive!(
  NaiveDateTime.t(),
  Calendar.time_zone(),
  Calendar.time_zone_database()
) :: t()

Converts the given NaiveDateTime to DateTime.

It expects a time zone to put the NaiveDateTime in. If the time zone is "Etc/UTC", it always succeeds. Otherwise, the NaiveDateTime is checked against the time zone database given as time_zone_database. See the "Time zone database" section in the module documentation.

Examples

iex> DateTime.from_naive!(~N[2016-05-24 13:26:08.003], "Etc/UTC")
~U[2016-05-24 13:26:08.003Z]

iex> DateTime.from_naive!(~N[2018-05-24 13:26:08.003], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
#DateTime<2018-05-24 13:26:08.003+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

from_unix(integer, unit \\ :second, calendar \\ Calendar.ISO)

@spec from_unix(integer(), :native | System.time_unit(), Calendar.calendar()) ::
  {:ok, t()} | {:error, atom()}

Converts the given Unix time to DateTime.

The integer can be given in different unit according to System.convert_time_unit/3 and it will be converted to microseconds internally. Up to 253402300799 seconds is supported.

Unix times are always in UTC and therefore the DateTime will be returned in UTC.

Examples

iex> {:ok, datetime} = DateTime.from_unix(1_464_096_368)
iex> datetime
~U[2016-05-24 13:26:08Z]

iex> {:ok, datetime} = DateTime.from_unix(1_432_560_368_868_569, :microsecond)
iex> datetime
~U[2015-05-25 13:26:08.868569Z]

iex> {:ok, datetime} = DateTime.from_unix(253_402_300_799)
iex> datetime
~U[9999-12-31 23:59:59Z]

iex> {:error, :invalid_unix_time} = DateTime.from_unix(253_402_300_800)

The unit can also be an integer as in System.time_unit/0:

iex> {:ok, datetime} = DateTime.from_unix(143_256_036_886_856, 1024)
iex> datetime
~U[6403-03-17 07:05:22.320312Z]

Negative Unix times are supported up to -377705116800 seconds:

iex> {:ok, datetime} = DateTime.from_unix(-377_705_116_800)
iex> datetime
~U[-9999-01-01 00:00:00Z]

iex> {:error, :invalid_unix_time} = DateTime.from_unix(-377_705_116_801)

from_unix!(integer, unit \\ :second, calendar \\ Calendar.ISO)

@spec from_unix!(integer(), :native | System.time_unit(), Calendar.calendar()) :: t()

Converts the given Unix time to DateTime.

The integer can be given in different unit according to System.convert_time_unit/3 and it will be converted to microseconds internally.

Unix times are always in UTC and therefore the DateTime will be returned in UTC.

Examples

# An easy way to get the Unix epoch is passing 0 to this function
iex> DateTime.from_unix!(0)
~U[1970-01-01 00:00:00Z]

iex> DateTime.from_unix!(1_464_096_368)
~U[2016-05-24 13:26:08Z]

iex> DateTime.from_unix!(1_432_560_368_868_569, :microsecond)
~U[2015-05-25 13:26:08.868569Z]

iex> DateTime.from_unix!(143_256_036_886_856, 1024)
~U[6403-03-17 07:05:22.320312Z]

new(date, time, time_zone \\ "Etc/UTC", time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.11.0)

@spec new(Date.t(), Time.t(), Calendar.time_zone(), Calendar.time_zone_database()) ::
  {:ok, t()}
  | {:ambiguous, first_datetime :: t(), second_datetime :: t()}
  | {:gap, t(), t()}
  | {:error,
     :incompatible_calendars
     | :time_zone_not_found
     | :utc_only_time_zone_database}

Builds a datetime from date and time structs.

It expects a time zone to put the DateTime in. If the time zone is not passed it will default to "Etc/UTC", which always succeeds. Otherwise, the DateTime is checked against the time zone database given as time_zone_database. See the "Time zone database" section in the module documentation.

Examples

iex> DateTime.new(~D[2016-05-24], ~T[13:26:08.003], "Etc/UTC")
{:ok, ~U[2016-05-24 13:26:08.003Z]}

When the datetime is ambiguous - for instance during changing from summer to winter time - the two possible valid datetimes are returned in a tuple. The first datetime is also the one which comes first chronologically, while the second one comes last.

iex> {:ambiguous, first_dt, second_dt} = DateTime.new(~D[2018-10-28], ~T[02:30:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> first_dt
#DateTime<2018-10-28 02:30:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>
iex> second_dt
#DateTime<2018-10-28 02:30:00+01:00 CET Europe/Copenhagen>

When there is a gap in wall time - for instance in spring when the clocks are turned forward - the latest valid datetime just before the gap and the first valid datetime just after the gap.

iex> {:gap, just_before, just_after} = DateTime.new(~D[2019-03-31], ~T[02:30:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> just_before
#DateTime<2019-03-31 01:59:59.999999+01:00 CET Europe/Copenhagen>
iex> just_after
#DateTime<2019-03-31 03:00:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

Most of the time there is one, and just one, valid datetime for a certain date and time in a certain time zone.

iex> {:ok, datetime} = DateTime.new(~D[2018-07-28], ~T[12:30:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> datetime
#DateTime<2018-07-28 12:30:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

new!(date, time, time_zone \\ "Etc/UTC", time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.11.0)

@spec new!(Date.t(), Time.t(), Calendar.time_zone(), Calendar.time_zone_database()) ::
  t()

Builds a datetime from date and time structs, raising on errors.

It expects a time zone to put the DateTime in. If the time zone is not passed it will default to "Etc/UTC", which always succeeds. Otherwise, the DateTime is checked against the time zone database given as time_zone_database. See the "Time zone database" section in the module documentation.

Examples

iex> DateTime.new!(~D[2016-05-24], ~T[13:26:08.003], "Etc/UTC")
~U[2016-05-24 13:26:08.003Z]

When the datetime is ambiguous - for instance during changing from summer to winter time - an error will be raised.

iex> DateTime.new!(~D[2018-10-28], ~T[02:30:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
** (ArgumentError) cannot build datetime with ~D[2018-10-28] and ~T[02:30:00] because such instant is ambiguous in time zone Europe/Copenhagen as there is an overlap between #DateTime<2018-10-28 02:30:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen> and #DateTime<2018-10-28 02:30:00+01:00 CET Europe/Copenhagen>

When there is a gap in wall time - for instance in spring when the clocks are turned forward - an error will be raised.

iex> DateTime.new!(~D[2019-03-31], ~T[02:30:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
** (ArgumentError) cannot build datetime with ~D[2019-03-31] and ~T[02:30:00] because such instant does not exist in time zone Europe/Copenhagen as there is a gap between #DateTime<2019-03-31 01:59:59.999999+01:00 CET Europe/Copenhagen> and #DateTime<2019-03-31 03:00:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

Most of the time there is one, and just one, valid datetime for a certain date and time in a certain time zone.

iex> datetime = DateTime.new!(~D[2018-07-28], ~T[12:30:00], "Europe/Copenhagen", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> datetime
#DateTime<2018-07-28 12:30:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

now(time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.8.0)

@spec now(Calendar.time_zone(), Calendar.time_zone_database()) ::
  {:ok, t()} | {:error, :time_zone_not_found | :utc_only_time_zone_database}

Returns the current datetime in the provided time zone.

By default, it uses the default time_zone returned by Calendar.get_time_zone_database/0, which defaults to Calendar.UTCOnlyTimeZoneDatabase which only handles "Etc/UTC" datetimes. Other time zone databases can be passed as argument or set globally. See the "Time zone database" section in the module docs.

Examples

iex> {:ok, datetime} = DateTime.now("Etc/UTC")
iex> datetime.time_zone
"Etc/UTC"

iex> DateTime.now("Europe/Copenhagen")
{:error, :utc_only_time_zone_database}

iex> DateTime.now("bad timezone", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
{:error, :time_zone_not_found}

now!(time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.10.0)

@spec now!(Calendar.time_zone(), Calendar.time_zone_database()) :: t()

Returns the current datetime in the provided time zone or raises on errors

See now/2 for more information.

Examples

iex> datetime = DateTime.now!("Etc/UTC")
iex> datetime.time_zone
"Etc/UTC"

iex> DateTime.now!("Europe/Copenhagen")
** (ArgumentError) cannot get current datetime in "Europe/Copenhagen" time zone, reason: :utc_only_time_zone_database

iex> DateTime.now!("bad timezone", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
** (ArgumentError) cannot get current datetime in "bad timezone" time zone, reason: :time_zone_not_found

shift(datetime, duration, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.17.0)

@spec shift(Calendar.datetime(), Duration.duration(), Calendar.time_zone_database()) ::
  t()

Shifts given datetime by duration according to its calendar.

Allowed units are: :year, :month, :week, :day, :hour, :minute, :second, :microsecond.

This operation is equivalent to shifting the datetime wall clock (in other words, the value as someone in that timezone would see on their watch), then applying the time zone offset to convert it to UTC, and finally computing the new timezone in case of shifts. This ensures shift/3 always returns a valid datetime.

On the other hand, time zones that observe "Daylight Saving Time" or other changes, across summer/winter time will add/remove hours from the resulting datetime:

dt = DateTime.new!(~D[2019-03-31], ~T[01:00:00], "Europe/Copenhagen")
DateTime.shift(dt, hour: 1)
#=> #DateTime<2019-03-31 03:00:00+02:00 CEST Europe/Copenhagen>

dt = DateTime.new!(~D[2018-11-04], ~T[00:00:00], "America/Los_Angeles")
DateTime.shift(dt, hour: 2)
#=> #DateTime<2018-11-04 01:00:00-08:00 PST America/Los_Angeles>

In case you don't want these changes to happen automatically or you want to surface time zone conflicts to the user, you can shift the datetime as a naive datetime and then use from_naive/2:

dt |> NaiveDateTime.shift(duration) |> DateTime.from_naive(dt.time_zone)

When using the default ISO calendar, durations are collapsed and applied in the order of months, then seconds and microseconds:

when shifting by 1 year and 2 months the date is actually shifted by 14 months
weeks, days and smaller units are collapsed into seconds and microseconds

When shifting by month, days are rounded down to the nearest valid date.

Examples

iex> DateTime.shift(~U[2016-01-01 00:00:00Z], month: 2)
~U[2016-03-01 00:00:00Z]
iex> DateTime.shift(~U[2016-01-01 00:00:00Z], year: 1, week: 4)
~U[2017-01-29 00:00:00Z]
iex> DateTime.shift(~U[2016-01-01 00:00:00Z], minute: -25)
~U[2015-12-31 23:35:00Z]
iex> DateTime.shift(~U[2016-01-01 00:00:00Z], minute: 5, microsecond: {500, 4})
~U[2016-01-01 00:05:00.0005Z]

# leap years
iex> DateTime.shift(~U[2024-02-29 00:00:00Z], year: 1)
~U[2025-02-28 00:00:00Z]
iex> DateTime.shift(~U[2024-02-29 00:00:00Z], year: 4)
~U[2028-02-29 00:00:00Z]

# rounding down
iex> DateTime.shift(~U[2015-01-31 00:00:00Z], month: 1)
~U[2015-02-28 00:00:00Z]

shift_zone(datetime, time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.8.0)

@spec shift_zone(t(), Calendar.time_zone(), Calendar.time_zone_database()) ::
  {:ok, t()} | {:error, :time_zone_not_found | :utc_only_time_zone_database}

Changes the time zone of a DateTime.

Returns a DateTime for the same point in time, but instead at the time zone provided. It assumes that DateTime is valid and exists in the given time zone and calendar.

By default, it uses the default time zone database returned by Calendar.get_time_zone_database/0, which defaults to Calendar.UTCOnlyTimeZoneDatabase which only handles "Etc/UTC" datetimes. Other time zone databases can be passed as argument or set globally. See the "Time zone database" section in the module docs.

Examples

iex> {:ok, pacific_datetime} = DateTime.shift_zone(~U[2018-07-16 10:00:00Z], "America/Los_Angeles", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
iex> pacific_datetime
#DateTime<2018-07-16 03:00:00-07:00 PDT America/Los_Angeles>

iex> DateTime.shift_zone(~U[2018-07-16 10:00:00Z], "bad timezone", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
{:error, :time_zone_not_found}

shift_zone!(datetime, time_zone, time_zone_database \\ Calendar.get_time_zone_database())

(since 1.10.0)

@spec shift_zone!(t(), Calendar.time_zone(), Calendar.time_zone_database()) :: t()

Changes the time zone of a DateTime or raises on errors.

See shift_zone/3 for more information.

Examples

iex> DateTime.shift_zone!(~U[2018-07-16 10:00:00Z], "America/Los_Angeles", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
#DateTime<2018-07-16 03:00:00-07:00 PDT America/Los_Angeles>

iex> DateTime.shift_zone!(~U[2018-07-16 10:00:00Z], "bad timezone", FakeTimeZoneDatabase)
** (ArgumentError) cannot shift ~U[2018-07-16 10:00:00Z] to "bad timezone" time zone, reason: :time_zone_not_found

to_date(datetime)

@spec to_date(Calendar.datetime()) :: Date.t()

Converts a DateTime into a Date.

Because Date does not hold time nor time zone information, data will be lost during the conversion.

Examples

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Warsaw"}
iex> DateTime.to_date(dt)
~D[2000-02-29]

to_gregorian_seconds(datetime)

(since 1.11.0)

@spec to_gregorian_seconds(Calendar.datetime()) :: {integer(), non_neg_integer()}

Converts a DateTime struct to a number of gregorian seconds and microseconds.

Examples

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 0000, month: 1, day: 1, zone_abbr: "UTC",
...>                hour: 0, minute: 0, second: 1, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 0, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Etc/UTC"}
iex> DateTime.to_gregorian_seconds(dt)
{1, 0}

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2020, month: 5, day: 1, zone_abbr: "UTC",
...>                hour: 0, minute: 26, second: 31, microsecond: {5000, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 0, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Etc/UTC"}
iex> DateTime.to_gregorian_seconds(dt)
{63_755_511_991, 5000}

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2020, month: 5, day: 1, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                hour: 1, minute: 26, second: 31, microsecond: {5000, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Warsaw"}
iex> DateTime.to_gregorian_seconds(dt)
{63_755_511_991, 5000}

to_iso8601(datetime, format \\ :extended, offset \\ nil)

@spec to_iso8601(Calendar.datetime(), :basic | :extended, nil | integer()) ::
  String.t()

Converts the given datetime to ISO 8601:2019 format.

By default, DateTime.to_iso8601/2 returns datetimes formatted in the "extended" format, for human readability. It also supports the "basic" format through passing the :basic option.

You can also optionally specify an offset for the formatted string. If none is given, the one in the given datetime is used.

Only supports converting datetimes which are in the ISO calendar. If another calendar is given, it is automatically converted to ISO. It raises if not possible.

WARNING: the ISO 8601 datetime format does not contain the time zone nor its abbreviation, which means information is lost when converting to such format.

Examples

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Warsaw"}
iex> DateTime.to_iso8601(dt)
"2000-02-29T23:00:07+01:00"

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "UTC",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 0, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Etc/UTC"}
iex> DateTime.to_iso8601(dt)
"2000-02-29T23:00:07Z"

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "AMT",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: -14400, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "America/Manaus"}
iex> DateTime.to_iso8601(dt, :extended)
"2000-02-29T23:00:07-04:00"

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "AMT",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: -14400, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "America/Manaus"}
iex> DateTime.to_iso8601(dt, :basic)
"20000229T230007-0400"

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "AMT",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: -14400, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "America/Manaus"}
iex> DateTime.to_iso8601(dt, :extended, 3600)
"2000-03-01T04:00:07+01:00"

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "AMT",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: -14400, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "America/Manaus"}
iex> DateTime.to_iso8601(dt, :extended, 0)
"2000-03-01T03:00:07+00:00"

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 3, day: 01, zone_abbr: "UTC",
...>                hour: 03, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 0, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Etc/UTC"}
iex> DateTime.to_iso8601(dt, :extended, 0)
"2000-03-01T03:00:07Z"

iex> {:ok, dt, offset} = DateTime.from_iso8601("2000-03-01T03:00:07Z")
iex> "2000-03-01T03:00:07Z" = DateTime.to_iso8601(dt, :extended, offset)

to_naive(datetime)

@spec to_naive(Calendar.datetime()) :: NaiveDateTime.t()

Converts the given datetime into a NaiveDateTime.

Because NaiveDateTime does not hold time zone information, any time zone related data will be lost during the conversion.

Examples

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 1},
...>                utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Warsaw"}
iex> DateTime.to_naive(dt)
~N[2000-02-29 23:00:07.0]

to_string(datetime)

@spec to_string(Calendar.datetime()) :: String.t()

Converts the given datetime to a string according to its calendar.

Unfortunately, there is no standard that specifies rendering of a datetime with its complete time zone information, so Elixir uses a custom (but relatively common) representation which appends the time zone abbreviation and full name to the datetime.

Examples

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Warsaw"}
iex> DateTime.to_string(dt)
"2000-02-29 23:00:07+01:00 CET Europe/Warsaw"

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "UTC",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 0, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Etc/UTC"}
iex> DateTime.to_string(dt)
"2000-02-29 23:00:07Z"

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "AMT",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: -14400, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "America/Manaus"}
iex> DateTime.to_string(dt)
"2000-02-29 23:00:07-04:00 AMT America/Manaus"

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: -100, month: 12, day: 19, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                hour: 3, minute: 20, second: 31, microsecond: {0, 0},
...>                utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Stockholm"}
iex> DateTime.to_string(dt)
"-0100-12-19 03:20:31+01:00 CET Europe/Stockholm"

to_time(datetime)

@spec to_time(Calendar.datetime()) :: Time.t()

Converts a DateTime into Time.

Because Time does not hold date nor time zone information, data will be lost during the conversion.

Examples

iex> dt = %DateTime{year: 2000, month: 2, day: 29, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                hour: 23, minute: 0, second: 7, microsecond: {0, 1},
...>                utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Warsaw"}
iex> DateTime.to_time(dt)
~T[23:00:07.0]

to_unix(datetime, unit \\ :second)

@spec to_unix(Calendar.datetime(), :native | System.time_unit()) :: integer()

Converts the given datetime to Unix time.

The datetime is expected to be using the ISO calendar with a year greater than or equal to 0.

It will return the integer with the given unit, according to System.convert_time_unit/3.

Examples

iex> 1_464_096_368 |> DateTime.from_unix!() |> DateTime.to_unix()
1464096368

iex> dt = %DateTime{calendar: Calendar.ISO, day: 20, hour: 18, microsecond: {273806, 6},
...>                minute: 58, month: 11, second: 19, time_zone: "America/Montevideo",
...>                utc_offset: -10800, std_offset: 3600, year: 2014, zone_abbr: "UYST"}
iex> DateTime.to_unix(dt)
1416517099

iex> flamel = %DateTime{calendar: Calendar.ISO, day: 22, hour: 8, microsecond: {527771, 6},
...>                minute: 2, month: 3, second: 25, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Etc/UTC",
...>                utc_offset: 0, year: 1418, zone_abbr: "UTC"}
iex> DateTime.to_unix(flamel)
-17412508655

truncate(datetime, precision)

(since 1.6.0)

@spec truncate(Calendar.datetime(), :microsecond | :millisecond | :second) :: t()

Returns the given datetime with the microsecond field truncated to the given precision (:microsecond, :millisecond or :second).

The given datetime is returned unchanged if it already has lower precision than the given precision.

Examples

iex> dt1 = %DateTime{year: 2017, month: 11, day: 7, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                 hour: 11, minute: 45, second: 18, microsecond: {123456, 6},
...>                 utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Paris"}
iex> DateTime.truncate(dt1, :microsecond)
#DateTime<2017-11-07 11:45:18.123456+01:00 CET Europe/Paris>

iex> dt2 = %DateTime{year: 2017, month: 11, day: 7, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                 hour: 11, minute: 45, second: 18, microsecond: {123456, 6},
...>                 utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Paris"}
iex> DateTime.truncate(dt2, :millisecond)
#DateTime<2017-11-07 11:45:18.123+01:00 CET Europe/Paris>

iex> dt3 = %DateTime{year: 2017, month: 11, day: 7, zone_abbr: "CET",
...>                 hour: 11, minute: 45, second: 18, microsecond: {123456, 6},
...>                 utc_offset: 3600, std_offset: 0, time_zone: "Europe/Paris"}
iex> DateTime.truncate(dt3, :second)
#DateTime<2017-11-07 11:45:18+01:00 CET Europe/Paris>

utc_now(calendar_or_time_unit \\ Calendar.ISO)

@spec utc_now(Calendar.calendar() | :native | :microsecond | :millisecond | :second) ::
  t()

Returns the current datetime in UTC.

If you want the current time in Unix seconds, use System.os_time/1 instead.

You can also pass a time unit to automatically truncate the resulting datetime. This is available since v1.15.0.

The default unit if none gets passed is :native, which results on a default resolution of microseconds.

Examples

iex> datetime = DateTime.utc_now()
iex> datetime.time_zone
"Etc/UTC"

iex> datetime = DateTime.utc_now(:second)
iex> datetime.microsecond
{0, 0}

utc_now(time_unit, calendar)

(since 1.15.0)

@spec utc_now(:native | :microsecond | :millisecond | :second, Calendar.calendar()) ::
  t()

Returns the current datetime in UTC, supporting a specific calendar and precision.

If you want the current time in Unix seconds, use System.os_time/1 instead.

Examples

iex> datetime = DateTime.utc_now(:microsecond, Calendar.ISO)
iex> datetime.time_zone
"Etc/UTC"

iex> datetime = DateTime.utc_now(:second, Calendar.ISO)
iex> datetime.microsecond
{0, 0}

Dependencies and umbrella projects

In this chapter, we will discuss how to manage dependencies in Mix.

Our kv application is complete, so it's time to implement the server that will handle the requests we defined in the first chapter:

CREATE shopping
OK

PUT shopping milk 1
OK

PUT shopping eggs 3
OK

GET shopping milk
1
OK

DELETE shopping eggs
OK

However, instead of adding more code to the kv application, we are going to build the TCP server as another application that is a client of the kv application. Since the whole runtime and Elixir ecosystem are geared towards applications, it makes sense to break our projects into smaller applications that work together rather than building a big, monolithic app.

Before creating our new application, we must discuss how Mix handles dependencies. In practice, there are two kinds of dependencies we usually work with: internal and external dependencies. Mix supports mechanisms to work with both.

External dependencies

External dependencies are the ones not tied to your business domain. For example, if you need an HTTP API for your distributed KV application, you can use the Plug project as an external dependency.

Installing external dependencies is simple. Most commonly, we use the Hex Package Manager, by listing the dependency inside the deps function in our mix.exs file:

def deps do
  [{:plug, "~> 1.0"}]
end

This dependency refers to the latest version of Plug in the 1.x.x version series that has been pushed to Hex. This is indicated by the ~> preceding the version number. For more information on specifying version requirements, see the documentation for the Version module.

Typically, stable releases are pushed to Hex. If you want to depend on an external dependency still in development, Mix is able to manage Git dependencies too:

def deps do
  [{:plug, git: "https://github.com/elixir-lang/plug.git"}]
end

You will notice that when you add a dependency to your project, Mix generates a mix.lock file that guarantees repeatable builds. The lock file must be checked in to your version control system, to guarantee that everyone who uses the project will use the same dependency versions as you.

Mix provides many tasks for working with dependencies, which can be seen in mix help:

$ mix help
mix deps              # Lists dependencies and their status
mix deps.clean        # Deletes the given dependencies' files
mix deps.compile      # Compiles dependencies
mix deps.get          # Gets all out of date dependencies
mix deps.tree         # Prints the dependency tree
mix deps.unlock       # Unlocks the given dependencies
mix deps.update       # Updates the given dependencies

The most common tasks are mix deps.get and mix deps.update. Once fetched, dependencies are automatically compiled for you. You can read more about deps by typing mix help deps, and in the documentation for the Mix.Tasks.Deps module.

Internal dependencies

Internal dependencies are the ones that are specific to your project. They usually don't make sense outside the scope of your project/company/organization. Most of the time, you want to keep them private, whether due to technical, economic or business reasons.

If you have an internal dependency, Mix supports two methods to work with them: Git repositories or umbrella projects.

For example, if you push the kv project to a Git repository, you'll need to list it in your deps code in order to use it:

def deps do
  [{:kv, git: "https://github.com/YOUR_ACCOUNT/kv.git"}]
end

If the repository is private though, you may need to specify the private URL git@github.com:YOUR_ACCOUNT/kv.git. In any case, Mix will be able to fetch it for you as long as you have the proper credentials.

Using Git repositories for internal dependencies is somewhat discouraged in Elixir. Remember that the runtime and the Elixir ecosystem already provide the concept of applications. As such, we expect you to frequently break your code into applications that can be organized logically, even within a single project.

However, if you push every application as a separate project to a Git repository, your projects may become very hard to maintain as you will spend a lot of time managing those Git repositories rather than writing your code.

For this reason, Mix supports "umbrella projects". Umbrella projects are used to build applications that run together in a single repository. That is exactly the style we are going to explore in the next sections.

Let's create a new Mix project. We are going to creatively name it kv_umbrella, and this new project will have both the existing kv application and the new kv_server application inside. The directory structure will look like this:

+ kv_umbrella
  + apps
    + kv
    + kv_server

The interesting thing about this approach is that Mix has many conveniences for working with such projects, such as the ability to compile and test all applications inside apps with a single command. However, even though they are all listed together inside apps, they are still decoupled from each other, so you can build, test and deploy each application in isolation if you want to.

So let's get started!

Umbrella projects

Let's start a new project using mix new. This new project will be named kv_umbrella and we need to pass the --umbrella option when creating it. Do not create this new project inside the existing kv project!

$ mix new kv_umbrella --umbrella
* creating README.md
* creating .formatter.exs
* creating .gitignore
* creating mix.exs
* creating apps
* creating config
* creating config/config.exs

From the printed information, we can see far fewer files are generated. The generated mix.exs file is different too. Let's take a look (comments have been removed):

defmodule KvUmbrella.MixProject do
  use Mix.Project

  def project do
    [
      apps_path: "apps",
      start_permanent: Mix.env() == :prod,
      deps: deps()
    ]
  end

  defp deps do
    []
  end
end

What makes this project different from the previous one is the apps_path: "apps" entry in the project definition. This means this project will act as an umbrella. Such projects do not have source files nor tests, although they can have their own dependencies. Each child application must be defined inside the apps directory.

Let's move inside the apps directory and start building kv_server. This time, we are going to pass the --sup flag, which will tell Mix to generate a supervision tree automatically for us, instead of building one manually as we did in previous chapters:

$ cd kv_umbrella/apps
$ mix new kv_server --module KVServer --sup

The generated files are similar to the ones we first generated for kv, with a few differences. Let's open up mix.exs:

defmodule KVServer.MixProject do
  use Mix.Project

  def project do
    [
      app: :kv_server,
      version: "0.1.0",
      build_path: "../../_build",
      config_path: "../../config/config.exs",
      deps_path: "../../deps",
      lockfile: "../../mix.lock",
      elixir: "~> 1.14",
      start_permanent: Mix.env() == :prod,
      deps: deps()
    ]
  end

  # Run "mix help compile.app" to learn about applications
  def application do
    [
      extra_applications: [:logger],
      mod: {KVServer.Application, []}
    ]
  end

  # Run "mix help deps" to learn about dependencies
  defp deps do
    [
      # {:dep_from_hexpm, "~> 0.3.0"},
      # {:dep_from_git, git: "https://github.com/elixir-lang/my_dep.git", tag: "0.1.0"},
      # {:sibling_app_in_umbrella, in_umbrella: true},
    ]
  end
end

First of all, since we generated this project inside kv_umbrella/apps, Mix automatically detected the umbrella structure and added four lines to the project definition:

build_path: "../../_build",
config_path: "../../config/config.exs",
deps_path: "../../deps",
lockfile: "../../mix.lock",

Those options mean all dependencies will be checked out to kv_umbrella/deps, and they will share the same build, config, and lock files. We haven't talked about configuration yet, but from here we can build the intuition that all configuration and dependencies are shared across all projects in an umbrella, and it is not per application.

The second change is in the application function inside mix.exs:

def application do
  [
    extra_applications: [:logger],
    mod: {KVServer.Application, []}
  ]
end

Because we passed the --sup flag, Mix automatically added mod: {KVServer.Application, []}, specifying that KVServer.Application is our application callback module. KVServer.Application will start our application supervision tree.

In fact, let's open up lib/kv_server/application.ex:

defmodule KVServer.Application do
  # See https://hexdocs.pm/elixir/Application.html
  # for more information on OTP Applications
  @moduledoc false

  use Application

  @impl true
  def start(_type, _args) do
    # List all child processes to be supervised
    children = [
      # Starts a worker by calling: KVServer.Worker.start_link(arg)
      # {KVServer.Worker, arg},
    ]

    # See https://hexdocs.pm/elixir/Supervisor.html
    # for other strategies and supported options
    opts = [strategy: :one_for_one, name: KVServer.Supervisor]
    Supervisor.start_link(children, opts)
  end
end

Notice that it defines the application callback function, start/2, and instead of defining a supervisor named KVServer.Supervisor that uses the Supervisor module, it conveniently defined the supervisor inline! You can read more about such supervisors by reading the Supervisor module documentation.

We can already try out our first umbrella child. We could run tests inside the apps/kv_server directory, but that wouldn't be much fun. Instead, go to the root of the umbrella project and run mix test:

$ mix test

And it works!

Since we want kv_server to eventually use the functionality we defined in kv, we need to add kv as a dependency to our application.

Dependencies within an umbrella project

Dependencies between applications in an umbrella project must still be explicitly defined and Mix makes it easy to do so. Open up apps/kv_server/mix.exs and change the deps/0 function to the following:

defp deps do
  [{:kv, in_umbrella: true}]
end

The line above makes :kv available as a dependency inside :kv_server and automatically starts the :kv application before the server starts.

Finally, copy the kv application we have built so far to the apps directory in our new umbrella project. The final directory structure should match the structure we mentioned earlier:

+ kv_umbrella
  + apps
    + kv
    + kv_server

We now need to modify apps/kv/mix.exs to contain the umbrella entries we have seen in apps/kv_server/mix.exs. Open up apps/kv/mix.exs and add to the project/0 function:

build_path: "../../_build",
config_path: "../../config/config.exs",
deps_path: "../../deps",
lockfile: "../../mix.lock",

Now you can run tests for both projects from the umbrella root with mix test. Sweet!

Don't drink the kool aid

Umbrella projects are a convenience to help you organize and manage multiple applications. While it provides a degree of separation between applications, those applications are not fully decoupled, as they share the same configuration and the same dependencies.

The pattern of keeping multiple applications in the same repository is known as "mono-repo". Umbrella projects maximize this pattern by providing conveniences to compile, test and run multiple applications at once.

If you find yourself in a position where you want to use different configurations in each application for the same dependency or use different dependency versions, then it is likely your codebase has grown beyond what umbrellas can provide.

The good news is that breaking an umbrella apart is quite straightforward, as you simply need to move applications outside of the umbrella project's apps/ directory and update the project's mix.exs file to no longer set the build_path, config_path, deps_path, and lockfile configuration. You can depend on private projects outside of the umbrella in multiple ways:

Move it to a separate folder within the same repository and point to it using a path dependency (the mono-repo pattern)
Move the repository to a separate Git repository and depend on it
Publish the project to a private Hex.pm organization

Summing up

In this chapter, we have learned more about Mix dependencies and umbrella projects. While we may run kv without a server, our kv_server depends directly on kv. By breaking them into separate applications, we gain more control in how they are developed and tested.

When using umbrella applications, it is important to have a clear boundary between them. Our upcoming kv_server must only access public APIs defined in kv. Think of your umbrella apps as any other dependency or even Elixir itself: you can only access what is public and documented. Reaching into private functionality in your dependencies is a poor practice that will eventually cause your code to break when a new version is up.

Umbrella applications can also be used as a stepping stone for eventually extracting an application from your codebase. For example, imagine a web application that has to send "push notifications" to its users. The whole "push notifications system" can be developed as a separate application in the umbrella, with its own supervision tree and APIs. If you ever run into a situation where another project needs the push notifications system, the system can be moved to a private repository or a Hex package.

Finally, keep in mind that applications in an umbrella project all share the same configurations and dependencies. If two applications in your umbrella need to configure the same dependency in drastically different ways or even use different versions, you have probably outgrown the benefits brought by umbrellas. Remember you can break the umbrella and still leverage the benefits behind "mono-repos".

With our umbrella project up and running, it is time to start writing our server.

Kernel

Kernel is Elixir's default environment.

It mainly consists of:

basic language primitives, such as arithmetic operators, spawning of processes, data type handling, and others
macros for control-flow and defining new functionality (modules, functions, and the like)
guard checks for augmenting pattern matching

You can invoke Kernel functions and macros anywhere in Elixir code without the use of the Kernel. prefix since they have all been automatically imported. For example, in IEx, you can call:

iex> is_number(13)
true

If you don't want to import a function or macro from Kernel, use the :except option and then list the function/macro by arity:

import Kernel, except: [if: 2, unless: 2]

See import/2 for more information on importing.

Elixir also has special forms that are always imported and cannot be skipped. These are described in Kernel.SpecialForms.

The standard library

Kernel provides the basic capabilities the Elixir standard library is built on top of. It is recommended to explore the standard library for advanced functionality. Here are the main groups of modules in the standard library (this list is not a complete reference, see the documentation sidebar for all entries).

Built-in types

The following modules handle Elixir built-in data types:

Atom - literal constants with a name (true, false, and nil are atoms)
Float - numbers with floating point precision
Function - a reference to code chunk, created with the fn/1 special form
Integer - whole numbers (not fractions)
List - collections of a variable number of elements (linked lists)
Map - collections of key-value pairs
Process - light-weight threads of execution
Port - mechanisms to interact with the external world
Tuple - collections of a fixed number of elements

There are two data types without an accompanying module:

Bitstring - a sequence of bits, created with <<>>/1. When the number of bits is divisible by 8, they are called binaries and can be manipulated with Erlang's :binary module
Reference - a unique value in the runtime system, created with make_ref/0

Data types

Elixir also provides other data types that are built on top of the types listed above. Some of them are:

Date - year-month-day structs in a given calendar
DateTime - date and time with time zone in a given calendar
Exception - data raised from errors and unexpected scenarios
MapSet - unordered collections of unique elements
NaiveDateTime - date and time without time zone in a given calendar
Keyword - lists of two-element tuples, often representing optional values
Range - inclusive ranges between two integers
Regex - regular expressions
String - UTF-8 encoded binaries representing characters
Time - hour:minute:second structs in a given calendar
URI - representation of URIs that identify resources
Version - representation of versions and requirements

System modules

Modules that interface with the underlying system, such as:

IO - handles input and output
File - interacts with the underlying file system
Path - manipulates file system paths
System - reads and writes system information

Protocols

Protocols add polymorphic dispatch to Elixir. They are contracts implementable by data types. See Protocol for more information on protocols. Elixir provides the following protocols in the standard library:

Collectable - collects data into a data type
Enumerable - handles collections in Elixir. The Enum module provides eager functions for working with collections, the Stream module provides lazy functions
Inspect - converts data types into their programming language representation
List.Chars - converts data types to their outside world representation as charlists (non-programming based)
String.Chars - converts data types to their outside world representation as strings (non-programming based)

Process-based and application-centric functionality

The following modules build on top of processes to provide concurrency, fault-tolerance, and more.

Agent - a process that encapsulates mutable state
Application - functions for starting, stopping and configuring applications
GenServer - a generic client-server API
Registry - a key-value process-based storage
Supervisor - a process that is responsible for starting, supervising and shutting down other processes
Task - a process that performs computations
Task.Supervisor - a supervisor for managing tasks exclusively

Supporting documents

Under the "Pages" section in sidebar you will find tutorials, guides, and reference documents that outline Elixir semantics and behaviors in more detail. Those are:

Compatibility and deprecations - lists compatibility between every Elixir version and Erlang/OTP, release schema; lists all deprecated functions, when they were deprecated and alternatives
Library guidelines - general guidelines, anti-patterns, and rules for those writing libraries
Naming conventions - naming conventions for Elixir code
Operators reference - lists all Elixir operators and their precedences
Patterns and guards - an introduction to patterns, guards, and extensions
Syntax reference - the language syntax reference
Typespecs reference- types and function specifications, including list of types
Unicode syntax - outlines Elixir support for Unicode

Guards

This module includes the built-in guards used by Elixir developers. They are a predefined set of functions and macros that augment pattern matching, typically invoked after the when operator. For example:

def drive(%User{age: age}) when age >= 16 do
  ...
end

The clause above will only be invoked if the user's age is more than or equal to 16. Guards also support joining multiple conditions with and and or. The whole guard is true if all guard expressions will evaluate to true. A more complete introduction to guards is available in the Patterns and guards page.

Truthy and falsy values

Besides the booleans true and false, Elixir has the concept of a "truthy" or "falsy" value.

a value is truthy when it is neither false nor nil
a value is falsy when it is either false or nil

Elixir has functions, like and/2, that only work with booleans, but also functions that work with these truthy/falsy values, like &&/2 and !/1.

Structural comparison

The functions in this module perform structural comparison. This allows different data types to be compared using comparison operators:

1 < :an_atom

This is possible so Elixir developers can create collections, such as dictionaries and ordered sets, that store a mixture of data types in them. To understand why this matters, let's discuss the two types of comparisons we find in software: structural and semantic.

Structural means we are comparing the underlying data structures and we often want those operations to be as fast as possible, because it is used to power several algorithms and data structures in the language. A semantic comparison worries about what each data type represents. For example, semantically speaking, it doesn't make sense to compare Time with Date.

One example that shows the differences between structural and semantic comparisons are strings: "alien" sorts less than "office" ("alien" < "office") but "álien" is greater than "office". This happens because < compares the underlying bytes that form the string. If you were doing alphabetical listing, you may want "álien" to also appear before "office".

This means comparisons in Elixir are structural, as it has the goal of comparing data types as efficiently as possible to create flexible and performant data structures. This distinction is specially important for functions that provide ordering, such as >/2, </2, >=/2, <=/2, min/2, and max/2. For example:

~D[2017-03-31] > ~D[2017-04-01]

will return true because structural comparison compares the :day field before :month or :year. Luckily, the Elixir compiler will detect whenever comparing structs or whenever comparing code that is either always true or false, and emit a warning accordingly.

In order to perform semantic comparisons, the relevant data-types provide a compare/2 function, such as Date.compare/2:

iex> Date.compare(~D[2017-03-31], ~D[2017-04-01])
:lt

Alternatively, you can use the functions in the Enum module to sort or compute a maximum/minimum:

iex> Enum.sort([~D[2017-03-31], ~D[2017-04-01]], Date)
[~D[2017-03-31], ~D[2017-04-01]]
iex> Enum.max([~D[2017-03-31], ~D[2017-04-01]], Date)
~D[2017-04-01]

The second argument is precisely the module to be used for semantic comparison. Keeping this distinction is important, because if semantic comparison was used by default for implementing data structures and algorithms, they could become orders of magnitude slower!

Finally, note there is an overall structural sorting order, called "Term Ordering", defined below. This order is provided for reference purposes, it is not required by Elixir developers to know it by heart.

Term ordering

number < atom < reference < function < port < pid < tuple < map < list < bitstring

When comparing two numbers of different types (a number being either an integer or a float), a conversion to the type with greater precision will always occur, unless the comparison operator used is either ===/2 or !==/2. A float will be considered more precise than an integer, unless the float is greater/less than +/-9007199254740992.0 respectively, at which point all the significant figures of the float are to the left of the decimal point. This behavior exists so that the comparison of large numbers remains transitive.

The collection types are compared using the following rules:

Tuples are compared by size, then element by element.
Maps are compared by size, then by key-value pairs.
Lists are compared element by element.
Bitstrings are compared byte by byte, incomplete bytes are compared bit by bit.
Atoms are compared using their string value, codepoint by codepoint.

Examples

We can check the truthiness of a value by using the !/1 function twice.

Truthy values:

iex> !!true
true
iex> !!5
true
iex> !![1,2]
true
iex> !!"foo"
true

Falsy values (of which there are exactly two):

iex> !!false
false
iex> !!nil
false

Inlining

Some of the functions described in this module are inlined by the Elixir compiler into their Erlang counterparts in the :erlang module. Those functions are called BIFs (built-in internal functions) in Erlang-land and they exhibit interesting properties, as some of them are allowed in guards and others are used for compiler optimizations.

Most of the inlined functions can be seen in effect when capturing the function:

iex> &Kernel.is_atom/1
&:erlang.is_atom/1

Those functions will be explicitly marked in their docs as "inlined by the compiler".

Summary

Guards

left * right

Arithmetic multiplication operator.

+value

Arithmetic positive unary operator.

left + right

Arithmetic addition operator.

-value

Arithmetic negative unary operator.

left - right

Arithmetic subtraction operator.

left / right

Arithmetic division operator.

left != right

Not equal to operator.

left !== right

Strictly not equal to operator.

left < right

Less-than operator.

left <= right

Less-than or equal to operator.

left == right

Equal to operator. Returns true if the two terms are equal.

left === right

Strictly equal to operator.

left > right

Greater-than operator.

left >= right

Greater-than or equal to operator.

abs(number)

Returns an integer or float which is the arithmetical absolute value of number.

left and right

Strictly boolean "and" operator.

binary_part(binary, start, size)

Extracts the part of the binary at start with size.

bit_size(bitstring)

Returns an integer which is the size in bits of bitstring.

byte_size(bitstring)

Returns the number of bytes needed to contain bitstring.

ceil(number)

Returns the smallest integer greater than or equal to number.

div(dividend, divisor)

Performs an integer division.

elem(tuple, index)

Gets the element at the zero-based index in tuple.

floor(number)

Returns the largest integer smaller than or equal to number.

hd(list)

Returns the head of a list. Raises ArgumentError if the list is empty.

left in right

Membership operator.

is_atom(term)

Returns true if term is an atom, otherwise returns false.

is_binary(term)

Returns true if term is a binary, otherwise returns false.

is_bitstring(term)

Returns true if term is a bitstring (including a binary), otherwise returns false.

is_boolean(term)

Returns true if term is either the atom true or the atom false (i.e., a boolean), otherwise returns false.

is_exception(term)

Returns true if term is an exception, otherwise returns false.

is_exception(term, name)

Returns true if term is an exception of name, otherwise returns false.

is_float(term)

Returns true if term is a floating-point number, otherwise returns false.

is_function(term)

Returns true if term is a function, otherwise returns false.

is_function(term, arity)

Returns true if term is a function that can be applied with arity number of arguments; otherwise returns false.

is_integer(term)

Returns true if term is an integer, otherwise returns false.

is_list(term)

Returns true if term is a list with zero or more elements, otherwise returns false.

is_map(term)

Returns true if term is a map, otherwise returns false.

is_map_key(map, key)

Returns true if key is a key in map, otherwise returns false.

is_nil(term)

Returns true if term is nil, false otherwise.

is_non_struct_map(term)

Returns true if term is a map that is not a struct, otherwise returns false.

is_number(term)

Returns true if term is either an integer or a floating-point number; otherwise returns false.

is_pid(term)

Returns true if term is a PID (process identifier), otherwise returns false.

is_port(term)

Returns true if term is a port identifier, otherwise returns false.

is_reference(term)

Returns true if term is a reference, otherwise returns false.

is_struct(term)

Returns true if term is a struct, otherwise returns false.

is_struct(term, name)

Returns true if term is a struct of name, otherwise returns false.

is_tuple(term)

Returns true if term is a tuple, otherwise returns false.

length(list)

Returns the length of list.

map_size(map)

Returns the size of a map.

node()

Returns an atom representing the name of the local node. If the node is not alive, :nonode@nohost is returned instead.

node(arg)

Returns the node where the given argument is located. The argument can be a PID, a reference, or a port. If the local node is not alive, :nonode@nohost is returned.

not value

Strictly boolean "not" operator.

left or right

Strictly boolean "or" operator.

rem(dividend, divisor)

Computes the remainder of an integer division.

round(number)

Rounds a number to the nearest integer.

self()

Returns the PID (process identifier) of the calling process.

tl(list)

Returns the tail of a list. Raises ArgumentError if the list is empty.

trunc(number)

Returns the integer part of number.

tuple_size(tuple)

Returns the size of a tuple.

Functions

left && right

Boolean "and" operator.

base ** exponent

Power operator.

left ++ right

List concatenation operator. Concatenates a proper list and a term, returning a list.

left -- right

List subtraction operator. Removes the first occurrence of an element on the left list for each element on the right.

..

Creates the full-slice range 0..-1//1.

first..last

Creates a range from first to last.

first..last//step

Creates a range from first to last with step.

!value

Boolean "not" operator.

left <> right

Binary concatenation operator. Concatenates two binaries.

left =~ right

Text-based match operator. Matches the term on the left against the regular expression or string on the right.

@expr

Module attribute unary operator.

alias!(alias)

When used inside quoting, marks that the given alias should not be hygienized. This means the alias will be expanded when the macro is expanded.

apply(fun, args)

Invokes the given anonymous function fun with the list of arguments args.

apply(module, function_name, args)

Invokes the given function from module with the list of arguments args.

binary_slice(binary, range)

Returns a binary from the offset given by the start of the range to the offset given by the end of the range.

binary_slice(binary, start, size)

Returns a binary starting at the offset start and of the given size.

binding(context \\ nil)

Returns the binding for the given context as a keyword list.

dbg(code \\ quote do binding() end, options \\ [])

Debugs the given code.

def(call, expr \\ nil)

Defines a public function with the given name and body.

defdelegate(funs, opts)

Defines a function that delegates to another module.

defexception(fields)

Defines an exception.

defguard(guard)

Defines a macro suitable for use in guard expressions.

defguardp(guard)

Defines a private macro suitable for use in guard expressions.

defimpl(name, opts, do_block \\ [])

Defines an implementation for the given protocol.

defmacro(call, expr \\ nil)

Defines a public macro with the given name and body.

defmacrop(call, expr \\ nil)

Defines a private macro with the given name and body.

defmodule(alias, do_block)

Defines a module given by name with the given contents.

defoverridable(keywords_or_behaviour)

Makes the given definitions in the current module overridable.

defp(call, expr \\ nil)

Defines a private function with the given name and body.

defprotocol(name, do_block)

Defines a protocol.

defstruct(fields)

Defines a struct.

destructure(left, right)

Destructures two lists, assigning each term in the right one to the matching term in the left one.

exit(reason)

Stops the execution of the calling process with the given reason.

function_exported?(module, function, arity)

Returns true if module is loaded and contains a public function with the given arity, otherwise false.

get_and_update_in(path, fun)

Gets a value and updates a nested data structure via the given path.

get_and_update_in(data, keys, fun)

Gets a value and updates a nested structure.

get_in(path)

Gets a key from the nested structure via the given path, with nil-safe handling.

get_in(data, keys)

Gets a value from a nested structure with nil-safe handling.

if(condition, clauses)

Provides an if/2 macro.

inspect(term, opts \\ [])

Inspects the given argument according to the Inspect protocol. The second argument is a keyword list with options to control inspection.

macro_exported?(module, macro, arity)

Returns true if module is loaded and contains a public macro with the given arity, otherwise false.

make_ref()

Returns an almost unique reference.

match?(pattern, expr)

A convenience macro that checks if the right side (an expression) matches the left side (a pattern).

max(first, second)

Returns the biggest of the two given terms according to their structural comparison.

min(first, second)

Returns the smallest of the two given terms according to their structural comparison.

pop_in(path)

Pops a key from the nested structure via the given path.

pop_in(data, keys)

Pops a key from the given nested structure.

put_elem(tuple, index, value)

Puts value at the given zero-based index in tuple.

put_in(path, value)

Puts a value in a nested structure via the given path.

put_in(data, keys, value)

Puts a value in a nested structure.

raise(message)

Raises an exception.

raise(exception, attributes)

Raises an exception.

reraise(message, stacktrace)

Raises an exception preserving a previous stacktrace.

reraise(exception, attributes, stacktrace)

Raises an exception preserving a previous stacktrace.

send(dest, message)

Sends a message to the given dest and returns the message.

sigil_C(term, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~C for charlists.

sigil_c(term, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~c for charlists.

sigil_D(date_string, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~D for dates.

sigil_N(naive_datetime_string, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~N for naive date times.

sigil_r(term, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~r for regular expressions.

sigil_S(term, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~S for strings.

sigil_s(term, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~s for strings.

sigil_T(time_string, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~T for times.

sigil_U(datetime_string, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~U to create a UTC DateTime.

sigil_W(term, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~W for list of words.

sigil_w(term, modifiers)

Handles the sigil ~w for list of words.

spawn(fun)

Spawns the given function and returns its PID.

spawn(module, fun, args)

Spawns the given function fun from the given module passing it the given args and returns its PID.

spawn_link(fun)

Spawns the given function, links it to the current process, and returns its PID.

spawn_link(module, fun, args)

Spawns the given function fun from the given module passing it the given args, links it to the current process, and returns its PID.

spawn_monitor(fun)

Spawns the given function, monitors it and returns its PID and monitoring reference.

spawn_monitor(module, fun, args)

Spawns the given module and function passing the given args, monitors it and returns its PID and monitoring reference.

struct(struct, fields \\ [])

Creates and updates a struct.

struct!(struct, fields \\ [])

Similar to struct/2 but checks for key validity.

tap(value, fun)

Pipes the first argument, value, into the second argument, a function fun, and returns value itself.

then(value, fun)

Pipes the first argument, value, into the second argument, a function fun, and returns the result of calling fun.

throw(term)

A non-local return from a function.

to_charlist(term)

Converts the given term to a charlist according to the List.Chars protocol.

to_string(term)

Converts the argument to a string according to the String.Chars protocol.

to_timeout(duration)

Constructs a millisecond timeout from the given components, duration, or timeout.

unless(condition, clauses) deprecated

Provides an unless macro.

update_in(path, fun)

Updates a nested structure via the given path.

update_in(data, keys, fun)

Updates a key in a nested structure.

use(module, opts \\ [])

Uses the given module in the current context.

var!(var, context \\ nil)

Marks that the given variable should not be hygienized.

left |> right

Pipe operator.

left || right

Boolean "or" operator.

Guards

left * right

@spec integer() * integer() :: integer()

@spec float() * float() :: float()

@spec integer() * float() :: float()

@spec float() * integer() :: float()

Arithmetic multiplication operator.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 * 2
2

+value

@spec +integer() :: integer()

@spec +float() :: float()

Arithmetic positive unary operator.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> +1
1

left + right

@spec integer() + integer() :: integer()

@spec float() + float() :: float()

@spec integer() + float() :: float()

@spec float() + integer() :: float()

Arithmetic addition operator.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 + 2
3

-value

@spec -0 :: 0

@spec -pos_integer() :: neg_integer()

@spec -neg_integer() :: pos_integer()

@spec -float() :: float()

Arithmetic negative unary operator.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> -2
-2

left - right

@spec integer() - integer() :: integer()

@spec float() - float() :: float()

@spec integer() - float() :: float()

@spec float() - integer() :: float()

Arithmetic subtraction operator.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 - 2
-1

left / right

@spec number() / number() :: float()

Arithmetic division operator.

The result is always a float. Use div/2 and rem/2 if you want an integer division or the remainder.

Raises ArithmeticError if right is 0 or 0.0.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

1 / 2
#=> 0.5

-3.0 / 2.0
#=> -1.5

5 / 1
#=> 5.0

7 / 0
** (ArithmeticError) bad argument in arithmetic expression

left != right

@spec term() != term() :: boolean()

Not equal to operator.

Returns true if the two terms are not equal.

This operator considers 1 and 1.0 to be equal. For match comparison, use !==/2 instead.

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 != 2
true

iex> 1 != 1.0
false

left !== right

@spec term() !== term() :: boolean()

Strictly not equal to operator.

Returns true if the two terms are not exactly equal. See ===/2 for a definition of what is considered "exactly equal".

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 !== 2
true

iex> 1 !== 1.0
true

left < right

@spec term() < term() :: boolean()

Less-than operator.

Returns true if left is less than right.

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 < 2
true

left <= right

@spec term() <= term() :: boolean()

Less-than or equal to operator.

Returns true if left is less than or equal to right.

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 <= 2
true

left == right

@spec term() == term() :: boolean()

Equal to operator. Returns true if the two terms are equal.

This operator considers 1 and 1.0 to be equal. For stricter semantics, use ===/2 instead.

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 == 2
false

iex> 1 == 1.0
true

left === right

@spec term() === term() :: boolean()

Strictly equal to operator.

Returns true if the two terms are exactly equal.

The terms are only considered to be exactly equal if they have the same value and are of the same type. For example, 1 == 1.0 returns true, but since they are of different types, 1 === 1.0 returns false.

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 === 2
false

iex> 1 === 1.0
false

left > right

@spec term() > term() :: boolean()

Greater-than operator.

Returns true if left is more than right.

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 > 2
false

left >= right

@spec term() >= term() :: boolean()

Greater-than or equal to operator.

Returns true if left is more than or equal to right.

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> 1 >= 2
false

abs(number)

@spec abs(number()) :: number()

Returns an integer or float which is the arithmetical absolute value of number.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> abs(-3.33)
3.33

iex> abs(-3)
3

left and right

(macro)

Strictly boolean "and" operator.

If left is false, returns false, otherwise returns right.

Requires only the left operand to be a boolean since it short-circuits. If the left operand is not a boolean, a BadBooleanError exception is raised.

Allowed in guard tests.

Examples

iex> true and false
false

iex> true and "yay!"
"yay!"

iex> "yay!" and true
** (BadBooleanError) expected a boolean on left-side of "and", got: "yay!"

binary_part(binary, start, size)

@spec binary_part(binary(), non_neg_integer(), integer()) :: binary()

Extracts the part of the binary at start with size.

If start or size reference in any way outside the binary, an ArgumentError exception is raised.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> binary_part("foo", 1, 2)
"oo"

A negative size can be used to extract bytes that come before the byte at start:

iex> binary_part("Hello", 5, -3)
"llo"

An ArgumentError is raised when the size is outside of the binary:

binary_part("Hello", 0, 10)
** (ArgumentError) argument error

bit_size(bitstring)

@spec bit_size(bitstring()) :: non_neg_integer()

Returns an integer which is the size in bits of bitstring.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> bit_size(<<433::16, 3::3>>)
19

iex> bit_size(<<1, 2, 3>>)
24

byte_size(bitstring)

@spec byte_size(bitstring()) :: non_neg_integer()

Returns the number of bytes needed to contain bitstring.

That is, if the number of bits in bitstring is not divisible by 8, the resulting number of bytes will be rounded up (by excess). This operation happens in constant time.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> byte_size(<<433::16, 3::3>>)
3

iex> byte_size(<<1, 2, 3>>)
3

ceil(number)

(since 1.8.0)

@spec ceil(number()) :: integer()

Returns the smallest integer greater than or equal to number.

If you want to perform ceil operation on other decimal places, use Float.ceil/2 instead.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> ceil(10)
10

iex> ceil(10.1)
11

iex> ceil(-10.1)
-10

div(dividend, divisor)

@spec div(integer(), neg_integer() | pos_integer()) :: integer()

Performs an integer division.

Raises an ArithmeticError exception if one of the arguments is not an integer, or when the divisor is 0.

div/2 performs truncated integer division. This means that the result is always rounded towards zero.

If you want to perform floored integer division (rounding towards negative infinity), use Integer.floor_div/2 instead.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

div(5, 2)
#=> 2

div(6, -4)
#=> -1

div(-99, 2)
#=> -49

div(100, 0)
** (ArithmeticError) bad argument in arithmetic expression

elem(tuple, index)

@spec elem(tuple(), non_neg_integer()) :: term()

Gets the element at the zero-based index in tuple.

It raises ArgumentError when index is negative or it is out of range of the tuple elements.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

tuple = {:foo, :bar, 3}
elem(tuple, 1)
#=> :bar

elem({}, 0)
** (ArgumentError) argument error

elem({:foo, :bar}, 2)
** (ArgumentError) argument error

floor(number)

(since 1.8.0)

@spec floor(number()) :: integer()

Returns the largest integer smaller than or equal to number.

If you want to perform floor operation on other decimal places, use Float.floor/2 instead.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> floor(10)
10

iex> floor(9.7)
9

iex> floor(-9.7)
-10

hd(list)

@spec hd(nonempty_maybe_improper_list(elem, term())) :: elem when elem: term()

Returns the head of a list. Raises ArgumentError if the list is empty.

The head of a list is its first element.

It works with improper lists.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

hd([1, 2, 3, 4])
#=> 1

hd([1 | 2])
#=> 1

Giving it an empty list raises:

hd([])
** (ArgumentError) argument error

left in right

(macro)

Membership operator.

Checks if the element on the left-hand side is a member of the collection on the right-hand side.

Examples

iex> x = 1
iex> x in [1, 2, 3]
true

This operator (which is a macro) simply translates to a call to Enum.member?/2. The example above would translate to:

Enum.member?([1, 2, 3], x)

Elixir also supports left not in right, which evaluates to not(left in right):

iex> x = 1
iex> x not in [1, 2, 3]
false

Guards

The in/2 operator (as well as not in) can be used in guard clauses as long as the right-hand side is a range or a list.

If the right-hand side is a list, Elixir will expand the operator to a valid guard expression which needs to check each value. For example:

when x in [1, 2, 3]

translates to:

when x === 1 or x === 2 or x === 3

However, this construct will be inefficient for large lists. In such cases, it is best to stop using guards and use a more appropriate data structure, such as MapSet.

If the right-hand side is a range, a more efficient comparison check will be done. For example:

when x in 1..1000

translates roughly to:

when x >= 1 and x <= 1000

AST considerations

left not in right is parsed by the compiler into the AST:

{:not, _, [{:in, _, [left, right]}]}

This is the same AST as not(left in right).

Additionally, Macro.to_string/2 and Code.format_string!/2 will translate all occurrences of this AST to left not in right.

is_atom(term)

@spec is_atom(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is an atom, otherwise returns false.

Note true, false, and nil are atoms in Elixir, as well as module names. Therefore this function will return true to all of those values.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> is_atom(:name)
true

iex> is_atom(false)
true

iex> is_atom(AnAtom)
true

iex> is_atom("string")
false

is_binary(term)

@spec is_binary(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a binary, otherwise returns false.

A binary always contains a complete number of bytes.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> is_binary("foo")
true
iex> is_binary(<<1::3>>)
false

is_bitstring(term)

@spec is_bitstring(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a bitstring (including a binary), otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> is_bitstring("foo")
true
iex> is_bitstring(<<1::3>>)
true

is_boolean(term)

@spec is_boolean(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is either the atom true or the atom false (i.e., a boolean), otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> is_boolean(false)
true

iex> is_boolean(true)
true

iex> is_boolean(:test)
false

is_exception(term)

(since 1.11.0) (macro)

Returns true if term is an exception, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests.

Examples

iex> is_exception(%RuntimeError{})
true

iex> is_exception(%{})
false

is_exception(term, name)

(since 1.11.0) (macro)

Returns true if term is an exception of name, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests.

Examples

iex> is_exception(%RuntimeError{}, RuntimeError)
true

iex> is_exception(%RuntimeError{}, Macro.Env)
false

is_float(term)

@spec is_float(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a floating-point number, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

is_function(term)

@spec is_function(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a function, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> is_function(fn x -> x + x end)
true

iex> is_function("not a function")
false

is_function(term, arity)

@spec is_function(term(), non_neg_integer()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a function that can be applied with arity number of arguments; otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> is_function(fn x -> x * 2 end, 1)
true
iex> is_function(fn x -> x * 2 end, 2)
false

is_integer(term)

@spec is_integer(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is an integer, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

is_list(term)

@spec is_list(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a list with zero or more elements, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

is_map(term)

@spec is_map(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a map, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Structs are maps

Structs are also maps, and many of Elixir data structures are implemented using structs: Ranges, Regexes, Dates...

iex> is_map(1..10)
true
iex> is_map(~D[2024-04-18])
true

If you mean to specifically check for non-struct maps, use is_non_struct_map/1 instead.

iex> is_non_struct_map(1..10)
false

is_map_key(map, key)

(since 1.10.0)

@spec is_map_key(map(), term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if key is a key in map, otherwise returns false.

It raises BadMapError if the first element is not a map.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> is_map_key(%{a: "foo", b: "bar"}, :a)
true

iex> is_map_key(%{a: "foo", b: "bar"}, :c)
false

is_nil(term)

(macro)

Returns true if term is nil, false otherwise.

Allowed in guard clauses.

Examples

iex> is_nil(1 + 2)
false

iex> is_nil(nil)
true

is_non_struct_map(term)

(since 1.17.0) (macro)

Returns true if term is a map that is not a struct, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests.

Examples

iex> is_non_struct_map(%{})
true

iex> is_non_struct_map(URI.parse("/"))
false

iex> is_non_struct_map(nil)
false

is_number(term)

@spec is_number(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is either an integer or a floating-point number; otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

is_pid(term)

@spec is_pid(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a PID (process identifier), otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

is_port(term)

@spec is_port(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a port identifier, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

is_reference(term)

@spec is_reference(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a reference, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

is_struct(term)

(since 1.10.0) (macro)

Returns true if term is a struct, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests.

Examples

iex> is_struct(URI.parse("/"))
true

iex> is_struct(%{})
false

is_struct(term, name)

(since 1.11.0) (macro)

Returns true if term is a struct of name, otherwise returns false.

is_struct/2 does not check that name exists and is a valid struct. If you want such validations, you must pattern match on the struct instead, such as match?(%URI{}, arg).

Allowed in guard tests.

Examples

iex> is_struct(URI.parse("/"), URI)
true

iex> is_struct(URI.parse("/"), Macro.Env)
false

is_tuple(term)

@spec is_tuple(term()) :: boolean()

Returns true if term is a tuple, otherwise returns false.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

length(list)

@spec length(list()) :: non_neg_integer()

Returns the length of list.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> length([1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9])
9

map_size(map)

@spec map_size(map()) :: non_neg_integer()

Returns the size of a map.

The size of a map is the number of key-value pairs that the map contains.

This operation happens in constant time.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> map_size(%{a: "foo", b: "bar"})
2

node()

@spec node() :: node()

Returns an atom representing the name of the local node. If the node is not alive, :nonode@nohost is returned instead.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

node(arg)

@spec node(pid() | reference() | port()) :: node()

Returns the node where the given argument is located. The argument can be a PID, a reference, or a port. If the local node is not alive, :nonode@nohost is returned.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

not value

@spec not true :: false

@spec not false :: true

Strictly boolean "not" operator.

value must be a boolean; if it's not, an ArgumentError exception is raised.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> not false
true

left or right

(macro)

Strictly boolean "or" operator.

If left is true, returns true, otherwise returns right.

Requires only the left operand to be a boolean since it short-circuits. If the left operand is not a boolean, a BadBooleanError exception is raised.

Allowed in guard tests.

Examples

iex> true or false
true

iex> false or 42
42

iex> 42 or false
** (BadBooleanError) expected a boolean on left-side of "or", got: 42

rem(dividend, divisor)

@spec rem(integer(), neg_integer() | pos_integer()) :: integer()

Computes the remainder of an integer division.

rem/2 uses truncated division, which means that the result will always have the sign of the dividend.

Raises an ArithmeticError exception if one of the arguments is not an integer, or when the divisor is 0.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> rem(5, 2)
1
iex> rem(6, -4)
2

round(number)

@spec round(number()) :: integer()

Rounds a number to the nearest integer.

If the number is equidistant to the two nearest integers, rounds away from zero.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> round(5.6)
6

iex> round(5.2)
5

iex> round(-9.9)
-10

iex> round(-9)
-9

iex> round(2.5)
3

iex> round(-2.5)
-3

self()

@spec self() :: pid()

Returns the PID (process identifier) of the calling process.

Allowed in guard clauses. Inlined by the compiler.

tl(list)

@spec tl(nonempty_maybe_improper_list(elem, last)) ::
  maybe_improper_list(elem, last) | last
when elem: term(), last: term()

Returns the tail of a list. Raises ArgumentError if the list is empty.

The tail of a list is the list without its first element.

It works with improper lists.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

tl([1, 2, 3, :go])
#=> [2, 3, :go]

tl([:one])
#=> []

tl([:a, :b | :improper_end])
#=> [:b | :improper_end]

tl([:a | %{b: 1}])
#=> %{b: 1}

Giving it an empty list raises:

tl([])
** (ArgumentError) argument error

trunc(number)

@spec trunc(number()) :: integer()

Returns the integer part of number.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> trunc(5.4)
5

iex> trunc(-5.99)
-5

iex> trunc(-5)
-5

tuple_size(tuple)

@spec tuple_size(tuple()) :: non_neg_integer()

Returns the size of a tuple.

This operation happens in constant time.

Allowed in guard tests. Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> tuple_size({:a, :b, :c})
3

Functions

left && right

(macro)

Boolean "and" operator.

Provides a short-circuit operator that evaluates and returns the second expression only if the first one evaluates to a truthy value (neither false nor nil). Returns the first expression otherwise.

Not allowed in guard clauses.

Examples

iex> Enum.empty?([]) && Enum.empty?([])
true

iex> List.first([]) && true
nil

iex> Enum.empty?([]) && List.first([1])
1

iex> false && throw(:bad)
false

Note that, unlike and/2, this operator accepts any expression as the first argument, not only booleans.

base ** exponent

(since 1.13.0)

@spec integer() ** non_neg_integer() :: integer()

@spec integer() ** neg_integer() :: float()

@spec float() ** float() :: float()

@spec integer() ** float() :: float()

@spec float() ** integer() :: float()

Power operator.

It takes two numbers for input. If both are integers and the right-hand side (the exponent) is also greater than or equal to 0, then the result will also be an integer. Otherwise it returns a float.

Examples

iex> 2 ** 2
4
iex> 2 ** -4
0.0625

iex> 2.0 ** 2
4.0
iex> 2 ** 2.0
4.0

left ++ right

@spec [] ++ a :: a when a: term()

@spec [...] ++ term() :: maybe_improper_list()

List concatenation operator. Concatenates a proper list and a term, returning a list.

The complexity of a ++ b is proportional to length(a), so avoid repeatedly appending to lists of arbitrary length, for example, list ++ [element]. Instead, consider prepending via [element | rest] and then reversing.

If the right operand is not a proper list, it returns an improper list. If the left operand is not a proper list, it raises ArgumentError. If the left operand is an empty list, it returns the right operand.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> [1] ++ [2, 3]
[1, 2, 3]

iex> ~c"foo" ++ ~c"bar"
~c"foobar"

# a non-list on the right will return an improper list
# with said element at the end
iex> [1, 2] ++ 3
[1, 2 | 3]
iex> [1, 2] ++ {3, 4}
[1, 2 | {3, 4}]

# improper list on the right will return an improper list
iex> [1] ++ [2 | 3]
[1, 2 | 3]

# empty list on the left will return the right operand
iex> [] ++ 1
1

The ++/2 operator is right associative, meaning:

iex> [1, 2, 3] -- [1] ++ [2]
[3]

As it is equivalent to:

iex> [1, 2, 3] -- ([1] ++ [2])
[3]

left -- right

@spec list() -- list() :: list()

List subtraction operator. Removes the first occurrence of an element on the left list for each element on the right.

This function is optimized so the complexity of a -- b is proportional to length(a) * log(length(b)). See also the Erlang efficiency guide.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> [1, 2, 3] -- [1, 2]
[3]

iex> [1, 2, 3, 2, 1] -- [1, 2, 2]
[3, 1]

The --/2 operator is right associative, meaning:

iex> [1, 2, 3] -- [2] -- [3]
[1, 3]

As it is equivalent to:

iex> [1, 2, 3] -- ([2] -- [3])
[1, 3]

..

(since 1.14.0) (macro)

Creates the full-slice range 0..-1//1.

This macro returns a range with the following properties:

When enumerated, it is empty

When used as a slice, it returns the sliced element as is

See ..///3 and the Range module for more information.

Examples

iex> Enum.to_list(..)
[]

iex> String.slice("Hello world!", ..)
"Hello world!"

first..last

(macro)

Creates a range from first to last.

If first is less than last, the range will be increasing from first to last. If first is equal to last, the range will contain one element, which is the number itself.

If first is more than last, the range will be decreasing from first to last, albeit this behavior is deprecated. Instead prefer to explicitly list the step with first..last//-1.

See the Range module for more information.

Examples

iex> 0 in 1..3
false
iex> 2 in 1..3
true

iex> Enum.to_list(1..3)
[1, 2, 3]

first..last//step

(since 1.12.0) (macro)

Creates a range from first to last with step.

See the Range module for more information.

Examples

iex> 0 in 1..3//1
false
iex> 2 in 1..3//1
true
iex> 2 in 1..3//2
false

iex> Enum.to_list(1..3//1)
[1, 2, 3]
iex> Enum.to_list(1..3//2)
[1, 3]
iex> Enum.to_list(3..1//-1)
[3, 2, 1]
iex> Enum.to_list(1..0//1)
[]

!value

(macro)

Boolean "not" operator.

Receives any value (not just booleans) and returns true if value is false or nil; returns false otherwise.

Not allowed in guard clauses.

Examples

iex> !Enum.empty?([])
false

iex> !List.first([])
true

left <> right

(macro)

Binary concatenation operator. Concatenates two binaries.

Raises an ArgumentError if one of the sides aren't binaries.

Examples

iex> "foo" <> "bar"
"foobar"

The <>/2 operator can also be used in pattern matching (and guard clauses) as long as the left argument is a literal binary:

iex> "foo" <> x = "foobar"
iex> x
"bar"

x <> "bar" = "foobar" would result in an ArgumentError exception.

left =~ right

@spec String.t() =~ (String.t() | Regex.t()) :: boolean()

Text-based match operator. Matches the term on the left against the regular expression or string on the right.

If right is a regular expression, returns true if left matches right.

If right is a string, returns true if left contains right.

Examples

iex> "abcd" =~ ~r/c(d)/
true

iex> "abcd" =~ ~r/e/
false

iex> "abcd" =~ ~r//
true

iex> "abcd" =~ "bc"
true

iex> "abcd" =~ "ad"
false

iex> "abcd" =~ "abcd"
true

iex> "abcd" =~ ""
true

For more information about regular expressions, please check the Regex module.

@expr

(macro)

Module attribute unary operator.

Reads and writes attributes in the current module.

The canonical example for attributes is annotating that a module implements an OTP behaviour, such as GenServer:

defmodule MyServer do
  @behaviour GenServer
  # ... callbacks ...
end

By default Elixir supports all the module attributes supported by Erlang, but custom attributes can be used as well:

defmodule MyServer do
  @my_data 13
  IO.inspect(@my_data)
  #=> 13
end

Unlike Erlang, such attributes are not stored in the module by default since it is common in Elixir to use custom attributes to store temporary data that will be available at compile-time. Custom attributes may be configured to behave closer to Erlang by using Module.register_attribute/3.

Prefixing module attributes

Libraries and frameworks should consider prefixing any module attributes that are private by underscore, such as @_my_data, so code completion tools do not show them on suggestions and prompts.

Finally, note that attributes can also be read inside functions:

defmodule MyServer do
  @my_data 11
  def first_data, do: @my_data
  @my_data 13
  def second_data, do: @my_data
end

MyServer.first_data()
#=> 11

MyServer.second_data()
#=> 13

It is important to note that reading an attribute takes a snapshot of its current value. In other words, the value is read at compilation time and not at runtime. Check the Module module for other functions to manipulate module attributes.

Attention! Multiple references of the same attribute

As mentioned above, every time you read a module attribute, a snapshot of its current value is taken. Therefore, if you are storing large values inside module attributes (for example, embedding external files in module attributes), you should avoid referencing the same attribute multiple times. For example, don't do this:

@files %{
  example1: File.read!("lib/example1.data"),
  example2: File.read!("lib/example2.data")
}

def example1, do: @files[:example1]
def example2, do: @files[:example2]

In the above, each reference to @files may end-up with a complete and individual copy of the whole @files module attribute. Instead, reference the module attribute once in a private function:

@files %{
  example1: File.read!("lib/example1.data"),
  example2: File.read!("lib/example2.data")
}

defp files(), do: @files
def example1, do: files()[:example1]
def example2, do: files()[:example2]

alias!(alias)

(macro)

When used inside quoting, marks that the given alias should not be hygienized. This means the alias will be expanded when the macro is expanded.

Check quote/2 for more information.

apply(fun, args)

@spec apply(fun(), [any()]) :: any()

Invokes the given anonymous function fun with the list of arguments args.

If the number of arguments is known at compile time, prefer fun.(arg_1, arg_2, ..., arg_n) as it is clearer than apply(fun, [arg_1, arg_2, ..., arg_n]).

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> apply(fn x -> x * 2 end, [2])
4

apply(module, function_name, args)

@spec apply(module(), function_name :: atom(), [any()]) :: any()

Invokes the given function from module with the list of arguments args.

apply/3 is used to invoke functions where the module, function name or arguments are defined dynamically at runtime. For this reason, you can't invoke macros using apply/3, only functions.

If the number of arguments and the function name are known at compile time, prefer module.function(arg_1, arg_2, ..., arg_n) as it is clearer than apply(module, :function, [arg_1, arg_2, ..., arg_n]).

apply/3 cannot be used to call private functions.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> apply(Enum, :reverse, [[1, 2, 3]])
[3, 2, 1]

binary_slice(binary, range)

(since 1.14.0)

Returns a binary from the offset given by the start of the range to the offset given by the end of the range.

If the start or end of the range are negative, they are converted into positive indices based on the binary size. For example, -1 means the last byte of the binary.

This is similar to binary_part/3 except that it works with ranges and it is not allowed in guards.

This function works with bytes. For a slicing operation that considers characters, see String.slice/2.

Examples

iex> binary_slice("elixir", 0..5)
"elixir"
iex> binary_slice("elixir", 1..3)
"lix"
iex> binary_slice("elixir", 1..10)
"lixir"

iex> binary_slice("elixir", -4..-1)
"ixir"
iex> binary_slice("elixir", -4..6)
"ixir"
iex> binary_slice("elixir", -10..10)
"elixir"

For ranges where start > stop, you need to explicitly mark them as increasing:

iex> binary_slice("elixir", 2..-1//1)
"ixir"
iex> binary_slice("elixir", 1..-2//1)
"lixi"

You can use ../0 as a shortcut for 0..-1//1, which returns the whole binary as is:

iex> binary_slice("elixir", ..)
"elixir"

The step can be any positive number. For example, to get every 2 characters of the binary:

iex> binary_slice("elixir", 0..-1//2)
"eii"

If the first position is after the string ends or after the last position of the range, it returns an empty string:

iex> binary_slice("elixir", 10..3//1)
""
iex> binary_slice("elixir", -10..-7)
""
iex> binary_slice("a", 1..1500)
""

binary_slice(binary, start, size)

(since 1.14.0)

Returns a binary starting at the offset start and of the given size.

This is similar to binary_part/3 except that if start + size is greater than the binary size, it automatically clips it to the binary size instead of raising. Opposite to binary_part/3, this function is not allowed in guards.

This function works with bytes. For a slicing operation that considers characters, see String.slice/3.

Examples

iex> binary_slice("elixir", 0, 6)
"elixir"
iex> binary_slice("elixir", 0, 5)
"elixi"
iex> binary_slice("elixir", 1, 4)
"lixi"
iex> binary_slice("elixir", 0, 10)
"elixir"

If start is negative, it is normalized against the binary size and clamped to 0:

iex> binary_slice("elixir", -3, 10)
"xir"
iex> binary_slice("elixir", -10, 10)
"elixir"

If the size is zero, an empty binary is returned:

iex> binary_slice("elixir", 1, 0)
""

If start is greater than or equal to the binary size, an empty binary is returned:

iex> binary_slice("elixir", 10, 10)
""

binding(context \\ nil)

(macro)

Returns the binding for the given context as a keyword list.

In the returned result, keys are variable names and values are the corresponding variable values.

If the given context is nil (by default it is), the binding for the current context is returned.

Examples

iex> x = 1
iex> binding()
[x: 1]
iex> x = 2
iex> binding()
[x: 2]

iex> binding(:foo)
[]
iex> var!(x, :foo) = 1
1
iex> binding(:foo)
[x: 1]

dbg(code \\ quote do binding() end, options \\ [])

(since 1.14.0) (macro)

Debugs the given code.

dbg/2 can be used to debug the given code through a configurable debug function. It returns the result of the given code.

Examples

Let's take this call to dbg/2:

dbg(Atom.to_string(:debugging))
#=> "debugging"

It returns the string "debugging", which is the result of the Atom.to_string/1 call. Additionally, the call above prints:

[my_file.ex:10: MyMod.my_fun/0]
Atom.to_string(:debugging) #=> "debugging"

The default debugging function prints additional debugging info when dealing with pipelines. It prints the values at every "step" of the pipeline.

"Elixir is cool!"
|> String.trim_trailing("!")
|> String.split()
|> List.first()
|> dbg()
#=> "Elixir"

The code above prints:

[my_file.ex:10: MyMod.my_fun/0]
"Elixir is cool!" #=> "Elixir is cool!"
|> String.trim_trailing("!") #=> "Elixir is cool"
|> String.split() #=> ["Elixir", "is", "cool"]
|> List.first() #=> "Elixir"

With no arguments, dbg() debugs information about the current binding. See binding/1.

dbg inside IEx

You can enable IEx to replace dbg with its IEx.pry/0 backend by calling:

$ iex --dbg pry

In such cases, dbg will start a pry session where you can interact with the imports, aliases, and variables of the current environment at the location of the dbg call.

If you call dbg at the end of a pipeline (using |>) within IEx, you are able to go through each step of the pipeline one by one by entering "next" (or "n").

Note dbg only supports stepping for pipelines (in other words, it can only step through the code it sees). For general stepping, you can set breakpoints using IEx.break!/4.

For more information, see IEx documentation.

Configuring the debug function

One of the benefits of dbg/2 is that its debugging logic is configurable, allowing tools to extend dbg with enhanced behaviour. This is done, for example, by IEx which extends dbg with an interactive shell where you can directly inspect and access values.

The debug function can be configured at compile time through the :dbg_callback key of the :elixir application. The debug function must be a {module, function, args} tuple. The function function in module will be invoked with three arguments prepended to args:

The AST of code
The AST of options
The Macro.Env environment of where dbg/2 is invoked

The debug function is invoked at compile time and it must also return an AST. The AST is expected to ultimately return the result of evaluating the debugged expression.

Here's a simple example:

defmodule MyMod do
  def debug_fun(code, options, caller, device) do
    quote do
      result = unquote(code)
      IO.inspect(unquote(device), result, label: unquote(Macro.to_string(code)))
    end
  end
end

To configure the debug function:

# In config/config.exs
config :elixir, :dbg_callback, {MyMod, :debug_fun, [:stdio]}

Default debug function

By default, the debug function we use is Macro.dbg/3. It just prints information about the code to standard output and returns the value returned by evaluating code. options are used to control how terms are inspected. They are the same options accepted by inspect/2.

def(call, expr \\ nil)

(macro)

Defines a public function with the given name and body.

Examples

defmodule Foo do
  def bar, do: :baz
end

Foo.bar()
#=> :baz

A function that expects arguments can be defined as follows:

defmodule Foo do
  def sum(a, b) do
    a + b
  end
end

In the example above, a sum/2 function is defined; this function receives two arguments and returns their sum.

Default arguments

\\ is used to specify a default value for a parameter of a function. For example:

defmodule MyMath do
  def multiply_by(number, factor \\ 2) do
    number * factor
  end
end

MyMath.multiply_by(4, 3)
#=> 12

MyMath.multiply_by(4)
#=> 8

The compiler translates this into multiple functions with different arities, here MyMath.multiply_by/1 and MyMath.multiply_by/2, that represent cases when arguments for parameters with default values are passed or not passed.

When defining a function with default arguments as well as multiple explicitly declared clauses, you must write a function head that declares the defaults. For example:

defmodule MyString do
  def join(string1, string2 \\ nil, separator \\ " ")

  def join(string1, nil, _separator) do
    string1
  end

  def join(string1, string2, separator) do
    string1 <> separator <> string2
  end
end

Note that \\ can't be used with anonymous functions because they can only have a sole arity.

Keyword lists with default arguments

Functions containing many arguments can benefit from using Keyword lists to group and pass attributes as a single value.

defmodule MyConfiguration do
  @default_opts [storage: "local"]

  def configure(resource, opts \\ []) do
    opts = Keyword.merge(@default_opts, opts)
    storage = opts[:storage]
    # ...
  end
end

The difference between using Map and Keyword to store many arguments is Keyword's keys:

must be atoms
can be given more than once
ordered, as specified by the developer

Function names

Function and variable names in Elixir must start with an underscore or a Unicode letter that is not in uppercase or titlecase. They may continue using a sequence of Unicode letters, numbers, and underscores. They may end in ? or !. Elixir's Naming Conventions suggest for function and variable names to be written in the snake_case format.

rescue/catch/after/else

Function bodies support rescue, catch, after, and else as try/1 does (known as "implicit try"). For example, the following two functions are equivalent:

def convert(number) do
  try do
    String.to_integer(number)
  rescue
    e in ArgumentError -> {:error, e.message}
  end
end

def convert(number) do
  String.to_integer(number)
rescue
  e in ArgumentError -> {:error, e.message}
end

defdelegate(funs, opts)

(macro)

Defines a function that delegates to another module.

Functions defined with defdelegate/2 are public and can be invoked from outside the module they're defined in, as if they were defined using def/2. Therefore, defdelegate/2 is about extending the current module's public API. If what you want is to invoke a function defined in another module without using its full module name, then use alias/2 to shorten the module name or use import/2 to be able to invoke the function without the module name altogether.

Delegation only works with functions; delegating macros is not supported.

Check def/2 for rules on naming and default arguments.

Options

:to - the module to dispatch to.

:as - the function to call on the target given in :to. This parameter is optional and defaults to the name being delegated (funs).

Examples

defmodule MyList do
  defdelegate reverse(list), to: Enum
  defdelegate other_reverse(list), to: Enum, as: :reverse
end

MyList.reverse([1, 2, 3])
#=> [3, 2, 1]

MyList.other_reverse([1, 2, 3])
#=> [3, 2, 1]

defexception(fields)

(macro)

Defines an exception.

Exceptions are structs backed by a module that implements the Exception behaviour. The Exception behaviour requires two functions to be implemented:

exception/1 - receives the arguments given to raise/2 and returns the exception struct. The default implementation accepts either a set of keyword arguments that is merged into the struct or a string to be used as the exception's message.

message/1 - receives the exception struct and must return its message. Most commonly exceptions have a message field which by default is accessed by this function. However, if an exception does not have a message field, this function must be explicitly implemented.

Since exceptions are structs, the API supported by defstruct/1 is also available in defexception/1.

Raising exceptions

The most common way to raise an exception is via raise/2:

defmodule MyAppError do
  defexception [:message]
end

value = [:hello]

raise MyAppError,
  message: "did not get what was expected, got: #{inspect(value)}"

In many cases it is more convenient to pass the expected value to raise/2 and generate the message in the Exception.exception/1 callback:

defmodule MyAppError do
  defexception [:message]

  @impl true
  def exception(value) do
    msg = "did not get what was expected, got: #{inspect(value)}"
    %MyAppError{message: msg}
  end
end

raise MyAppError, value

The example above shows the preferred strategy for customizing exception messages.

defguard(guard)

(since 1.6.0) (macro)

@spec defguard(Macro.t()) :: Macro.t()

Defines a macro suitable for use in guard expressions.

It raises at compile time if the guard uses expressions that aren't allowed in guard clauses, and otherwise creates a macro that can be used both inside or outside guards.

When defining your own guards, consider the naming conventions around boolean-returning guards.

Example

defmodule Integer.Guards do
  defguard is_even(value) when is_integer(value) and rem(value, 2) == 0
end

defmodule Collatz do
  @moduledoc "Tools for working with the Collatz sequence."
  import Integer.Guards

  @doc "Determines the number of steps `n` takes to reach `1`."
  # If this function never converges, please let me know what `n` you used.
  def converge(n) when n > 0, do: step(n, 0)

  defp step(1, step_count) do
    step_count
  end

  defp step(n, step_count) when is_even(n) do
    step(div(n, 2), step_count + 1)
  end

  defp step(n, step_count) do
    step(3 * n + 1, step_count + 1)
  end
end

defguardp(guard)

(since 1.6.0) (macro)

@spec defguardp(Macro.t()) :: Macro.t()

Defines a private macro suitable for use in guard expressions.

It raises at compile time if the guard uses expressions that aren't allowed in guard clauses, and otherwise creates a private macro that can be used both inside or outside guards in the current module.

When defining your own guards, consider the naming conventions around boolean-returning guards.

Similar to defmacrop/2, defguardp/1 must be defined before its use in the current module.

defimpl(name, opts, do_block \\ [])

(macro)

Defines an implementation for the given protocol.

See the Protocol module for more information.

defmacro(call, expr \\ nil)

(macro)

Defines a public macro with the given name and body.

Macros must be defined before its usage.

Check def/2 for rules on naming and default arguments.

Examples

defmodule MyLogic do
  defmacro unless(expr, opts) do
    quote do
      if !unquote(expr), unquote(opts)
    end
  end
end

require MyLogic

MyLogic.unless false do
  IO.puts("It works")
end

defmacrop(call, expr \\ nil)

(macro)

Defines a private macro with the given name and body.

Private macros are only accessible from the same module in which they are defined.

Private macros must be defined before its usage.

Check defmacro/2 for more information, and check def/2 for rules on naming and default arguments.

defmodule(alias, do_block)

(macro)

Defines a module given by name with the given contents.

This macro defines a module with the given alias as its name and with the given contents. It returns a tuple with four elements:

:module
the module name
the binary contents of the module
the result of evaluating the contents block

Examples

defmodule Number do
  def one, do: 1
  def two, do: 2
end
#=> {:module, Number, <<70, 79, 82, ...>>, {:two, 0}}

Number.one()
#=> 1

Number.two()
#=> 2

Module names and aliases

Module names (and aliases) must start with an ASCII uppercase character which may be followed by any ASCII letter, number, or underscore. Elixir's Naming Conventions suggest for module names and aliases to be written in the CamelCase format.

You can also use atoms as the module name, although they must only contain ASCII characters.

Nesting

Nesting a module inside another module affects the name of the nested module:

defmodule Foo do
  defmodule Bar do
  end
end

In the example above, two modules - Foo and Foo.Bar - are created. When nesting, Elixir automatically creates an alias to the inner module, allowing the second module Foo.Bar to be accessed as Bar in the same lexical scope where it's defined (the Foo module). This only happens if the nested module is defined via an alias.

If the Foo.Bar module is moved somewhere else, the references to Bar in the Foo module need to be updated to the fully-qualified name (Foo.Bar) or an alias has to be explicitly set in the Foo module with the help of alias/2.

defmodule Foo.Bar do
  # code
end

defmodule Foo do
  alias Foo.Bar
  # code here can refer to "Foo.Bar" as just "Bar"
end

Dynamic names

Elixir module names can be dynamically generated. This is very useful when working with macros. For instance, one could write:

defmodule Module.concat(["Foo", "Bar"]) do
  # contents ...
end

Elixir will accept any module name as long as the expression passed as the first argument to defmodule/2 evaluates to an atom. Note that, when a dynamic name is used, Elixir won't nest the name under the current module nor automatically set up an alias.

Reserved module names

If you attempt to define a module that already exists, you will get a warning saying that a module has been redefined.

There are some modules that Elixir does not currently implement but it may be implement in the future. Those modules are reserved and defining them will result in a compilation error:

defmodule Any do
  # code
end
** (CompileError) iex:1: module Any is reserved and cannot be defined

Elixir reserves the following module names: Elixir, Any, BitString, PID, and Reference.

defoverridable(keywords_or_behaviour)

(macro)

Makes the given definitions in the current module overridable.

If the user defines a new function or macro with the same name and arity, then the overridable ones are discarded. Otherwise, the original definitions are used.

It is possible for the overridden definition to have a different visibility than the original: a public function can be overridden by a private function and vice-versa.

Macros cannot be overridden as functions and vice-versa.

Example

defmodule DefaultMod do
  defmacro __using__(_opts) do
    quote do
      def test(x, y) do
        x + y
      end

      defoverridable test: 2
    end
  end
end

defmodule ChildMod do
  use DefaultMod

  def test(x, y) do
    x * y + super(x, y)
  end
end

As seen as in the example above, super can be used to call the default implementation.

Disclaimer

Use defoverridable with care. If you need to define multiple modules with the same behaviour, it may be best to move the default implementation to the caller, and check if a callback exists via Code.ensure_loaded?/1 and function_exported?/3.

For example, in the example above, imagine there is a module that calls the test/2 function. This module could be defined as such:

defmodule CallsTest do
  def receives_module_and_calls_test(module, x, y) do
    if Code.ensure_loaded?(module) and function_exported?(module, :test, 2) do
      module.test(x, y)
    else
      x + y
    end
  end
end

Example with behaviour

You can also pass a behaviour to defoverridable and it will mark all of the callbacks in the behaviour as overridable:

defmodule Behaviour do
  @callback test(number(), number()) :: number()
end

defmodule DefaultMod do
  defmacro __using__(_opts) do
    quote do
      @behaviour Behaviour

      def test(x, y) do
        x + y
      end

      defoverridable Behaviour
    end
  end
end

defmodule ChildMod do
  use DefaultMod

  def test(x, y) do
    x * y + super(x, y)
  end
end

defp(call, expr \\ nil)

(macro)

Defines a private function with the given name and body.

Private functions are only accessible from within the module in which they are defined. Trying to access a private function from outside the module it's defined in results in an UndefinedFunctionError exception.

Check def/2 for more information.

Examples

defmodule Foo do
  def bar do
    sum(1, 2)
  end

  defp sum(a, b), do: a + b
end

Foo.bar()
#=> 3

Foo.sum(1, 2)
** (UndefinedFunctionError) undefined function Foo.sum/2

defprotocol(name, do_block)

(macro)

Defines a protocol.

See the Protocol module for more information.

defstruct(fields)

(macro)

Defines a struct.

A struct is a tagged map that allows developers to provide default values for keys, tags to be used in polymorphic dispatches and compile time assertions.

It is only possible to define a struct per module, as the struct is tied to the module itself.

Examples

defmodule User do
  defstruct name: nil, age: nil
end

Struct fields are evaluated at compile-time, which allows them to be dynamic. In the example below, 10 + 11 is evaluated at compile-time and the age field is stored with value 21:

defmodule User do
  defstruct name: nil, age: 10 + 11
end

The fields argument is usually a keyword list with field names as atom keys and default values as corresponding values. defstruct/1 also supports a list of atoms as its argument: in that case, the atoms in the list will be used as the struct's field names and they will all default to nil.

defmodule Post do
  defstruct [:title, :content, :author]
end

Add documentation to a struct with the @doc attribute, like a function.

defmodule Post do
  @doc "A post. The content should be valid Markdown."
  defstruct [:title, :content, :author]
end

Once a struct is defined, it is possible to create them as follows:

%Post{title: "Hello world!"}

For more information on creating, updating, and pattern matching on structs, please check %/2.

Deriving

Although structs are maps, by default structs do not implement any of the protocols implemented for maps. For example, attempting to use a protocol with the User struct leads to an error:

john = %User{name: "John"}
MyProtocol.call(john)
** (Protocol.UndefinedError) protocol MyProtocol not implemented for %User{...}

defstruct/1, however, allows protocol implementations to be derived. This can be done by defining a @derive attribute as a list before invoking defstruct/1:

defmodule User do
  @derive MyProtocol
  defstruct name: nil, age: nil
end

MyProtocol.call(john) # it works!

A common example is to @derive the Inspect protocol to hide certain fields when the struct is printed:

defmodule User do
  @derive {Inspect, only: :name}
  defstruct name: nil, age: nil
end

For each protocol in @derive, Elixir will verify if the protocol has implemented the Protocol.__deriving__/2 callback. If so, the callback will be invoked and it should define the implementation module. Otherwise an implementation that simply points to the Any implementation is automatically derived. For more information, see Protocol.derive/3.

Enforcing keys

When building a struct, Elixir will automatically guarantee all keys belong to the struct:

%User{name: "john", unknown: :key}
** (KeyError) key :unknown not found in: %User{age: 21, name: nil}

Elixir also allows developers to enforce that certain keys must always be given when building the struct:

defmodule User do
  @enforce_keys [:name]
  defstruct name: nil, age: 10 + 11
end

Now trying to build a struct without the name key will fail:

%User{age: 21}
** (ArgumentError) the following keys must also be given when building struct User: [:name]

Keep in mind @enforce_keys is a simple compile-time guarantee to aid developers when building structs. It is not enforced on updates and it does not provide any sort of value-validation.

Types

It is recommended to define types for structs. By convention, such a type is called t. To define a struct inside a type, the struct literal syntax is used:

defmodule User do
  defstruct name: "John", age: 25
  @type t :: %__MODULE__{name: String.t(), age: non_neg_integer}
end

It is recommended to only use the struct syntax when defining the struct's type. When referring to another struct, it's better to use User.t() instead of %User{}.

The types of the struct fields that are not included in %User{} default to term() (see term/0).

Structs whose internal structure is private to the local module (pattern matching them or directly accessing their fields should not be allowed) should use the @opaque attribute. Structs whose internal structure is public should use @type.

destructure(left, right)

(macro)

Destructures two lists, assigning each term in the right one to the matching term in the left one.

Unlike pattern matching via =, if the sizes of the left and right lists don't match, destructuring simply stops instead of raising an error.

Examples

iex> destructure([x, y, z], [1, 2, 3, 4, 5])
iex> {x, y, z}
{1, 2, 3}

In the example above, even though the right list has more entries than the left one, destructuring works fine. If the right list is smaller, the remaining elements are simply set to nil:

iex> destructure([x, y, z], [1])
iex> {x, y, z}
{1, nil, nil}

The left-hand side supports any expression you would use on the left-hand side of a match:

x = 1
destructure([^x, y, z], [1, 2, 3])

The example above will only work if x matches the first value in the right list. Otherwise, it will raise a MatchError (like the = operator would do).

exit(reason)

@spec exit(term()) :: no_return()

Stops the execution of the calling process with the given reason.

Since evaluating this function causes the process to terminate, it has no return value.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

When a process reaches its end, by default it exits with reason :normal. You can also call exit/1 explicitly if you want to terminate a process but not signal any failure:

exit(:normal)

In case something goes wrong, you can also use exit/1 with a different reason:

exit(:seems_bad)

If the exit reason is not :normal, all the processes linked to the process that exited will crash (unless they are trapping exits).

OTP exits

Exits are used by the OTP to determine if a process exited abnormally or not. The following exits are considered "normal":

exit(:normal)
exit(:shutdown)
exit({:shutdown, term})

Exiting with any other reason is considered abnormal and treated as a crash. This means the default supervisor behavior kicks in, error reports are emitted, and so forth.

This behavior is relied on in many different places. For example, ExUnit uses exit(:shutdown) when exiting the test process to signal linked processes, supervision trees and so on to politely shut down too.

CLI exits

Building on top of the exit signals mentioned above, if the process started by the command line exits with any of the three reasons above, its exit is considered normal and the Operating System process will exit with status 0.

It is, however, possible to customize the operating system exit signal by invoking:

exit({:shutdown, integer})

This will cause the operating system process to exit with the status given by integer while signaling all linked Erlang processes to politely shut down.

Any other exit reason will cause the operating system process to exit with status 1 and linked Erlang processes to crash.

function_exported?(module, function, arity)

@spec function_exported?(module(), atom(), arity()) :: boolean()

Returns true if module is loaded and contains a public function with the given arity, otherwise false.

Note that this function does not load the module in case it is not loaded. Check Code.ensure_loaded/1 for more information.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> function_exported?(Enum, :map, 2)
true

iex> function_exported?(Enum, :map, 10)
false

iex> function_exported?(List, :to_string, 1)
true

get_and_update_in(path, fun)

(macro)

Gets a value and updates a nested data structure via the given path.

This is similar to get_and_update_in/3, except the path is extracted via a macro rather than passing a list. For example:

get_and_update_in(opts[:foo][:bar], &{&1, &1 + 1})

Is equivalent to:

get_and_update_in(opts, [:foo, :bar], &{&1, &1 + 1})

This also works with nested structs and the struct.path.to.value way to specify paths:

get_and_update_in(struct.foo.bar, &{&1, &1 + 1})

Note that in order for this macro to work, the complete path must always be visible by this macro. See the "Paths" section below.

Examples

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> get_and_update_in(users["john"].age, &{&1, &1 + 1})
{27, %{"john" => %{age: 28}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}}

Paths

A path may start with a variable, local or remote call, and must be followed by one or more:

foo[bar] - accesses the key bar in foo; in case foo is nil, nil is returned

foo.bar - accesses a map/struct field; in case the field is not present, an error is raised

Here are some valid paths:

users["john"][:age]
users["john"].age
User.all()["john"].age
all_users()["john"].age

Here are some invalid ones:

# Does a remote call after the initial value
users["john"].do_something(arg1, arg2)

# Does not access any key or field
users

get_and_update_in(data, keys, fun)

@spec get_and_update_in(
  structure,
  keys,
  (term() | nil -> {current_value, new_value} | :pop)
) :: {current_value, new_structure :: structure}
when structure: Access.t(),
     keys: [term(), ...],
     current_value: Access.value(),
     new_value: Access.value()

Gets a value and updates a nested structure.

data is a nested structure (that is, a map, keyword list, or struct that implements the Access behaviour).

The fun argument receives the value of key (or nil if key is not present) and must return one of the following values:

a two-element tuple {current_value, new_value}. In this case, current_value is the retrieved value which can possibly be operated on before being returned. new_value is the new value to be stored under key.

:pop, which implies that the current value under key should be removed from the structure and returned.

This function uses the Access module to traverse the structures according to the given keys, unless the key is a function, which is detailed in a later section.

Examples

This function is useful when there is a need to retrieve the current value (or something calculated in function of the current value) and update it at the same time. For example, it could be used to read the current age of a user while increasing it by one in one pass:

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> get_and_update_in(users, ["john", :age], &{&1, &1 + 1})
{27, %{"john" => %{age: 28}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}}

Note the current value given to the anonymous function may be nil. If any of the intermediate values are nil, it will raise:

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> get_and_update_in(users, ["jane", :age], &{&1, &1 + 1})
** (ArgumentError) could not put/update key :age on a nil value

Functions as keys

If a key is a function, the function will be invoked passing three arguments:

the operation (:get_and_update)
the data to be accessed
a function to be invoked next

This means get_and_update_in/3 can be extended to provide custom lookups. The downside is that functions cannot be stored as keys in the accessed data structures.

When one of the keys is a function, the function is invoked. In the example below, we use a function to get and increment all ages inside a list:

iex> users = [%{name: "john", age: 27}, %{name: "meg", age: 23}]
iex> all = fn :get_and_update, data, next ->
...>   data |> Enum.map(next) |> Enum.unzip()
...> end
iex> get_and_update_in(users, [all, :age], &{&1, &1 + 1})
{[27, 23], [%{name: "john", age: 28}, %{name: "meg", age: 24}]}

If the previous value before invoking the function is nil, the function will receive nil as a value and must handle it accordingly (be it by failing or providing a sane default).

The Access module ships with many convenience accessor functions, like the all anonymous function defined above. See Access.all/0, Access.key/2, and others as examples.

get_in(path)

(macro)

Gets a key from the nested structure via the given path, with nil-safe handling.

This is similar to get_in/2, except the path is extracted via a macro rather than passing a list. For example:

get_in(opts[:foo][:bar])

Is equivalent to:

get_in(opts, [:foo, :bar])

Additionally, this macro can traverse structs:

get_in(struct.foo.bar)

In case any of the keys returns nil, then nil will be returned and get_in/1 won't traverse any further.

Note that in order for this macro to work, the complete path must always be visible by this macro. For more information about the supported path expressions, please check get_and_update_in/2 docs.

Examples

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> get_in(users["john"].age)
27
iex> get_in(users["unknown"].age)
nil

get_in(data, keys)

@spec get_in(Access.t(), [term(), ...]) :: term()

Gets a value from a nested structure with nil-safe handling.

Uses the Access module to traverse the structures according to the given keys, unless the key is a function, which is detailed in a later section.

Examples

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> get_in(users, ["john", :age])
27
iex> # Equivalent to:
iex> users["john"][:age]
27

get_in/2 can also use the accessors in the Access module to traverse more complex data structures. For example, here we use Access.all/0 to traverse a list:

iex> users = [%{name: "john", age: 27}, %{name: "meg", age: 23}]
iex> get_in(users, [Access.all(), :age])
[27, 23]

In case any of the components returns nil, nil will be returned and get_in/2 won't traverse any further:

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> get_in(users, ["unknown", :age])
nil
iex> # Equivalent to:
iex> users["unknown"][:age]
nil

Functions as keys

If a key given to get_in/2 is a function, the function will be invoked passing three arguments:

the operation (:get)
the data to be accessed
a function to be invoked next

This means get_in/2 can be extended to provide custom lookups. That's precisely how the Access.all/0 key in the previous section behaves. For example, we can manually implement such traversal as follows:

iex> users = [%{name: "john", age: 27}, %{name: "meg", age: 23}]
iex> all = fn :get, data, next -> Enum.map(data, next) end
iex> get_in(users, [all, :age])
[27, 23]

The Access module ships with many convenience accessor functions. See Access.all/0, Access.key/2, and others as examples.

Working with structs

By default, structs do not implement the Access behaviour required by this function. Therefore, you can't do this:

get_in(some_struct, [:some_key, :nested_key])

There are two alternatives. Given structs have predefined keys, we can use the struct.field notation:

some_struct.some_key.nested_key

However, the code above will fail if any of the values return nil. If you also want to handle nil values, you can use get_in/1:

get_in(some_struct.some_key.nested_key)

Pattern-matching is another option for handling such cases, which can be especially useful if you want to match on several fields at once or provide custom return values:

case some_struct do
  %{some_key: %{nested_key: value}} -> value
  %{} -> nil
end

if(condition, clauses)

(macro)

Provides an if/2 macro.

This macro expects the first argument to be a condition and the second argument to be a keyword list. Generally speaking, Elixir developers prefer to use pattern matching and guards in function definitions and case/2, as they are succinct and precise. However, not all conditions can be expressed through patterns and guards, which makes if/2 a viable alternative.

Similar to case/2, any assignment in the condition will be available on both clauses, as well as after the if expression.

One-liner examples

if(foo, do: bar)

In the example above, bar will be returned if foo evaluates to a truthy value (neither false nor nil). Otherwise, nil will be returned.

An else option can be given to specify the opposite:

if(foo, do: bar, else: baz)

Blocks examples

It's also possible to pass a block to the if/2 macro. The first example above would be translated to:

if foo do
  bar
end

Note that do-end become delimiters. The second example would translate to:

if foo do
  bar
else
  baz
end

If you find yourself nesting conditionals inside conditionals, consider using cond/1.

inspect(term, opts \\ [])

@spec inspect(
  Inspect.t(),
  keyword()
) :: String.t()

Inspects the given argument according to the Inspect protocol. The second argument is a keyword list with options to control inspection.

Options

inspect/2 accepts a list of options that are internally translated to an Inspect.Opts struct. Check the docs for Inspect.Opts to see the supported options.

Examples

iex> inspect(:foo)
":foo"

iex> inspect([1, 2, 3, 4, 5], limit: 3)
"[1, 2, 3, ...]"

iex> inspect([1, 2, 3], pretty: true, width: 0)
"[1,\n 2,\n 3]"

iex> inspect("olá" <> <<0>>)
"<<111, 108, 195, 161, 0>>"

iex> inspect("olá" <> <<0>>, binaries: :as_strings)
"\"olá\\0\""

iex> inspect("olá", binaries: :as_binaries)
"<<111, 108, 195, 161>>"

iex> inspect(~c"bar")
"~c\"bar\""

iex> inspect([0 | ~c"bar"])
"[0, 98, 97, 114]"

iex> inspect(100, base: :octal)
"0o144"

iex> inspect(100, base: :hex)
"0x64"

Note that the Inspect protocol does not necessarily return a valid representation of an Elixir term. In such cases, the inspected result must start with #. For example, inspecting a function will return:

inspect(fn a, b -> a + b end)
#=> #Function<...>

The Inspect protocol can be derived to hide certain fields from structs, so they don't show up in logs, inspects and similar. See the "Deriving" section of the documentation of the Inspect protocol for more information.

macro_exported?(module, macro, arity)

@spec macro_exported?(module(), atom(), arity()) :: boolean()

Returns true if module is loaded and contains a public macro with the given arity, otherwise false.

Note that this function does not load the module in case it is not loaded. Check Code.ensure_loaded/1 for more information.

If module is an Erlang module (as opposed to an Elixir module), this function always returns false.

Examples

iex> macro_exported?(Kernel, :use, 2)
true

iex> macro_exported?(:erlang, :abs, 1)
false

make_ref()

@spec make_ref() :: reference()

Returns an almost unique reference.

The returned reference will re-occur after approximately 2^82 calls; therefore it is unique enough for practical purposes.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

make_ref()
#=> #Reference<0.0.0.135>

match?(pattern, expr)

(macro)

A convenience macro that checks if the right side (an expression) matches the left side (a pattern).

Examples

iex> match?(1, 1)
true

iex> match?({1, _}, {1, 2})
true

iex> map = %{a: 1, b: 2}
iex> match?(%{a: _}, map)
true

iex> a = 1
iex> match?(^a, 1)
true

match?/2 is very useful when filtering or finding a value in an enumerable:

iex> list = [a: 1, b: 2, a: 3]
iex> Enum.filter(list, &match?({:a, _}, &1))
[a: 1, a: 3]

Guard clauses can also be given to the match:

iex> list = [a: 1, b: 2, a: 3]
iex> Enum.filter(list, &match?({:a, x} when x < 2, &1))
[a: 1]

Variables assigned in the match will not be available outside of the function call (unlike regular pattern matching with the = operator):

iex> match?(_x, 1)
true
iex> binding()
[]

Values vs patterns

Remember the pin operator matches values, not patterns. Passing a variable as the pattern will always return true and will result in a warning that the variable is unused:

# don't do this
pattern = %{a: :a}
match?(pattern, %{b: :b})

Similarly, moving an expression out the pattern may no longer preserve its semantics. For example:

match?([_ | _], [1, 2, 3])
#=> true

pattern = [_ | _]
match?(pattern, [1, 2, 3])
** (CompileError) invalid use of _. _ can only be used inside patterns to ignore values and cannot be used in expressions. Make sure you are inside a pattern or change it accordingly

Another example is that a map as a pattern performs a subset match, but not once assigned to a variable:

match?(%{x: 1}, %{x: 1, y: 2})
#=> true

attrs = %{x: 1}
match?(^attrs, %{x: 1, y: 2})
#=> false

The pin operator will check if the values are equal, using ===/2, while patterns have their own rules when matching maps, lists, and so forth. Such behavior is not specific to match?/2. The following code also throws an exception:

attrs = %{x: 1}
^attrs = %{x: 1, y: 2}
#=> (MatchError) no match of right hand side value: %{x: 1, y: 2}

max(first, second)

@spec max(first, second) :: first | second when first: term(), second: term()

Returns the biggest of the two given terms according to their structural comparison.

If the terms compare equal, the first one is returned.

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> max(1, 2)
2
iex> max("a", "b")
"b"

min(first, second)

@spec min(first, second) :: first | second when first: term(), second: term()

Returns the smallest of the two given terms according to their structural comparison.

If the terms compare equal, the first one is returned.

This performs a structural comparison where all Elixir terms can be compared with each other. See the "Structural comparison" section for more information.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> min(1, 2)
1
iex> min("foo", "bar")
"bar"

pop_in(path)

(macro)

Pops a key from the nested structure via the given path.

This is similar to pop_in/2, except the path is extracted via a macro rather than passing a list. For example:

pop_in(opts[:foo][:bar])

Is equivalent to:

pop_in(opts, [:foo, :bar])

Note that in order for this macro to work, the complete path must always be visible by this macro. For more information about the supported path expressions, please check get_and_update_in/2 docs.

Examples

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> pop_in(users["john"][:age])
{27, %{"john" => %{}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}}

iex> users = %{john: %{age: 27}, meg: %{age: 23}}
iex> pop_in(users.john[:age])
{27, %{john: %{}, meg: %{age: 23}}}

In case any entry returns nil, its key will be removed and the deletion will be considered a success.

pop_in(data, keys)

@spec pop_in(data, [Access.get_and_update_fun(term(), data) | term(), ...]) ::
  {term(), data}
when data: Access.container()

Pops a key from the given nested structure.

Uses the Access protocol to traverse the structures according to the given keys, unless the key is a function. If the key is a function, it will be invoked as specified in get_and_update_in/3.

Examples

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> pop_in(users, ["john", :age])
{27, %{"john" => %{}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}}

In case any entry returns nil, its key will be removed and the deletion will be considered a success.

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> pop_in(users, ["jane", :age])
{nil, %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}}

put_elem(tuple, index, value)

@spec put_elem(tuple(), non_neg_integer(), term()) :: tuple()

Puts value at the given zero-based index in tuple.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> tuple = {:foo, :bar, 3}
iex> put_elem(tuple, 0, :baz)
{:baz, :bar, 3}

put_in(path, value)

(macro)

Puts a value in a nested structure via the given path.

This is similar to put_in/3, except the path is extracted via a macro rather than passing a list. For example:

put_in(opts[:foo][:bar], :baz)

Is equivalent to:

put_in(opts, [:foo, :bar], :baz)

This also works with nested structs and the struct.path.to.value way to specify paths:

put_in(struct.foo.bar, :baz)

Note that in order for this macro to work, the complete path must always be visible by this macro. For more information about the supported path expressions, please check get_and_update_in/2 docs.

Examples

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> put_in(users["john"][:age], 28)
%{"john" => %{age: 28}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> put_in(users["john"].age, 28)
%{"john" => %{age: 28}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}

put_in(data, keys, value)

@spec put_in(Access.t(), [term(), ...], term()) :: Access.t()

Puts a value in a nested structure.

Uses the Access module to traverse the structures according to the given keys, unless the key is a function. If the key is a function, it will be invoked as specified in get_and_update_in/3.

Examples

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> put_in(users, ["john", :age], 28)
%{"john" => %{age: 28}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}

If any of the intermediate values are nil, it will raise:

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> put_in(users, ["jane", :age], "oops")
** (ArgumentError) could not put/update key :age on a nil value

raise(message)

(macro)

Raises an exception.

If message is a string, it raises a RuntimeError exception with it.

If message is an atom, it just calls raise/2 with the atom as the first argument and [] as the second one.

If message is an exception struct, it is raised as is.

If message is anything else, raise will fail with an ArgumentError exception.

Examples

iex> raise "oops"
** (RuntimeError) oops

try do
  1 + :foo
rescue
  x in [ArithmeticError] ->
    IO.puts("that was expected")
    raise x
end

raise(exception, attributes)

(macro)

Raises an exception.

Calls the exception/1 function on the given argument (which has to be a module name like ArgumentError or RuntimeError) passing attributes in order to retrieve the exception struct.

Any module that contains a call to the defexception/1 macro automatically implements the Exception.exception/1 callback expected by raise/2. For more information, see defexception/1.

Examples

iex> raise(ArgumentError, "Sample")
** (ArgumentError) Sample

reraise(message, stacktrace)

(macro)

Raises an exception preserving a previous stacktrace.

Works like raise/1 but does not generate a new stacktrace.

Note that __STACKTRACE__ can be used inside catch/rescue to retrieve the current stacktrace.

Examples

try do
  raise "oops"
rescue
  exception ->
    reraise exception, __STACKTRACE__
end

reraise(exception, attributes, stacktrace)

(macro)

Raises an exception preserving a previous stacktrace.

reraise/3 works like reraise/2, except it passes arguments to the exception/1 function as explained in raise/2.

Examples

try do
  raise "oops"
rescue
  exception ->
    reraise WrapperError, [exception: exception], __STACKTRACE__
end

send(dest, message)

@spec send(dest :: Process.dest(), message) :: message when message: any()

Sends a message to the given dest and returns the message.

dest may be a remote or local PID, a local port, a locally registered name, or a tuple in the form of {registered_name, node} for a registered name at another node.

For additional documentation, see the ! operator Erlang documentation.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

iex> send(self(), :hello)
:hello

sigil_C(term, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~C for charlists.

It returns a charlist without interpolations and without escape characters.

A charlist is a list of integers where all the integers are valid code points. The three expressions below are equivalent:

~C"foo\n"
[?f, ?o, ?o, ?\\, ?n]
[102, 111, 111, 92, 110]

In practice, charlists are mostly used in specific scenarios such as interfacing with older Erlang libraries that do not accept binaries as arguments.

Examples

iex> ~C(foo)
~c"foo"

iex> ~C(f#{o}o)
~c"f\#{o}o"

iex> ~C(foo\n)
~c"foo\\n"

sigil_c(term, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~c for charlists.

It returns a charlist, unescaping characters and replacing interpolations.

A charlist is a list of integers where all the integers are valid code points. The three expressions below are equivalent:

~c"foo"
[?f, ?o, ?o]
[102, 111, 111]

In practice, charlists are mostly used in specific scenarios such as interfacing with older Erlang libraries that do not accept binaries as arguments.

Examples

iex> ~c(foo)
~c"foo"

iex> ~c(f#{:o}o)
~c"foo"

iex> ~c(f\#{:o}o)
~c"f\#{:o}o"

The list is only printed as a ~c sigil if all code points are within the ASCII range:

iex> ~c"hełło"
[104, 101, 322, 322, 111]

iex> [104, 101, 108, 108, 111]
~c"hello"

See Inspect.Opts for more information.

sigil_D(date_string, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~D for dates.

By default, this sigil uses the built-in Calendar.ISO, which requires dates to be written in the ISO8601 format:

~D[yyyy-mm-dd]

such as:

~D[2015-01-13]

If you are using alternative calendars, any representation can be used as long as you follow the representation by a single space and the calendar name:

~D[SOME-REPRESENTATION My.Alternative.Calendar]

The lower case ~d variant does not exist as interpolation and escape characters are not useful for date sigils.

More information on dates can be found in the Date module.

Examples

iex> ~D[2015-01-13]
~D[2015-01-13]

sigil_N(naive_datetime_string, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~N for naive date times.

By default, this sigil uses the built-in Calendar.ISO, which requires naive date times to be written in the ISO8601 format:

~N[yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ss]
~N[yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ss.ssssss]
~N[yyyy-mm-ddThh:mm:ss.ssssss]

such as:

~N[2015-01-13 13:00:07]
~N[2015-01-13T13:00:07.123]

If you are using alternative calendars, any representation can be used as long as you follow the representation by a single space and the calendar name:

~N[SOME-REPRESENTATION My.Alternative.Calendar]

The lower case ~n variant does not exist as interpolation and escape characters are not useful for date time sigils.

More information on naive date times can be found in the NaiveDateTime module.

Examples

iex> ~N[2015-01-13 13:00:07]
~N[2015-01-13 13:00:07]
iex> ~N[2015-01-13T13:00:07.001]
~N[2015-01-13 13:00:07.001]

sigil_r(term, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~r for regular expressions.

It returns a regular expression pattern, unescaping characters and replacing interpolations.

More information on regular expressions can be found in the Regex module.

Examples

iex> Regex.match?(~r/foo/, "foo")
true

iex> Regex.match?(~r/a#{:b}c/, "abc")
true

While the ~r sigil allows parens and brackets to be used as delimiters, it is preferred to use " or / to avoid escaping conflicts with reserved regex characters.

sigil_S(term, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~S for strings.

It returns a string without interpolations and without escape characters.

Examples

iex> ~S(foo)
"foo"
iex> ~S(f#{o}o)
"f\#{o}o"
iex> ~S(\o/)
"\\o/"

sigil_s(term, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~s for strings.

It returns a string as if it was a double quoted string, unescaping characters and replacing interpolations.

Examples

iex> ~s(foo)
"foo"

iex> ~s(f#{:o}o)
"foo"

iex> ~s(f\#{:o}o)
"f\#{:o}o"

sigil_T(time_string, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~T for times.

By default, this sigil uses the built-in Calendar.ISO, which requires times to be written in the ISO8601 format:

~T[hh:mm:ss]
~T[hh:mm:ss.ssssss]

such as:

~T[13:00:07]
~T[13:00:07.123]

If you are using alternative calendars, any representation can be used as long as you follow the representation by a single space and the calendar name:

~T[SOME-REPRESENTATION My.Alternative.Calendar]

The lower case ~t variant does not exist as interpolation and escape characters are not useful for time sigils.

More information on times can be found in the Time module.

Examples

iex> ~T[13:00:07]
~T[13:00:07]
iex> ~T[13:00:07.001]
~T[13:00:07.001]

sigil_U(datetime_string, modifiers)

(since 1.9.0) (macro)

Handles the sigil ~U to create a UTC DateTime.

By default, this sigil uses the built-in Calendar.ISO, which requires UTC date times to be written in the ISO8601 format:

~U[yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ssZ]
~U[yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ss.ssssssZ]
~U[yyyy-mm-ddThh:mm:ss.ssssss+00:00]

such as:

~U[2015-01-13 13:00:07Z]
~U[2015-01-13T13:00:07.123+00:00]

If you are using alternative calendars, any representation can be used as long as you follow the representation by a single space and the calendar name:

~U[SOME-REPRESENTATION My.Alternative.Calendar]

The given datetime_string must include "Z" or "00:00" offset which marks it as UTC, otherwise an error is raised.

The lower case ~u variant does not exist as interpolation and escape characters are not useful for date time sigils.

More information on date times can be found in the DateTime module.

Examples

iex> ~U[2015-01-13 13:00:07Z]
~U[2015-01-13 13:00:07Z]
iex> ~U[2015-01-13T13:00:07.001+00:00]
~U[2015-01-13 13:00:07.001Z]

sigil_W(term, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~W for list of words.

It returns a list of "words" split by whitespace without interpolations and without escape characters.

Modifiers

s: words in the list are strings (default)
a: words in the list are atoms
c: words in the list are charlists

Examples

iex> ~W(foo #{bar} baz)
["foo", "\#{bar}", "baz"]

sigil_w(term, modifiers)

(macro)

Handles the sigil ~w for list of words.

It returns a list of "words" split by whitespace. Character unescaping and interpolation happens for each word.

Modifiers

s: words in the list are strings (default)
a: words in the list are atoms
c: words in the list are charlists

Examples

iex> ~w(foo #{:bar} baz)
["foo", "bar", "baz"]

iex> ~w(foo #{" bar baz "})
["foo", "bar", "baz"]

iex> ~w(--source test/enum_test.exs)
["--source", "test/enum_test.exs"]

iex> ~w(foo bar baz)a
[:foo, :bar, :baz]

iex> ~w(foo bar baz)c
[~c"foo", ~c"bar", ~c"baz"]

spawn(fun)

@spec spawn((-> any())) :: pid()

Spawns the given function and returns its PID.

Typically developers do not use the spawn functions, instead they use abstractions such as Task, GenServer and Agent, built on top of spawn, that spawns processes with more conveniences in terms of introspection and debugging.

Check the Process module for more process-related functions.

The anonymous function receives 0 arguments, and may return any value.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

current = self()
child = spawn(fn -> send(current, {self(), 1 + 2}) end)

receive do
  {^child, 3} -> IO.puts("Received 3 back")
end

spawn(module, fun, args)

@spec spawn(module(), atom(), list()) :: pid()

Spawns the given function fun from the given module passing it the given args and returns its PID.

Typically developers do not use the spawn functions, instead they use abstractions such as Task, GenServer and Agent, built on top of spawn, that spawns processes with more conveniences in terms of introspection and debugging.

Check the Process module for more process-related functions.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

spawn(SomeModule, :function, [1, 2, 3])

spawn_link(fun)

@spec spawn_link((-> any())) :: pid()

Spawns the given function, links it to the current process, and returns its PID.

Typically developers do not use the spawn functions, instead they use abstractions such as Task, GenServer and Agent, built on top of spawn, that spawns processes with more conveniences in terms of introspection and debugging.

Check the Process module for more process-related functions. For more information on linking, check Process.link/1.

The anonymous function receives 0 arguments, and may return any value.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

current = self()
child = spawn_link(fn -> send(current, {self(), 1 + 2}) end)

receive do
  {^child, 3} -> IO.puts("Received 3 back")
end

spawn_link(module, fun, args)

@spec spawn_link(module(), atom(), list()) :: pid()

Spawns the given function fun from the given module passing it the given args, links it to the current process, and returns its PID.

Typically developers do not use the spawn functions, instead they use abstractions such as Task, GenServer and Agent, built on top of spawn, that spawns processes with more conveniences in terms of introspection and debugging.

Check the Process module for more process-related functions. For more information on linking, check Process.link/1.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

spawn_link(SomeModule, :function, [1, 2, 3])

spawn_monitor(fun)

@spec spawn_monitor((-> any())) :: {pid(), reference()}

Spawns the given function, monitors it and returns its PID and monitoring reference.

Typically developers do not use the spawn functions, instead they use abstractions such as Task, GenServer and Agent, built on top of spawn, that spawns processes with more conveniences in terms of introspection and debugging.

Check the Process module for more process-related functions.

The anonymous function receives 0 arguments, and may return any value.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

current = self()
spawn_monitor(fn -> send(current, {self(), 1 + 2}) end)

spawn_monitor(module, fun, args)

@spec spawn_monitor(module(), atom(), list()) :: {pid(), reference()}

Spawns the given module and function passing the given args, monitors it and returns its PID and monitoring reference.

Typically developers do not use the spawn functions, instead they use abstractions such as Task, GenServer and Agent, built on top of spawn, that spawns processes with more conveniences in terms of introspection and debugging.

Check the Process module for more process-related functions.

Inlined by the compiler.

Examples

spawn_monitor(SomeModule, :function, [1, 2, 3])

struct(struct, fields \\ [])

@spec struct(module() | struct(), Enumerable.t()) :: struct()

Creates and updates a struct.

The struct argument may be an atom (which defines defstruct) or a struct itself. The second argument is any Enumerable that emits two-element tuples (key-value pairs) during enumeration.

Keys in the Enumerable that don't exist in the struct are automatically discarded. Note that keys must be atoms, as only atoms are allowed when defining a struct. If there are duplicate keys in the Enumerable, the last entry will be taken (same behavior as Map.new/1).

This function is useful for dynamically creating and updating structs, as well as for converting maps to structs; in the latter case, just inserting the appropriate :__struct__ field into the map may not be enough and struct/2 should be used instead.

Examples

defmodule User do
  defstruct name: "john"
end

struct(User)
#=> %User{name: "john"}

opts = [name: "meg"]
user = struct(User, opts)
#=> %User{name: "meg"}

struct(user, unknown: "value")
#=> %User{name: "meg"}

struct(User, %{name: "meg"})
#=> %User{name: "meg"}

# String keys are ignored
struct(User, %{"name" => "meg"})
#=> %User{name: "john"}

struct!(struct, fields \\ [])

@spec struct!(module() | struct(), Enumerable.t()) :: struct()

Similar to struct/2 but checks for key validity.

The function struct!/2 emulates the compile time behavior of structs. This means that:

when building a struct, as in struct!(SomeStruct, key: :value), it is equivalent to %SomeStruct{key: :value} and therefore this function will check if every given key-value belongs to the struct. If the struct is enforcing any key via @enforce_keys, those will be enforced as well;

when updating a struct, as in struct!(%SomeStruct{}, key: :value), it is equivalent to %SomeStruct{struct | key: :value} and therefore this function will check if every given key-value belongs to the struct.

tap(value, fun)

(since 1.12.0) (macro)

Pipes the first argument, value, into the second argument, a function fun, and returns value itself.

Useful for running synchronous side effects in a pipeline, using the |>/2 operator.

Examples

iex> tap(1, fn x -> x + 1 end)
1

Most commonly, this is used in pipelines, using the |>/2 operator. For example, let's suppose you want to inspect part of a data structure. You could write:

%{a: 1}
|> Map.update!(:a, & &1 + 2)
|> tap(&IO.inspect(&1.a))
|> Map.update!(:a, & &1 * 2)

then(value, fun)

(since 1.12.0) (macro)

Pipes the first argument, value, into the second argument, a function fun, and returns the result of calling fun.

In other words, it invokes the function fun with value as argument, and returns its result.

This is most commonly used in pipelines, using the |>/2 operator, allowing you to pipe a value to a function outside of its first argument.

Examples

iex> 1 |> then(fn x -> x * 2 end)
2

iex> 1 |> then(fn x -> Enum.drop(["a", "b", "c"], x) end)
["b", "c"]

throw(term)

@spec throw(term()) :: no_return()

A non-local return from a function.

Using throw/1 is generally discouraged, as it allows a function to escape from its regular execution flow, which can make the code harder to read. Furthermore, all thrown values must be caught by try/catch. See try/1 for more information.

Inlined by the compiler.

to_charlist(term)

(macro)

Converts the given term to a charlist according to the List.Chars protocol.

Examples

iex> to_charlist(:foo)
~c"foo"

to_string(term)

(macro)

Converts the argument to a string according to the String.Chars protocol.

This is the function invoked when there is string interpolation.

Examples

iex> to_string(:foo)
"foo"

to_timeout(duration)

(since 1.17.0)

@spec to_timeout([{unit, non_neg_integer()}] | timeout() | Duration.t()) :: timeout()
when unit: :week | :day | :hour | :minute | :second | :millisecond

Constructs a millisecond timeout from the given components, duration, or timeout.

This function is useful for constructing timeouts to use in functions that expect timeout/0 values (such as Process.send_after/4 and many others).

Argument

The duration argument can be one of a Duration, a timeout/0, or a list of components. Each of these is described below.

Passing Durations

Duration.t/0 structs can be converted to timeouts. The given duration must have year and month fields set to 0, since those cannot be reliably converted to milliseconds (due to the varying number of days in a month and year).

Microseconds in durations are converted to milliseconds (through System.convert_time_unit/3).

Passing components

The duration argument can also be keyword list which can contain the following keys, each appearing at most once with a non-negative integer value:

:week - the number of weeks (a week is always 7 days)
:day - the number of days (a day is always 24 hours)
:hour - the number of hours
:minute - the number of minutes
:second - the number of seconds
:millisecond - the number of milliseconds

The timeout is calculated as the sum of the components, each multiplied by the corresponding factor.

Passing timeouts

You can also pass timeouts directly to this functions, that is, milliseconds or the atom :infinity. In this case, this function just returns the given argument.

Examples

With a keyword list:

iex> to_timeout(hour: 1, minute: 30)
5400000

With a duration:

iex> to_timeout(%Duration{hour: 1, minute: 30})
5400000

With a timeout:

iex> to_timeout(5400000)
5400000
iex> to_timeout(:infinity)
:infinity

unless(condition, clauses)

(macro)

This macro is deprecated. Use if/2 instead.

Provides an unless macro.

This macro evaluates and returns the do block passed in as the second argument if condition evaluates to a falsy value (false or nil). Otherwise, it returns the value of the else block if present or nil if not.

See also if/2.

Examples

iex> unless(Enum.empty?([]), do: "Hello")
nil

iex> unless(Enum.empty?([1, 2, 3]), do: "Hello")
"Hello"

iex> unless Enum.sum([2, 2]) == 5 do
...>   "Math still works"
...> else
...>   "Math is broken"
...> end
"Math still works"

update_in(path, fun)

(macro)

Updates a nested structure via the given path.

This is similar to update_in/3, except the path is extracted via a macro rather than passing a list. For example:

update_in(opts[:foo][:bar], &(&1 + 1))

Is equivalent to:

update_in(opts, [:foo, :bar], &(&1 + 1))

This also works with nested structs and the struct.path.to.value way to specify paths:

update_in(struct.foo.bar, &(&1 + 1))

Note that in order for this macro to work, the complete path must always be visible by this macro. For more information about the supported path expressions, please check get_and_update_in/2 docs.

Examples

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> update_in(users["john"][:age], &(&1 + 1))
%{"john" => %{age: 28}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> update_in(users["john"].age, &(&1 + 1))
%{"john" => %{age: 28}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}

update_in(data, keys, fun)

@spec update_in(Access.t(), [term(), ...], (term() -> term())) :: Access.t()

Updates a key in a nested structure.

Uses the Access module to traverse the structures according to the given keys, unless the key is a function. If the key is a function, it will be invoked as specified in get_and_update_in/3.

data is a nested structure (that is, a map, keyword list, or struct that implements the Access behaviour). The fun argument receives the value of key (or nil if key is not present) and the result replaces the value in the structure.

Examples

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> update_in(users, ["john", :age], &(&1 + 1))
%{"john" => %{age: 28}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}

Note the current value given to the anonymous function may be nil. If any of the intermediate values are nil, it will raise:

iex> users = %{"john" => %{age: 27}, "meg" => %{age: 23}}
iex> update_in(users, ["jane", :age], & &1 + 1)
** (ArgumentError) could not put/update key :age on a nil value

use(module, opts \\ [])

(macro)

Uses the given module in the current context.

When calling:

use MyModule, some: :options

Elixir will invoke MyModule.__using__/1 passing the second argument of use as its argument. Since __using__/1 is typically a macro, all the usual macro rules apply, and its return value should be quoted code that is then inserted where use/2 is called.

Code injection

use MyModule works as a code-injection point in the caller. Given the caller of use MyModule has little control over how the code is injected, use/2 should be used with care. If you can, avoid use in favor of import/2 or alias/2 whenever possible.

Examples

For example, to write test cases using the ExUnit framework provided with Elixir, a developer should use the ExUnit.Case module:

defmodule AssertionTest do
  use ExUnit.Case, async: true

  test "always pass" do
    assert true
  end
end

In this example, Elixir will call the __using__/1 macro in the ExUnit.Case module with the keyword list [async: true] as its argument.

In other words, use/2 translates to:

defmodule AssertionTest do
  require ExUnit.Case
  ExUnit.Case.__using__(async: true)

  test "always pass" do
    assert true
  end
end

where ExUnit.Case defines the __using__/1 macro:

defmodule ExUnit.Case do
  defmacro __using__(opts) do
    # do something with opts
    quote do
      # return some code to inject in the caller
    end
  end
end

Best practices

__using__/1 is typically used when there is a need to set some state (via module attributes) or callbacks (like @before_compile, see the documentation for Module for more information) into the caller.

__using__/1 may also be used to alias, require, or import functionality from different modules:

defmodule MyModule do
  defmacro __using__(_opts) do
    quote do
      import MyModule.Foo
      import MyModule.Bar
      import MyModule.Baz

      alias MyModule.Repo
    end
  end
end

However, do not provide __using__/1 if all it does is to import, alias or require the module itself. For example, avoid this:

defmodule MyModule do
  defmacro __using__(_opts) do
    quote do
      import MyModule
    end
  end
end

In such cases, developers should instead import or alias the module directly, so that they can customize those as they wish, without the indirection behind use/2. Developers must also avoid defining functions inside __using__/1.

Given use MyModule can generate any code, it may not be easy for developers to understand the impact of use MyModule.

For this reason, to provide guidance and clarity, we recommend developers to include an admonition block in their @moduledoc that explains how use MyModule impacts their code. As an example, the GenServer documentation outlines:

use GenServer

When you use GenServer, the GenServer module will set @behaviour GenServer and define a child_spec/1 function, so your module can be used as a child in a supervision tree.

This provides a quick summary of how using a module impacts the user code. Keep in mind to only list changes made to the public API of the module. For example, if use MyModule sets an internal attribute called @_my_module_info and this attribute is never meant to be public, it must not be listed.

For convenience, the markup notation to generate the admonition block above is:

> #### `use GenServer` {: .info}
>
> When you `use GenServer`, the GenServer module will
> set `@behaviour GenServer` and define a `child_spec/1`
> function, so your module can be used as a child
> in a supervision tree.

var!(var, context \\ nil)

(macro)

Marks that the given variable should not be hygienized.

This macro expects a variable and it is typically invoked inside quote/2 to mark that a variable should not be hygienized. See quote/2 for more information.

Examples

iex> Kernel.var!(example) = 1
1
iex> Kernel.var!(example)
1

left |> right

(macro)

Pipe operator.

This operator introduces the expression on the left-hand side as the first argument to the function call on the right-hand side.

Examples

iex> [1, [2], 3] |> List.flatten()
[1, 2, 3]

The example above is the same as calling List.flatten([1, [2], 3]).

The |>/2 operator is mostly useful when there is a desire to execute a series of operations resembling a pipeline:

iex> [1, [2], 3] |> List.flatten() |> Enum.map(fn x -> x * 2 end)
[2, 4, 6]

In the example above, the list [1, [2], 3] is passed as the first argument to the List.flatten/1 function, then the flattened list is passed as the first argument to the Enum.map/2 function which doubles each element of the list.

In other words, the expression above simply translates to:

Enum.map(List.flatten([1, [2], 3]), fn x -> x * 2 end)

Pitfalls

There are two common pitfalls when using the pipe operator.

The first one is related to operator precedence. For example, the following expression:

String.graphemes "Hello" |> Enum.reverse

Translates to:

String.graphemes("Hello" |> Enum.reverse())

which results in an error as the Enumerable protocol is not defined for binaries. Adding explicit parentheses resolves the ambiguity:

String.graphemes("Hello") |> Enum.reverse()

Or, even better:

"Hello" |> String.graphemes() |> Enum.reverse()

The second limitation is that Elixir always pipes to a function call. Therefore, to pipe into an anonymous function, you need to invoke it:

some_fun = &Regex.replace(~r/l/, &1, "L")
"Hello" |> some_fun.()

Alternatively, you can use then/2 for the same effect:

some_fun = &Regex.replace(~r/l/, &1, "L")
"Hello" |> then(some_fun)

then/2 is most commonly used when you want to pipe to a function but the value is expected outside of the first argument, such as above. By replacing some_fun by its value, we get:

"Hello" |> then(&Regex.replace(~r/l/, &1, "L"))

left || right

(macro)

Boolean "or" operator.

Provides a short-circuit operator that evaluates and returns the second expression only if the first one does not evaluate to a truthy value (that is, it is either nil or false). Returns the first expression otherwise.

Not allowed in guard clauses.

Examples

iex> Enum.empty?([1]) || Enum.empty?([1])
false

iex> List.first([]) || true
true

iex> Enum.empty?([1]) || 1
1

iex> Enum.empty?([]) || throw(:bad)
true

Note that, unlike or/2, this operator accepts any expression as the first argument, not only booleans.

Library guidelines

This document outlines general guidelines for those writing and publishing Elixir libraries meant to be consumed by other developers.

Getting started

You can create a new Elixir library by running the mix new command:

$ mix new my_library

The project name is given in the snake_case convention where all letters are lowercase and words are separate with underscores. This is the same convention used by variables, function names and atoms in Elixir. See the Naming Conventions document for more information.

Every project has a mix.exs file, with instructions on how to build, compile, run tests, and so on. Libraries commonly have a lib directory, which includes Elixir source code, and a test directory. A src directory may also exist for Erlang sources.

The mix new command also allows the --sup option to scaffold a new project with a supervision tree out of the box. For more information on running your project, see the official Mix & OTP guide or Mix documentation.

Publishing

Writing code is only the first of many steps to publish a package. We strongly recommend developers to:

Choose a versioning schema. Elixir requires versions to be in the format MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH but the meaning of those numbers is up to you. Most projects choose Semantic Versioning.

Choose a license. The most common licenses in the Elixir community are the MIT License and the Apache License 2.0. The latter is also the one used by Elixir itself.

Run the code formatter. The code formatter formats your code according to a consistent style shared by your library and the whole community, making it easier for other developers to understand your code and contribute.

Write tests. Elixir ships with a test-framework named ExUnit. The project generated by mix new includes sample tests and doctests.

Write documentation. The Elixir community is proud of treating documentation as a first-class citizen and making documentation easily accessible. Libraries contribute to the status quo by providing complete API documentation with examples for their modules, types and functions. See the Writing documentation chapter of the Getting Started guide for more information. Projects like ExDoc can be used to generate HTML and EPUB documents from the documentation. ExDoc also supports "extra pages", like this one that you are reading. Such pages augment the documentation with tutorials, guides, references, and even cheat-sheets.

Follow best practices. The Elixir project documents a series of anti-patterns that you may want to avoid in your code. The process-related anti-patterns and meta-programming anti-patterns are of special attention to library authors.

Projects are often made available to other developers by publishing a Hex package. Hex also supports private packages for organizations. If ExDoc is configured for the Mix project, publishing a package on Hex will also automatically publish the generated documentation to HexDocs.

Dependency handling

When your library is used as a dependency, it runs by default in the :prod environment. Therefore, if your library has dependencies that are only useful in development or testing, you want to specify those dependencies with the :only option. You can also specify :optional dependencies in your library, which are not enforced upon users of your library. In such cases, you should also consider compiling your projects with the mix compile --no-optional-deps --warnings-as-errors in your test environments, to ensure your library compiles without warnings even if optional dependencies are missing. See mix deps for all available options.

Keep in mind your library's lockfile (usually named mix.lock) is ignored by the host project. Running mix deps.get in the host project attempts to get the latest possible versions of your library’s dependencies, as specified by the requirements in the deps section of your mix.exs. These versions might be greater than those stored in your mix.lock (and hence used in your tests / CI).

On the other hand, contributors of your library, need a deterministic build, which implies the presence of mix.lock in your Version Control System (VCS), such as git.

If you want to validate both scenarios, you should check the mix.lock into version control and run two different Continuous Integration (CI) workflows: one that relies on the mix.lock for deterministic builds, and another one, that starts with mix deps.unlock --all and always compiles your library and runs tests against latest versions of dependencies. The latter one might be even run nightly or otherwise recurrently to stay notified about any possible issue in regard to dependencies updates.

Regex

Provides regular expressions for Elixir.

Regex is based on PCRE (Perl Compatible Regular Expressions) and built on top of Erlang's :re module. More information can be found in the :re module documentation.

Regular expressions in Elixir can be created using the sigils ~r (see sigil_r/2):

# A simple regular expression that matches foo anywhere in the string
~r/foo/

# A regular expression with case insensitive and Unicode options
~r/foo/iu

Regular expressions created via sigils are pre-compiled and stored in the .beam file. Note that this may be a problem if you are precompiling Elixir, see the "Precompilation" section for more information.

A Regex is represented internally as the Regex struct. Therefore, %Regex{} can be used whenever there is a need to match on them. Keep in mind that all of the structs fields are private. There is also not guarantee two regular expressions from the same source are equal, for example:

~r/(?<foo>.)(?<bar>.)/ == ~r/(?<foo>.)(?<bar>.)/

may return true or false depending on your machine, endianness, available optimizations and others. You can, however, retrieve the source of a compiled regular expression by accessing the source field, and then compare those directly:

~r/(?<foo>.)(?<bar>.)/.source == ~r/(?<foo>.)(?<bar>.)/.source

Escapes

Escape sequences are split into two categories.

Non-printing characters

\a - Alarm, that is, the BEL character (hex 07)
\e - Escape (hex 1B)
\f - Form feed (hex 0C)
\n - Line feed (hex 0A)
\r - Carriage return (hex 0D)
\t - Tab (hex 09)
\xhh - Character with hex code hh
\x{hhh..} - Character with hex code hhh..

\u and \U are not supported. Other escape sequences, such as \ddd for octals, are supported but discouraged.

Generic character types

\d - Any decimal digit
\D - Any character that is not a decimal digit
\h - Any horizontal whitespace character
\H - Any character that is not a horizontal whitespace character
\s - Any whitespace character
\S - Any character that is not a whitespace character
\v - Any vertical whitespace character
\V - Any character that is not a vertical whitespace character
\w - Any "word" character
\W - Any "non-word" character

Modifiers

The modifiers available when creating a Regex are:

:unicode (u) - enables Unicode specific patterns like \p and causes character classes like \w, \W, \s, and the like to also match on Unicode (see examples below in "Character classes"). It expects valid Unicode strings to be given on match

:caseless (i) - adds case insensitivity

:dotall (s) - causes dot to match newlines and also set newline to anycrlf; the new line setting can be overridden by setting (*CR) or (*LF) or (*CRLF) or (*ANY) according to :re documentation

:multiline (m) - causes ^ and $ to mark the beginning and end of each line; use \A and \z to match the end or beginning of the string

:extended (x) - whitespace characters are ignored except when escaped or within [..], and allow # to delimit comments

:firstline (f) - forces the unanchored pattern to match before or at the first newline, though the matched text may continue over the newline

:ungreedy (U) - inverts the "greediness" of the regexp (the previous r option is deprecated in favor of U)

The options not available are:

:anchored - not available, use ^ or \A instead
:dollar_endonly - not available, use \z instead
:no_auto_capture - not available, use ?: instead
:newline - not available, use (*CR) or (*LF) or (*CRLF) or (*ANYCRLF) or (*ANY) at the beginning of the regexp according to the :re documentation

Captures

Many functions in this module handle what to capture in a regex match via the :capture option. The supported values are:

:all - all captured subpatterns including the complete matching string (this is the default)

:first - only the first captured subpattern, which is always the complete matching part of the string; all explicitly captured subpatterns are discarded

:all_but_first - all but the first matching subpattern, i.e. all explicitly captured subpatterns, but not the complete matching part of the string

:none - does not return matching subpatterns at all

:all_names - captures all named subpattern matches in the Regex as a list ordered alphabetically by the names of the subpatterns

list(binary | atom) - a list of named captures to capture

Character classes

Regex supports several built in named character classes. These are used by enclosing the class name in [: :] inside a group. For example:

iex> String.match?("123", ~r/^[[:alnum:]]+$/)
true
iex> String.match?("123 456", ~r/^[[:alnum:][:blank:]]+$/)
true

The supported class names are:

alnum - Letters and digits
alpha - Letters
blank - Space or tab only
cntrl - Control characters
digit - Decimal digits (same as \d)
graph - Printing characters, excluding space
lower - Lowercase letters
print - Printing characters, including space
punct - Printing characters, excluding letters, digits, and space
space - Whitespace (the same as \s from PCRE 8.34)
upper - Uppercase letters
word - "Word" characters (same as \w)
xdigit - Hexadecimal digits

There is another character class, ascii, that erroneously matches Latin-1 characters instead of the 0-127 range specified by POSIX. This cannot be fixed without altering the behavior of other classes, so we recommend matching the range with [\\0-\x7f] instead.

Note the behavior of those classes may change according to the Unicode and other modifiers:

iex> String.match?("josé", ~r/^[[:lower:]]+$/)
false
iex> String.match?("josé", ~r/^[[:lower:]]+$/u)
true
iex> Regex.replace(~r/\s/, "Unicode\u00A0spaces", "-")
"Unicode spaces"
iex> Regex.replace(~r/\s/u, "Unicode\u00A0spaces", "-")
"Unicode-spaces"

Precompilation

Regular expressions built with sigil are precompiled and stored in .beam files. Precompiled regexes will be checked in runtime and may work slower between operating systems and OTP releases. This is rarely a problem, as most Elixir code shared during development is compiled on the target (such as dependencies, archives, and escripts) and, when running in production, the code must either be compiled on the target (via mix compile or similar) or released on the host (via mix releases or similar) with a matching OTP, operating system and architecture as the target.

If you know you are running on a different system than the current one and you are doing multiple matches with the regex, you can manually invoke Regex.recompile/1 or Regex.recompile!/1 to perform a runtime version check and recompile the regex if necessary.

Summary

Types

t()

Functions

compile(source, opts \\ "")

Compiles the regular expression.

compile!(source, options \\ "")

Compiles the regular expression and raises Regex.CompileError in case of errors.

escape(string)

Escapes a string to be literally matched in a regex.

match?(regex, string)

Returns a boolean indicating whether there was a match or not.

named_captures(regex, string, options \\ [])

Returns the given captures as a map or nil if no captures are found.

names(regex)

Returns a list of names in the regex.

opts(regex)

Returns the regex options.

re_pattern(regex)

Returns the underlying re_pattern in the regular expression.

recompile(regex)

Recompiles the existing regular expression if necessary.

recompile!(regex)

Recompiles the existing regular expression and raises Regex.CompileError in case of errors.

replace(regex, string, replacement, options \\ [])

Receives a regex, a binary and a replacement, returns a new binary where all matches are replaced by the replacement.

run(regex, string, options \\ [])

Runs the regular expression against the given string until the first match. It returns a list with all captures or nil if no match occurred.

scan(regex, string, options \\ [])

Same as run/3 but returns all non-overlapping matches of the regular expression.

source(regex)

Returns the regex source as a binary.

split(regex, string, options \\ [])

Splits the given target based on the given pattern and in the given number of parts.

version()

Returns the version of the underlying Regex engine.

Types

t()

@type t() :: %Regex{
  opts: binary() | [term()],
  re_pattern: term(),
  re_version: term(),
  source: binary()
}

Functions

compile(source, opts \\ "")

@spec compile(binary(), binary() | [term()]) :: {:ok, t()} | {:error, term()}

Compiles the regular expression.

The given options can either be a binary with the characters representing the same regex options given to the ~r (see sigil_r/2) sigil, or a list of options, as expected by the Erlang's :re module.

It returns {:ok, regex} in case of success, {:error, reason} otherwise.

Examples

Regex.compile("foo")
#=> {:ok, ~r/foo/}

Regex.compile("foo", "i")
#=>{:ok, ~r/foo/i}

Regex.compile("*foo")
#=> {:error, {~c"nothing to repeat", 0}}

compile!(source, options \\ "")

@spec compile!(binary(), binary() | [term()]) :: t()

Compiles the regular expression and raises Regex.CompileError in case of errors.

escape(string)

@spec escape(String.t()) :: String.t()

Escapes a string to be literally matched in a regex.

Examples

iex> Regex.escape(".")
"\\."

iex> Regex.escape("\\what if")
"\\\\what\\ if"

match?(regex, string)

@spec match?(t(), String.t()) :: boolean()

Returns a boolean indicating whether there was a match or not.

Examples

iex> Regex.match?(~r/foo/, "foo")
true

iex> Regex.match?(~r/foo/, "bar")
false

Elixir also provides text-based match operator =~/2 and function String.match?/2 as an alternative to test strings against regular expressions and strings.

named_captures(regex, string, options \\ [])

@spec named_captures(t(), String.t(), [term()]) :: map() | nil

Returns the given captures as a map or nil if no captures are found.

Options

:return - when set to :index, returns byte index and match length. Defaults to :binary.

Examples

iex> Regex.named_captures(~r/c(?<foo>d)/, "abcd")
%{"foo" => "d"}

iex> Regex.named_captures(~r/a(?<foo>b)c(?<bar>d)/, "abcd")
%{"bar" => "d", "foo" => "b"}

iex> Regex.named_captures(~r/a(?<foo>b)c(?<bar>d)/, "efgh")
nil

names(regex)

@spec names(t()) :: [String.t()]

Returns a list of names in the regex.

Examples

iex> Regex.names(~r/(?<foo>bar)/)
["foo"]

opts(regex)

@spec opts(t()) :: [term()]

Returns the regex options.

See the documentation of Regex.compile/2 for more information.

Examples

iex> Regex.opts(~r/foo/m)
[:multiline]

iex> Regex.opts(Regex.compile!("foo", [:caseless]))
[:caseless]

re_pattern(regex)

@spec re_pattern(t()) :: term()

Returns the underlying re_pattern in the regular expression.

recompile(regex)

(since 1.4.0)

@spec recompile(t()) :: {:ok, t()} | {:error, any()}

Recompiles the existing regular expression if necessary.

This checks the version stored in the regular expression and recompiles the regex in case of version mismatch.

recompile!(regex)

(since 1.4.0)

@spec recompile!(t()) :: t()

Recompiles the existing regular expression and raises Regex.CompileError in case of errors.

replace(regex, string, replacement, options \\ [])

@spec replace(t(), String.t(), String.t() | (... -> String.t()), [
  {:global, boolean()}
]) :: String.t()

Receives a regex, a binary and a replacement, returns a new binary where all matches are replaced by the replacement.

The replacement can be either a string or a function that returns a string. The resulting string is used as a replacement for every match.

When the replacement is a string, it allows specific captures of the match using brackets at the regex expression and accessing them in the replacement via \N or \g{N}, where N is the number of the capture. In case \0 is used, the whole match is inserted. Note that in regexes the backslash needs to be escaped, hence in practice you'll need to use \\N and \\g{N}.

When the replacement is a function, it allows specific captures too. The function may have arity N where each argument maps to a capture, with the first argument being the whole match. If the function expects more arguments than captures found, the remaining arguments will receive "".

Options

:global - when false, replaces only the first occurrence (defaults to true)

Examples

iex> Regex.replace(~r/d/, "abc", "d")
"abc"

iex> Regex.replace(~r/b/, "abc", "d")
"adc"

iex> Regex.replace(~r/b/, "abc", "[\\0]")
"a[b]c"

iex> Regex.replace(~r/a(b|d)c/, "abcadc", "[\\1]")
"[b][d]"

iex> Regex.replace(~r/\.(\d)$/, "500.5", ".\\g{1}0")
"500.50"

iex> Regex.replace(~r/a(b|d)c/, "abcadc", fn _, x -> "[#{x}]" end)
"[b][d]"

iex> Regex.replace(~r/(\w+)@(\w+).(\w+)/, "abc@def.com", fn _full, _c1, _c2, c3 -> "TLD: #{c3}" end)
"TLD: com"

iex> Regex.replace(~r/a/, "abcadc", "A", global: false)
"Abcadc"

run(regex, string, options \\ [])

@spec run(t(), binary(), [term()]) :: nil | [binary()] | [{integer(), integer()}]

Runs the regular expression against the given string until the first match. It returns a list with all captures or nil if no match occurred.

Options

:return - when set to :index, returns byte index and match length. Defaults to :binary.
:capture - what to capture in the result. See the "Captures" section to see the possible capture values.
:offset - (since v1.12.0) specifies the starting offset to match in the given string. Defaults to zero.

Examples

iex> Regex.run(~r/c(d)/, "abcd")
["cd", "d"]

iex> Regex.run(~r/e/, "abcd")
nil

iex> Regex.run(~r/c(d)/, "abcd", return: :index)
[{2, 2}, {3, 1}]

iex> Regex.run(~r/c(d)/, "abcd", capture: :first)
["cd"]

iex> Regex.run(~r/c(?<foo>d)/, "abcd", capture: ["foo", "bar"])
["d", ""]

scan(regex, string, options \\ [])

@spec scan(t(), String.t(), [term()]) :: [[String.t()]] | [[{integer(), integer()}]]

Same as run/3 but returns all non-overlapping matches of the regular expression.

A list of lists is returned, where each entry in the primary list represents a match and each entry in the secondary list represents the captured contents.

Options

:return - when set to :index, returns byte index and match length. Defaults to :binary.
:capture - what to capture in the result. See the "Captures" section to see the possible capture values.
:offset - (since v1.12.0) specifies the starting offset to match in the given string. Defaults to zero.

Examples

iex> Regex.scan(~r/c(d|e)/, "abcd abce")
[["cd", "d"], ["ce", "e"]]

iex> Regex.scan(~r/c(?:d|e)/, "abcd abce")
[["cd"], ["ce"]]

iex> Regex.scan(~r/e/, "abcd")
[]

iex> Regex.scan(~r/ab|bc|cd/, "abcd")
[["ab"], ["cd"]]

iex> Regex.scan(~r/ab|bc|cd/, "abbccd")
[["ab"], ["bc"], ["cd"]]

iex> Regex.scan(~r/\p{Sc}/u, "$, £, and €")
[["$"], ["£"], ["€"]]

iex> Regex.scan(~r/=+/, "=ü†ƒ8===", return: :index)
[[{0, 1}], [{9, 3}]]

iex> Regex.scan(~r/c(d|e)/, "abcd abce", capture: :first)
[["cd"], ["ce"]]

source(regex)

@spec source(t()) :: String.t()

Returns the regex source as a binary.

Examples

iex> Regex.source(~r/foo/)
"foo"

split(regex, string, options \\ [])

@spec split(t(), String.t(), [term()]) :: [String.t()]

Splits the given target based on the given pattern and in the given number of parts.

Options

:parts - when specified, splits the string into the given number of parts. If not specified, :parts defaults to :infinity, which will split the string into the maximum number of parts possible based on the given pattern.

:trim - when true, removes empty strings ("") from the result. Defaults to false.

:on - specifies which captures to split the string on, and in what order. Defaults to :first which means captures inside the regex do not affect the splitting process. See the "Captures" section to see the possible capture values.

:include_captures - when true, includes in the result the matches of the regular expression. The matches are not counted towards the maximum number of parts if combined with the :parts option. Defaults to false.

Examples

iex> Regex.split(~r/-/, "a-b-c")
["a", "b", "c"]

iex> Regex.split(~r/-/, "a-b-c", parts: 2)
["a", "b-c"]

iex> Regex.split(~r/-/, "abc")
["abc"]

iex> Regex.split(~r//, "abc")
["", "a", "b", "c", ""]

iex> Regex.split(~r/a(?<second>b)c/, "abc")
["", ""]

iex> Regex.split(~r/a(?<second>b)c/, "abc", on: [:second])
["a", "c"]

iex> Regex.split(~r/(x)/, "Elixir", include_captures: true)
["Eli", "x", "ir"]

iex> Regex.split(~r/a(?<second>b)c/, "abc", on: [:second], include_captures: true)
["a", "b", "c"]

iex> Regex.split(~r/-/, "-a-b--c", trim: true)
["a", "b", "c"]

version()

(since 1.4.0)

@spec version() :: term()

Returns the version of the underlying Regex engine.

Syntax reference

Elixir syntax was designed to have a straightforward conversion to an abstract syntax tree (AST). This means the Elixir syntax is mostly uniform with a handful of "syntax sugar" constructs to reduce the noise in common Elixir idioms.

This document covers all of Elixir syntax constructs as a reference and then discuss their exact AST representation.

Reserved words

These are the reserved words in the Elixir language. They are detailed throughout this guide but summed up here for convenience:

true, false, nil - used as atoms
when, and, or, not, in - used as operators
fn - used for anonymous function definitions
do, end, catch, rescue, after, else - used in do-end blocks

Data types

Numbers

Integers (1234) and floats (123.4) in Elixir are represented as a sequence of digits that may be separated by underscore for readability purposes, such as 1_000_000. Integers never contain a dot (.) in their representation. Floats contain a dot and at least one other digit after the dot. Floats also support the scientific notation, such as 123.4e10 or 123.4E10.

Atoms

Unquoted atoms start with a colon (:) which must be immediately followed by a Unicode letter or an underscore. The atom may continue using a sequence of Unicode letters, numbers, underscores, and @. Atoms may end in ! or ?. Valid unquoted atoms are: :ok, :ISO8601, and :integer?.

If the colon is immediately followed by a pair of double- or single-quotes surrounding the atom name, the atom is considered quoted. In contrast with an unquoted atom, this one can be made of any Unicode character (not only letters), such as :'🌢 Elixir', :"++olá++", and :"123".

Quoted and unquoted atoms with the same name are considered equivalent, so :atom, :"atom", and :'atom' represent the same atom. The only catch is that the compiler will warn when quotes are used in atoms that do not need to be quoted.

All operators in Elixir are also valid atoms. Valid examples are :foo, :FOO, :foo_42, :foo@bar, and :++. Invalid examples are :@foo (@ is not allowed at start), :123 (numbers are not allowed at start), and :(*) (not a valid operator).

true, false, and nil are reserved words that are represented by the atoms :true, :false and :nil respectively.

To learn more about all Unicode characters allowed in atom, see the Unicode syntax document.

Strings

Single-line strings in Elixir are written between double-quotes, such as "foo". Any double-quote inside the string must be escaped with \. Strings support Unicode characters and are stored as UTF-8 encoded binaries.

Multi-line strings in Elixir are written with three double-quotes, and can have unescaped quotes within them. The resulting string will end with a newline. The indentation of the last """ is used to strip indentation from the inner string. For example:

iex> test = """
...>     this
...>     is
...>     a
...>     test
...> """
"    this\n    is\n    a\n    test\n"
iex> test = """
...>     This
...>     Is
...>     A
...>     Test
...>     """
"This\nIs\nA\nTest\n"

Strings are always represented as themselves in the AST.

Charlists

Charlists are lists of non-negative integers where each integer represents a Unicode code point.

iex(6)> 'abc' === [97, 98, 99]
true

Charlists are written in single-quotes, such as 'foo'. Any single-quote inside the string must be escaped with \. Multi-line charlists are written with three single-quotes ('''), the same way multi-line strings are. However, this syntax is deprecated in favor of the charlist sigil ~c.

Charlists are always represented as themselves in the AST.

For more in-depth information, please read the "Charlists" section in the List module.

Lists, tuples and binaries

Data structures such as lists, tuples, and binaries are marked respectively by the delimiters [...], {...}, and <<...>>. Each element is separated by comma. A trailing comma is also allowed, such as in [1, 2, 3,].

Maps and keyword lists

Maps use the %{...} notation and each key-value is given by pairs marked with =>, such as %{"hello" => 1, 2 => "world"}.

Both keyword lists (list of two-element tuples where the first element is an atom) and maps with atom keys support a keyword notation where the colon character : is moved to the end of the atom. %{hello: "world"} is equivalent to %{:hello => "world"} and [foo: :bar] is equivalent to [{:foo, :bar}]. We discuss keywords in later sections.

Structs

Structs built on the map syntax by passing the struct name between % and {. For example, %User{...}.

Expressions

Variables

Variables in Elixir must start with an underscore or a Unicode letter that is not in uppercase or titlecase. The variable may continue using a sequence of Unicode letters, numbers, and underscores. Variables may end in ? or !. To learn more about all Unicode characters allowed in variables, see the Unicode syntax document.

Elixir's naming conventions recommend variables to be in snake_case format.

Non-qualified calls (local calls)

Non-qualified calls, such as add(1, 2), must start with characters and then follow the same rules as variables, which are optionally followed by parentheses, and then arguments.

Parentheses are required for zero-arity calls (i.e. calls without arguments), to avoid ambiguity with variables. If parentheses are used, they must immediately follow the function name without spaces. For example, add (1, 2) is a syntax error, since (1, 2) is treated as an invalid block which is attempted to be given as a single argument to add.

Elixir's naming conventions recommend calls to be in snake_case format.

Operators

As many programming languages, Elixir also support operators as non-qualified calls with their precedence and associativity rules. Constructs such as =, when, & and @ are simply treated as operators. See the Operators page for a full reference.

Qualified calls (remote calls)

Qualified calls, such as Math.add(1, 2), must start with characters and then follow the same rules as variables, which are optionally followed by parentheses, and then arguments. Qualified calls also support operators, such as Kernel.+(1, 2). Elixir also allows the function name to be written between double- or single-quotes, allowing any character in between the quotes, such as Math."++add++"(1, 2).

Similar to non-qualified calls, parentheses have different meaning for zero-arity calls (i.e. calls without arguments). If parentheses are used, such as mod.fun(), it means a function call. If parenthesis are skipped, such as map.field, it means accessing a field of a map.

Elixir's naming conventions recommend calls to be in snake_case format.

Aliases

Aliases are constructs that expand to atoms at compile-time. The alias String expands to the atom :"Elixir.String". Aliases must start with an ASCII uppercase character which may be followed by any ASCII letter, number, or underscore. Non-ASCII characters are not supported in aliases.

Multiple aliases can be joined with ., such as MyApp.String, and it expands to the atom :"Elixir.MyApp.String". The dot is effectively part of the name but it can also be used for composition. If you define alias MyApp.Example, as: Example in your code, then Example will always expand to :"Elixir.MyApp.Example" and Example.String will expand to :"Elixir.MyApp.Example.String".

Elixir's naming conventions recommend aliases to be in CamelCase format.

Module attributes

Module attributes are module-specific storage and are written as the composition of the unary operator @ with variables and local calls. For example, to write to a module attribute named foo, use @foo "value", and use @foo to read from it. Given module attributes are written using existing constructs, they follow the same rules above defined for operators, variables, and local calls.

Blocks

Blocks are multiple Elixir expressions separated by newlines or semi-colons. A new block may be created at any moment by using parentheses.

Left to right arrow

The left to right arrow (->) is used to establish a relationship between left and right, commonly referred as clauses. The left side may have zero, one, or more arguments; the right side is zero, one, or more expressions separated by new line. The -> may appear one or more times between one of the following terminators: do-end, fn-end or (-). When -> is used, only other clauses are allowed between those terminators. Mixing clauses and regular expressions is invalid syntax.

It is seen on case and cond constructs between do and end:

case 1 do
  2 -> 3
  4 -> 5
end

cond do
  true -> false
end

Seen in typespecs between ( and ):

(integer(), boolean() -> integer())

It is also used between fn and end for building anonymous functions:

fn
  x, y -> x + y
end

Sigils

Sigils start with ~ and are followed by one lowercase letter or by one or more uppercase letters, immediately followed by one of the following pairs:

( and )
{ and }
[ and ]
< and >
" and "
' and '
| and |
/ and /

After closing the pair, zero or more ASCII letters and digits can be given as a modifier. Sigils are expressed as non-qualified calls prefixed with sigil_ where the first argument is the sigil contents as a string and the second argument is a list of integers as modifiers:

If the sigil letter is in uppercase, no interpolation is allowed in the sigil, otherwise its contents may be dynamic. Compare the results of the sigils below for more information:

~s/f#{"o"}o/
~S/f#{"o"}o/

Sigils are useful to encode text with their own escaping rules, such as regular expressions, datetimes, and others.

The Elixir AST

Elixir syntax was designed to have a straightforward conversion to an abstract syntax tree (AST). Elixir's AST is a regular Elixir data structure composed of the following elements:

atoms - such as :foo
integers - such as 42
floats - such as 13.1
strings - such as "hello"
lists - such as [1, 2, 3]
tuples with two elements - such as {"hello", :world}
tuples with three elements, representing calls or variables, as explained next

The building block of Elixir's AST is a call, such as:

sum(1, 2, 3)

which is represented as a tuple with three elements:

{:sum, meta, [1, 2, 3]}

the first element is an atom (or another tuple), the second element is a list of two-element tuples with metadata (such as line numbers) and the third is a list of arguments.

We can retrieve the AST for any Elixir expression by calling quote:

quote do
  sum()
end
#=> {:sum, [], []}

Variables are also represented using a tuple with three elements and a combination of lists and atoms, for example:

quote do
  sum
end
#=> {:sum, [], Elixir}

You can see that variables are also represented with a tuple, except the third element is an atom expressing the variable context.

Over the course of this section, we will explore many Elixir syntax constructs alongside their AST representations.

Operators

Operators are treated as non-qualified calls:

quote do
  1 + 2
end
#=> {:+, [], [1, 2]}

Note that . is also an operator. Remote calls use the dot in the AST with two arguments, where the second argument is always an atom:

quote do
  foo.bar(1, 2, 3)
end
#=> {{:., [], [{:foo, [], Elixir}, :bar]}, [], [1, 2, 3]}

Calling anonymous functions uses the dot in the AST with a single argument, mirroring the fact the function name is "missing" from right side of the dot:

quote do
  foo.(1, 2, 3)
end
#=> {{:., [], [{:foo, [], Elixir}]}, [], [1, 2, 3]}

Aliases

Aliases are represented by an __aliases__ call with each segment separated by a dot as an argument:

quote do
  Foo.Bar.Baz
end
#=> {:__aliases__, [], [:Foo, :Bar, :Baz]}

quote do
  __MODULE__.Bar.Baz
end
#=> {:__aliases__, [], [{:__MODULE__, [], Elixir}, :Bar, :Baz]}

All arguments, except the first, are guaranteed to be atoms.

Data structures

Remember that lists are literals, so they are represented as themselves in the AST:

quote do
  [1, 2, 3]
end
#=> [1, 2, 3]

Tuples have their own representation, except for two-element tuples, which are represented as themselves:

quote do
  {1, 2}
end
#=> {1, 2}

quote do
  {1, 2, 3}
end
#=> {:{}, [], [1, 2, 3]}

Binaries have a representation similar to tuples, except they are tagged with :<<>> instead of :{}:

quote do
  <<1, 2, 3>>
end
#=> {:<<>>, [], [1, 2, 3]}

The same applies to maps, where pairs are treated as a list of tuples with two elements:

quote do
  %{1 => 2, 3 => 4}
end
#=> {:%{}, [], [{1, 2}, {3, 4}]}

Blocks

Blocks are represented as a __block__ call with each line as a separate argument:

quote do
  1
  2
  3
end
#=> {:__block__, [], [1, 2, 3]}

quote do 1; 2; 3; end
#=> {:__block__, [], [1, 2, 3]}

Left to right arrow

The left to right arrow (->) is represented similar to operators except that they are always part of a list, its left side represents a list of arguments and the right side is an expression.

For example, in case and cond:

quote do
  case 1 do
    2 -> 3
    4 -> 5
  end
end
#=> {:case, [], [1, [do: [{:->, [], [[2], 3]}, {:->, [], [[4], 5]}]]]}

quote do
  cond do
    true -> false
  end
end
#=> {:cond, [], [[do: [{:->, [], [[true], false]}]]]}

Between ( and ):

quote do
  (1, 2 -> 3
   4, 5 -> 6)
end
#=> [{:->, [], [[1, 2], 3]}, {:->, [], [[4, 5], 6]}]

Between fn and end:

quote do
  fn
    1, 2 -> 3
    4, 5 -> 6
  end
end
#=> {:fn, [], [{:->, [], [[1, 2], 3]}, {:->, [], [[4, 5], 6]}]}

Qualified tuples

Qualified tuples (foo.{bar, baz}) are represented by a {:., [], [expr, :{}]} call, where the expr represents the left hand side of the dot, and the arguments represent the elements inside the curly braces. This is used in Elixir to provide multi aliases:

quote do
  Foo.{Bar, Baz}
end
#=> {{:., [], [{:__aliases__, [], [:Foo]}, :{}]}, [], [{:__aliases__, [], [:Bar]}, {:__aliases__, [], [:Baz]}]}

do-end blocks

Elixir's do-end blocks are equivalent to keywords as the last argument of a function call, where the block contents are wrapped in parentheses. For example:

if true do
  this
else
  that
end

is the same as:

if(true, do: (this), else: (that))

While the construct above does not require custom nodes in Elixir's AST, they are restricted only to certain keywords, listed next:

after
catch
else
rescue

You will find them in constructs such as receive, try, and others. You can also find more examples in the Optional Syntax chapter.

What are anti-patterns?

Anti-patterns describe common mistakes or indicators of problems in code. They are also known as "code smells".

The goal of these guides is to document potential anti-patterns found in Elixir software and teach developers how to identify them and their pitfalls. If an existing piece of code matches an anti-pattern, it does not mean your code must be rewritten. Sometimes, even if a snippet matches a potential anti-pattern and its limitations, it may be the best approach to the problem at hand. No codebase is free of anti-patterns and one should not aim to remove all of them.

The anti-patterns in these guides are broken into 4 main categories:

Code-related anti-patterns: related to your code and particular language idioms and features;

Design-related anti-patterns: related to your modules, functions, and the role they play within a codebase;

Process-related anti-patterns: related to processes and process-based abstractions;

Meta-programming anti-patterns: related to meta-programming.

Each anti-pattern is documented using the following structure:

Name: Unique identifier of the anti-pattern. This name is important to facilitate communication between developers;

Problem: How the anti-pattern can harm code quality and what impacts this can have for developers;

Example: Code and textual descriptions to illustrate the occurrence of the anti-pattern;

Refactoring: Ways to change your code to improve its qualities. Examples of refactored code are presented to illustrate these changes.

An additional section with "Additional Remarks" may be provided. Those may include known scenarios where the anti-pattern does not apply.

The initial catalog of anti-patterns was proposed by Lucas Vegi and Marco Tulio Valente, from ASERG/DCC/UFMG. For more info, see Understanding Code Smells in Elixir Functional Language and the associated code repository.

Additionally, the Security Working Group of the Erlang Ecosystem Foundation publishes documents with security resources and best-practices of both Erlang and Elixir, including detailed guides for web applications.

Writing documentation

Elixir treats documentation as a first-class citizen. Documentation must be easy to write and easy to read. In this guide you will learn how to write documentation in Elixir, covering constructs like module attributes, style practices, and doctests.

Markdown

Elixir documentation is written using Markdown. There are plenty of guides on Markdown online, we recommend the one from GitHub as a getting started point:

Basic writing and formatting syntax

Module Attributes

Documentation in Elixir is usually attached to module attributes. Let's see an example:

defmodule MyApp.Hello do
  @moduledoc """
  This is the Hello module.
  """
  @moduledoc since: "1.0.0"

  @doc """
  Says hello to the given `name`.

  Returns `:ok`.

  ## Examples

      iex> MyApp.Hello.world(:john)
      :ok

  """
  @doc since: "1.3.0"
  def world(name) do
    IO.puts("hello #{name}")
  end
end

The @moduledoc attribute is used to add documentation to the module. @doc is used before a function to provide documentation for it. Besides the attributes above, @typedoc can also be used to attach documentation to types defined as part of typespecs.

Function arguments

When documenting a function, argument names are inferred by the compiler. For example:

def size(%{size: size}) do
  size
end

The compiler will infer this argument as map. Sometimes the inference will be suboptimal, especially if the function contains multiple clauses with the argument matching on different values each time. You can specify the proper names for documentation by declaring only the function head at any moment before the implementation:

def size(map_with_size)

def size(%{size: size}) do
  size
end

Documentation metadata

Elixir allows developers to attach arbitrary metadata to the documentation. This is done by passing a keyword list to the relevant attribute (such as @moduledoc, @typedoc, and @doc). A commonly used metadata is :since, which annotates in which version that particular module, function, type, or callback was added, as shown in the example above.

Another common metadata is :deprecated, which emits a warning in the documentation, explaining that its usage is discouraged:

@doc deprecated: "Use Foo.bar/2 instead"

Note that the :deprecated key does not warn when a developer invokes the functions. If you want the code to also emit a warning, you can use the @deprecated attribute:

@deprecated "Use Foo.bar/2 instead"

Metadata can have any key. Documentation tools often use metadata to provide more data to readers and to enrich the user experience.

Recommendations

When writing documentation:

Keep the first paragraph of the documentation concise and simple, typically one-line. Tools like ExDoc use the first line to generate a summary.

Reference modules by their full name. Markdown uses backticks (`) to quote code. Elixir builds on top of that to automatically generate links when module or function names are referenced. For this reason, always use full module names. If you have a module called MyApp.Hello, always reference it as `MyApp.Hello` and never as `Hello`.

Reference functions by name and arity if they are local, as in `world/1`, or by module, name and arity if pointing to an external module: `MyApp.Hello.world/1`.

Reference a @callback by prepending c:, as in `c:world/1`.

Reference a @type by prepending t:, as in `t:values/0`.

Start new sections with second level Markdown headers ##. First level headers are reserved for module and function names.

Place documentation before the first clause of multi-clause functions. Documentation is always per function and arity and not per clause.

Use the :since key in the documentation metadata to annotate whenever new functions or modules are added to your API.

Doctests

We advise developers to include examples in their documentation, often under their own ## Examples heading. To ensure examples do not get out of date, Elixir's test framework (ExUnit) provides a feature called doctests that allows developers to test the examples in their documentation. Doctests work by parsing out code samples starting with iex> from the documentation. You can read more about them at ExUnit.DocTest.

Documentation != Code comments

Elixir treats documentation and code comments as different concepts. Documentation is an explicit contract between you and users of your Application Programming Interface (API), be they third-party developers, co-workers, or your future self. Modules and functions must always be documented if they are part of your API.

Code comments are aimed at developers reading the code. They are useful for marking improvements, leaving notes (for example, why you had to resort to a workaround due to a bug in a library), and so forth. They are tied to the source code: you can completely rewrite a function and remove all existing code comments, and it will continue to behave the same, with no change to either its behavior or its documentation.

Because private functions cannot be accessed externally, Elixir will warn if a private function has a @doc attribute and will discard its content. However, you can add code comments to private functions, as with any other piece of code, and we recommend developers to do so whenever they believe it will add relevant information to the readers and maintainers of such code.

In summary, documentation is a contract with users of your API, who may not necessarily have access to the source code, whereas code comments are for those who interact directly with the source. You can learn and express different guarantees about your software by separating those two concepts.

Hiding internal modules and functions

Besides the modules and functions libraries provide as part of their public interface, libraries may also implement important functionality that is not part of their API. While these modules and functions can be accessed, they are meant to be internal to the library and thus should not have documentation for end users.

Conveniently, Elixir allows developers to hide modules and functions from the documentation, by setting @doc false to hide a particular function, or @moduledoc false to hide the whole module. If a module is hidden, you may even document the functions in the module, but the module itself won't be listed in the documentation:

defmodule MyApp.Hidden do
  @moduledoc false

  @doc """
  This function won't be listed in docs.
  """
  def function_that_wont_be_listed_in_docs do
    # ...
  end
end

In case you don't want to hide a whole module, you can hide functions individually:

defmodule MyApp.Sample do
  @doc false
  def add(a, b), do: a + b
end

However, keep in mind @moduledoc false or @doc false do not make a function private. The function above can still be invoked as MyApp.Sample.add(1, 2). Not only that, if MyApp.Sample is imported, the add/2 function will also be imported into the caller. For those reasons, be cautious when adding @doc false to functions, instead use one of these two options:

Move the undocumented function to a module with @moduledoc false, like MyApp.Hidden, ensuring the function won't be accidentally exposed or imported. Remember that you can use @moduledoc false to hide a whole module and still document each function with @doc. Tools will still ignore the module.

Start the function name with one or two underscores, for example, __add__/2. Functions starting with underscore are automatically treated as hidden, although you can also be explicit and add @doc false. The compiler does not import functions with leading underscores and they hint to anyone reading the code of their intended private usage.

Code.fetch_docs/1

Elixir stores documentation inside pre-defined chunks in the bytecode. Documentation is not loaded into memory when modules are loaded, instead, it can be read from the bytecode in disk using the Code.fetch_docs/1 function. The downside is that modules defined in-memory, like the ones defined in IEx, cannot have their documentation accessed as they do not write their bytecode to disk.